In the second segment, devoted to the
history of
randomness, we are moving now to the 20th
century.
And I have summarized the messages of the
20th century in six of them.
And we're going to go through them one by
one.
The first one is probably the most
astonishing change in
the view of the world in the 20th
century's quantum physics.
We have seen that according to
Laplace, physics was going to be fully
deterministic.
We've seen that many physicists at the
turn of the century
declare that physics had essentially no
future, or a future of precision.
In fact, things changed a lot.
already at the beginning of the century,
there were some ideas that the atomic
world would not behave according to what
the Newtonian physics would predict.
And quantum physics as we know it was
fully born in 1926.
For our concerns the main message of
quantum physics
is that there is intrinsic randomness in
elementary physics.
The most famous example probably is the
fact that one cannot
both specify position and momentum of a
particle with arbitrary precision.
And this is not due to a default of the
measurement,
is not something that is due to our
imprecision in the measurement.
It's highly that position and momentum of
not sharply-defined in nature.
We're going to speak a lot about these,
we'll go two lectures into it.
But this is the first big change in which
randomness starts playing again a role.
Where you would expect less, least, which
is physics.
The second change in the 20th century is
deterministic chaos.
Remember, again, the citation from Laplace
that the intellect he was speaking
about should be vast enough to submit all
the data to analysis.
Towards the second half of the 20th
century, we have got computers.
And these are perfect tool to submit a lot
of data to analysis.
And, here came the surprise.
In the 1970s, what is called the butterfly
effect, notice first, studied models of
the weather.
And what is the idea, the idea is
that even simple dynamics, simple
evolution in time,
deterministics, does no intrinsic
randomness at all, can
become unpredictable in practice in the
long run.
And this is because the dynamics is, as
they call
it, chaotic and it depends a lot on the
precision.
At which one can enter the, the figures in
a computer.
Again, we're going to speak during two
lectures about this topic, but
second point in which randomness,
unpredictability,
comes back in physics and in computing.
Third topic is chance and evolution.
this is a topic that we're not going to
deal with in this course.
One of the most outstanding
claims one can make is that the rise of
humans is
probably unpredictable, as far as science
goes, from the past.
So an observer in the past, may have had
really hard time predicting that we human
beings would appear.
And why is it so?
Well, because the present state of the
world, of, of the
Earth has been shaped by both macroscopic
and microscopic chance events.
Both these asteroids hitting the Earth,
climate changes that are hard
to predict, and also at the microscopic
level, mutations in the DNA.
The fourth change is beginning of lack of
trust in statistics.
Statistics nowadays are everywhere.
We find it in polls, in insurance, in
sports, in politics.
But still, even with all these great
tools, we are not fully in control.
For instance, one of the most dramatic
examples, earthquakes.
The statistics of earthquakes are pretty
well established.
They don't follow the bell curve.
they follow another kind of statistical
log, but it's a well-established log.
It's a power log.
And nevertheless, as we will know, it's
almost
impossible to predict where the next
earthquake will hit.
Similarly, when it comes to human
endeavors
like finance, or of course even worse
terrorism
and crime, these are activities that, for
which statistics can be applied, and are
applied.
But nevertheless, in some cases they fail
to predict what's going to happen.
These are now topic that is not going to
be dealt with in the course,
but it's a little bit of beginning of
pessimism of trying to find the limits of
what statistics can tell you.
The fifth, the fifth advance in the 20th
century
that I wanted to mention goes in the
opposite direction.
And it concerns the possibility of
predicting our own behavior, human
behavior.
The hope is from long ago, already 19th
century, there was a hope of recognizing
criminals.
For instance, by looking at their physical
traits,
at their calligraphy, different behaviors,
and
this proved to be essentially a failure.
Maybe also the idea of new behavior is
undesirable, because it would of course it
would lead to violations of privacy to be
in control of the life of other people.
And ultimately, one could be safe and say
oh, my behavior
is really unpredictable because it's my
own, it's my free will.
And these experiments in the 1980s done by
Libet challenging this vision,
at least partly.
They of course have raised a lot of
debates,
and we are going to deal with them in.
And finally the last development of the
20th
century I want to mention is information
theory.
The theory of how signals carry
information, and how information can be
processed.
This has been developed around the 1940s,
1950s,
by people like Alan Turing and Claude
Shannon.
Nowadays it is a very important field of
science.
A message I would take out of information
theory
here is that unpredictability and
randomness are not always bad.
In fact, sometimes can be used as a
resource.
And we are going to see in lectures two
and three a few
examples, where randomness helps in
computing and
of course helps in privacy and secrecy.
For instance in online transactions to
make
sure that advertizers don't get the
information.
So let me summarize the six steps, the six
messages
from the 20th century.
Quantum physics, there is intrinsic
ignorance in physics.
Deterministic chaos, even without going to
quantum physics, and even with
computers, there will be ignorance in the
long term for some phenomena.
Chance in evolution, we ignore how we got
here.
It would be very hard to have predicted
the rise of humans.
The limits of statistics have been
stated and five while unpredictability
creeps
in nature, our own decisions may be less
unpredictable than what we're expecting.
In com, in information theory, randomness
becomes
a resource for computing and for privacy.