Now in this second segment, we are
going to start considering the history of
randomness.
In this first part, we're go very fast
forward from the antiquity to the 19th
century.
Randomness has been used since antiquity
and
up today in these essentially three tasks.
For games, secrecy And divination, which
you may think is less frequent today,
but oddly it's not.
Games, well, they use randomness there
where ignorance implies fairness.
Like both players have an element of
ignorance, of unpredictability.
The game is fair if one of them.
can predict better than the other the game
is unfair.
Secrecy of course your want the adversary
to
ignore your message, to ignore your secret
codes.
The idea of divination is that if there is
some unpredictable phenomena for us,
someone or something must know.
And thus these being must be in control of
what's really happening.
And this is why divinations uses a
power beyond predictable phenomena to
interrogate the divinities.
Then mathematics begin.
There's not much mathematics in
divination, so
they kept all the games in secrecy.
In games Give rise to the first three
pieces of
probabilities until the final Probability
Theory in the 18th century.
The first person to somehow systematize
the theory of probability is Gerolamo
Cardano.
And you see the title
of his book, Liber de ludo aleae.
De ludo aleae means the game of dice in
Latin.
1564.
He was a gambler in fact, apart from being
a mathemetician and other things.
The next
[UNKNOWN]
of the development of the probability
theory
are some letters exchanged between Fermat
and Pascal.
About again, a problem of gambling that
was
submitted to them by one of their friends.
And Huygens, a few years later, writes
another book, another treatise,
again ludo aleae, you see there again the
game of dice.
About secrecy well the story's very long,
of course.
The frequency analysis on some kind of
cypher was initiated in ninth century
already by Al Kindi in the Arabic world.
And then mathematics again helped the
[INAUDIBLE]
Alberti in the Italian Renaissance to,
invent polyalphabetic cyphers.
And then the history goes.
Essentially by inventing and cracking
codes.
Until, let's say, let me put it as a
milestone, in 1883, Kerchkhoff's
principle, where this person stated that
the
protocol of secrecy must always be known.
There must be some secret code, but the
way we use this code must be publicly
known.
We come back to these topics later.
The next tool that appears in history is
the bell curve.
that everybody has seen in statistic.
The bell curve is a very frequent
manifestation of statistical behavior,
although not universal.
You probably all know that some
assumptions go into it,
and there are some statistical behaviors
that are not described.
By the bell curve.
This was discovered by two different
paths.
On the one hand, De Moivre discovered that
this is the limiting distribution when you
toss
many coins and you ask, how many heads and
how many tails appear in a given sequence?
Essentially the most probable sequences of
those.
Where there are half heads and half tails.
The other way of finding the bell curve in
history was through measurement errors.
People were studying in physics, notably,
the fact that when you make a
measurement, and you repeat the
measurement
many times, you get always slightly
different.
Results because of the imprecision of your
eyes or of your device, and again, how
well the errors distributed in this case
finally Laplace found out that these are
distributed
according to the bell curve.
It's interesting to mention in the context
of distribution of errors something that.
Is the power of statistics.
The statistics tend to give certainty in
the presence of uncertainty.
So we cannot know the exact result.
And statistics does not help you to know
the exact result, but it
will help you to quantify rigorously how
far you may be away from
the exact result.
In the sense, statistics is a
science about something that is
intrinsically answered.
And now, I already mentioned these
treaties of 1812 of
Laplace, Theorie analytique de
probabilite, and I want to read
in full the most famous quotation of the
group, because
it is very relevant for the discussions in
this course.
Laplace writes, in French, of course, but
we'll
read the English translation, we may
regard the
present state of the universe as the
effect
of its past and the cause of its future.
An intellect which at a certain
moment would know all forces that set
nature in motion and
all positions of all the items of which
nature is composed.
If this intellect were also vast enough to
submit this data to analysis, it would
embrace in
a single formula the movements of the
greatest bodies
of the universe and those of the tiniest
atoms.
For such an intellect, nothing would be
uncertain.
And the future, just like the past,
would be present before its eyes.
This is the position that has often been
called physical determinism.
And in fact we reach now, the end of the
19th century is very fast
overview of the history of randomness so
far and what are the stances there?
We have.
In physics, as we have seen, the idea is,
all is predictable.
And then we have statistics that will help
to cope with
measurement errors, and the basics have
been solidly established by them.
I want to finish with two quotations.
One is by August Comte.
The, founder of positivism, who wrote in
his book
The Positive Philosophy, something that
was falsified two years later.
Of all objects,
the planets are those which appear to us
under the least varied aspect.
We see how we may determine their forms,
their distances, their bulk, and
their motions, But we can never know
anything of their chemical or
mineralogical structure.
Few years later people found out that by
looking at spectral emissions
they can find out inside the chemical and
mineralogical structure of the stars.
So this confirms, seemed to confirm the
idea of LaPlace that everything would be
[INAUDIBLE].
In fact, a few years later at the
beginning of the twentieth century.
Michelson was giving a conference and then
wrote it in a book
the following sentence, The more important
fundamental laws and facts of physical
science
have all been discovered, and these are so
firmly established that the possibility
of their ever being supplanted in
consequence of new discoveries is
exceedingly remote.
He's also known to have quoted after
reason by Lord Kelvin
will say that the future of physics is
in the sixth deci-, decimal place of
perception.