After having considered the definition of
the randomness of
a sequence, let us now move on to the
second
possible definition, which is to approach
a problem by
defining the randomness of the process
that produces the sequence.
What is an unpredictable process?
Here is a black box.
It's producing one string of bits.
And the question I'm going to ask is can
anyone predict what is going to be the
next bit?
The ideal random process is such that the
probability of
the bit number n, knowing all the bits
that came before is just one half.
Independently of what came before.
It means again that the bit n is really
unpredictable, fully unpredictable.
Of course, again, here we keep the problem
that we saw
before, that can be very, very, very long
list of 0s.
The next million of bits, for instance,
may be 0s, may turn out to be 0.
But of course, another thing to be said is
that I've never seen a 1 ever in that
process.
I would simply not trust the process to be
random.
So I must have seen some once before and
then at least a one million
zero can happen although with very, very
rare probability.
Now it turns out for what follows that is
useful
to discuss the case where the boxes are
not too black.
I've already mentioned historical
introduction there is Kerckhoff principle,
later formulated again by Shannon, that
there shouldn't be security by obscurity.
Namely, that we try to get security, we
try to get
randomness, just by not revealing to the
world how our boxes work.
The idea being that at some point the
world
may discover how the box is working and if
we are trusting that nobody knows it while
people
do know it, then we are really in trouble.
So the idea is let the algorithm be known,
how
the box generates some random numbers, but
not a seed.
There is an initial seed, an initial
element of
secrecy of randomness that used to
generate those random numbers.
All these
notions will become clear in the lecture
two and more, even more, in lecture three.
But this is just to say that it's good to
move away from
the fully black box scenario to go to a
not too black box scenario.
Here's an example for instance although
it's
not a very practical one to generate
random.
The sequence would be drawn tfrom the
second letter of each line of a book.
And they don't tell you which book.
So you know that I'm going to take a book
from my library and generate
my random numbers using that book, but you
don't know which book I'm going to use.
The algorithm is specified but the seed,
which is the book is not.
And of course it's unpredictable if you
can't guess which book I'm going to use.
But if you can guess it then.
If you can guess the seed, then there is
no more randomness there.
This is what is called pseudo-randomness.
Pseudo-randomness is when even a
mechanical algorithm, mechanical or
mathematical,
I mean, it can be run by a computer is
used.
You can use mathematical functions, for
instance, some divider.
You know, it's not easy to guess a
remainder of a division.
And this is used sometimes to generate
randomness.
Again, we are going to see some examples
in the coming lectures.
Or what happens often in computers
is that you can just take the last pieces
of the clock of the computer and
scramble them a little bit, but in a,
again, the way these are scrambled is
known.
And what is the seed, the seed is the
precise instant, key is touched.
I cannot monitor my fingers to touch the
the, the, the key
at a precise moment down to microseconds.
Why is it called pseudorandomness?
Well, nothing is really random here, but
it's unpredictable for someone who does
know this.
Again, that's the notion of
pseudorandomness that is pretty important.
Now, the question you may ask is well, is
it really true what I just said?
Because at the end of the day, the person
outside,
let's say the adversary or whoever wants
to guess this
randomness, knows the algorithm and sees
the production of the
algorithm, sees the random numbers that
are coming out of that.
Can't you guess the seed from this
information.
And the answer is, most of the time, yes.
In fact the seed can be
inferred by observing the process.
So then where is the randomness.
Well If things are well done, this will
be, again, well defined in the
coming lectures, this inference, the seed
can
be guessed only with high computational
power.
So only if you are very powerful in
computing, more than anyone else, you can
try to extract the seed by observing the
random numbers that are being produced.
All, all these preparation leads me to a
very frequent
definition of what a random process needs.
A process is random
if it is unpredictable at least with
limited computational power.
And this limited computational power is
something that is used a lot.
We are going to see, especially lecture
two and also lecture three
how this notion comes in.
First you can have a more black box
definition.
You can come back to the black box
scenario and you can
say that the process is random if it is
predictable at all.
Even with unlimited computational power.
This would be a much stronger definition
of randomness
So let me finish by putting together at a
glance
the two definitions, the random sequence
and the random process.
The random sequence captures the idea of
no pattern in the sequence.
We don't want to have pattern in the mode
of regularities you worked with.
No structure there.
If you use only the finishing base on
random sequences, your sequence may not be
secret.
What does it mean?
It means that your sequence might have
been produced
years ago, copied many times and handed
over to you.
Many people can, can have a copy.
Whereas, of course, later we're going to
see, if you discuss whether
the process is random, then you trust the
process is producing randomness there,
under your eyes.
Nobody else with a copy.
In practice, the randomness of a sequence
is uncomputable
and you have to put a little bit of trust.
You have to trust a finite battery of
tests.
You do some statistical test, you check
some things and saw some of these ideas.
Like, you could check that the number of
0s and number of 1s are roughly the same.
The number of 00, 01, 10, 11, are roughly
the same and so on.
So, but you stop.
And you trust that this battery of tests
has given you enough confidence that the
sequence is behaving in a random way.
In comparison, a random process if as I
said before, if you are trusting
that randomness is being generated by the
process then it is secret.
It is random, it is there and if you keep
the
secrets from the adversary, then you have
it only for yourself.
Of course, a random process may
occasionally generate a simple sequence.
So, the two definitions are somehow not
always
tied to one another from random process.
As I said before, you can get a sequence
of 1 million zeros.
It is certainly not a random sequence,
according to
the, the definition of a random sequence
of multi
[INAUDIBLE].
In practice, also, you need some trust.
We need to trust the characterization,
mathematical
or physical of the process, of the device.
And with this I can summarize all that
we've learned in this first lecture.
I want you to convey various nuances of
the word unpredictable.
You have seen that randomness means lack
of predictability.
This is the main, of course, definition in
this course.
And I stressed also that the lack of the
information is not only the problem.
The problem is the often lack
of information implies lack of control, so
the
feeling of not being in control of what's
up.
The mathematical tools especially are of
course probabilities and statistics.
And the fair coin is the ideal case.
I want to repeat it here before problems
happen.
That the ideal case doesn't mean it is an
exemplary case, it doesn't mean
that all of randomness can be reduced to
the idea of a fair coin.
It just is the typical example we use and
the
one we target for in applications when
randomness is useful.
And finally we finish by considering
possible definitions
of randomness, and we wondered whether one
should
define the definition or that's how the
randomness
of a sequence or the randomness of a
process.
And again, something that would be
important in the future to remember is
that any verification of randomness
requires
here or there some element of trust.
With this we finish our first lecture,
thank you and see next time.