After this short introduction on the
course, let us start with the
very first lecture, in which I will
introduce the basics of randomness.
Here is the Plan of this Lecture.
The general title if you want or the
general message is to introduce the
various nuances of unpredictable of this
word that will stay with us all the time.
And in the first segment of the lecture, I
will in fact define words.
I will define three words,
randomness, chance, and free will.
In the second and the third segment, I
will go rapidly through a history of
randomness.
First, in the from antiquity to nineteenth
century, and
then in the twentieth century some changes
have happened there.
In the fourth segment that we introduced a
fair coin,
which is usually the idea, the exemplary
model, for randomness.
And in the last two segments five and six,
I was
spent time defining the the notion of
randomness in two different ways.
First segment is about these three words
that
will come up very often during this
lecture.
The first word of course is Randomness.
What does randomness mean?
It means Lack of predictability.
First example, as I said we are going to
see the
[UNKNOWN]
later is the coin tossing.
As we all know we have ignorance of the
result of each toss.
And this leads to a, lack of pattern in
the sequence
degenerator, normally, because sometimes a
sequence generated could have some
pattern.
Another example is polling, obviously
sample from a population.
The goal is
[INAUDIBLE]
ignore which item will be picked, so that
we cannot base
our selection on some other criteria that
would buy us some thing.
And important notion is also that, of
Single events vs statistics.
So, what is unpredictable of single events
quite
often, the statistics will be predictable
will be known.
So, there is some regularity there, we can
do science
with them but we cannot predict what will
happen in every single draw,
in every single toss of the coin, in every
single run of a process.
Second, what is Chance?
Chance usually refers to coincidence.
Coincidence, which means, concurrent
uncorrelated causes.
Let me explain these with an example of
doing something that,
for sure, we have met many, many times in
our lives.
In this novel by Thornton Wilder, The
Bridge of San Luis
Rey, it opens with an interesting case
where five people are walking
on a bridge at the moment when the bridge
collapses, and these five people fall to
their death.
The whole novel is about trying to find
out, if
there was a sort of divine plan big plan
for
these people to be there on the bridge
exactly the
moment it collapses, or if it all is pure
coincidence.
This is what we refer to as chance.
So, in a basic view,
each of these five persons had their own
reason to be on
the bridge, so there was a cause for them
to be there.
And of course it was a cause for the
bridge to collapse.
The roads were weak, or whatever other the
problem the bridge had.
And the only thing that was not
predictable was the fact that the bridge
would collapse exactly at the moment,
where
those five people would walk through it.
As I mentioned here with the topic of this
book,
often when we speak of chance, there is a
desire
in us human beings to try to see a deeper
cause beneath the coincidence, especially
when this coincidence is tragic.
This doesn't mean that this cause is
there, but we'd like to try to find it.
What is the ration with randomness?
Well, of course some of the causes can be
modeled as random processes but it
can also be the case that neither cause is
random.
Neither process is random.
And only the conjunction is unpredictable.
That's, the slight difference between
chance and randomness.
And finally free will, so free will
usually refers to our choices.
Especially in a, in a moral context.
An example would be if I said nobody's
looking at me in a shopping mall.
Should I steal this object?
Now, clearly what is the relation with
randomness here?
Clearly for me, the choice is not random.
I'm not going to choose to steal or not to
steal by tossing a coin.
This decision would be based, on my
principles, on
my values, on my religion, or whatever
they see or
my vision of society, or my desire for
comfort
if I choose to steal, whatever other
principle it is.
I'm not going to choose at random.
However if you don't know me and you see
me
there you don't know which decision I'm
going to take.
So, my behavior is unpredictable for you,
for someone who, doesn't know me.
In this sense even
the behavior of freewill look random to an
observer who is not familiar with the
person.
What all these notions have in common is
the idea of Lack of information.
We lack some information, and as a
consequence
very often, lack of information implies
lack of control.
You're not in control of what's happening.
This goes with the examples.
I don't know exactly how the coin is going
to be tossed, even by my fingers.
So, I can't predict the outcome.
For chance, I can't imagine all that is
happening around me and may affect me.
Something
I don't know, like some car accident in
the street,
something that doesn't depend on me but
can affect my life.
And I also can't predict the behavior of
others.
So this is the crucial issue, lack of
information is
normally the cause of randomness and all
these related notions.
Now, as you see, we could be speaking of
many things in this course.
And here I'm going to show you what we are
going to
deal with and what unfortunately, we don't
have time to deal with.
So we're going to deal with,
the Mathematical definition of randomness,
which as
you are going to see in this lecture is
not at all trivial.
We're going to deal as randomness as a
resource, as something positive.
It would be very frequent that
unpredictability
is in fact something good rather than bad.
Then we're going to deal with sources of
randomness in the physical world.
That we'll say more about this later, and
then of course in the following lectures,
and finally we will discuss something of
the, the take of science on free will.
Among the many things we're not going to
deal with, there is, Chance in biological
evolution.
serious Statistics and decision making.
Of course, a little bit of statistics
here, here
and there, but this is not a course about
statistics.
We're not going to deal with Predictions
in finance, politics, force, and other
human activities.
We're not going to deal with the topic of
Destiny, fate, that I hinted to at the
beginning.
that of course is a dominant topic in
philosophy and in literature
worldwide with a sort of full study there.
We're not going to offer it.
And also, we're not going to deal with
religions and how someone who has a
religion view can consider randomness and
free
will in a context of all powerful God.
Well, of a universe that repeats itself
regularly.