Let us now consider our first example of a
random process, which will
be the typical process or the ideal
process, which is the fair coin.
Here's the definition of what I'm going to
call the Fair coin.
Fair coin is any object that can take two
values.
There will be labeled 0 and 1, it's called
a bit.
This is the alphabet.
The alphabet is
binary, two values, 0 and 1, head or tail.
Up or down.
Another part of the definition of fair
coin is that each
single run, single toss of the coin must
be fully unpredictable.
And third characteristics of the several
runs are uncorrelated.
What happens in the second run does not
depend on what happened in
the first, and of course, what is going to
happen in the third.
The fair coin, it's an ideal
resource for randomness.
I have to stress that it is not an
exemplary resource or universal resource,
is not that everything that is random can
be reduced to a fair coin.
And I mentioned earlier earthquakes.
Earthquakes cannot be modeled by fair
coins.
Nevertheless, it's the typical example.
And again as a resource, it can be the
ideal case.
So mathematically, the fact that a single
run
is truly unpredictable is translated by
fact that the probability of having zero
must be the same of the probability of
having one, is one half.
So that if you are asked to guess, if it
is
going to be zero or one, you really have
no clue.
As a consequence of the fact that
several answers are uncorrelated, the
probability of any
sequence is just the product of the
probability for, of the result for each
dose.
For each run.
And since the problem is one half all the
time, every sequence
of n runs have probability 1 over 2 to the
power n.
You see an interesting relation that we'll
discuss later, in fact probably in lecture
three.
about between the number of runs, the
number of bits and the probability.
In this case, the you obtain the number of
bits by taking the logarithm
in base two of the probability with a
minus sign in front.
This logarithm will appear many times in
the future.
Before continuing with the fair coin, I
want to
say that the alphabet is not really
creating though.
In the title here I have that one die is
equal
to 2.6 coins, so what is a fair die for
instance?
Why I am not, I am using a coin instead of
a die?
Well a die would change from the fair coin
just by the alphabet.
Now the alphabet of a die as you all know.
Has six values instead of two.
For the rest is the same, a single run,
that you call it
a cast in English, should be fully
unpredictable, and several runs should be
uncorrelated.
Now why I am saying that this is
essentially equivalent to a coin.
Okay, here are first the probabilities,
the single run, the probability of getting
the result one is the same as getting
results two, three, four, five,
six, is one over six.
And since there are some uncorrelated in a
sequence of n
runs, you get the probability 1 over 6 to
the n.
And now how do you get bits out of that?
Well, again you take the probability, but
instead of you take the probability,
the, the logarithm, sorry, in base 2 And
you get what?
You get that the, the number of bits is
proportional to the number of casts of the
die, times a number,
which is the logarithm of ba, in base 2 of
6, 2.58.
So you see that the number of bits and the
number of casts of
the die are essentially the same, up to a
number, up to a constant.
And this is a general rule.
So if you have an alphabet of size A, you
just get bits
by multiplying the number of casts, the
number of throws, the
number of runs, by the logarithm in base 2
of A.
So from now on, unless otherwise
specified,
I will only consider coins, but bits.
An interesting topic is a statistics of
sequences of bits.
Here, imagine that you take your coin, you
toss it n times.
And you these as a random process that is
equivalent
to the following, write all possible lists
of of n bits.
Of pieces of paper put them on, in an arm,
shake the arm, and draw one at random.
Of course we know already that each
sequence of length n will be
drawn with the probability, the same
probability 1 over 2 to the n.
And see what can happen in this, in this
particular statistical process.
In the end, there is only one sequence
that consists of all zeros.
So, the probability of getting all zeros
is just 1 over 2 to the n.
In the end,
there are n sequences.
Where they're at least 1, 1, and n minus 1
zeros.
So the probability of seeing 1, 1, and n
minus
1 zeros is n times 1 over 2 to the n.
And so on.
So, how many sequences with the k 1s and n
minus k zeros out there, n choose k.
So the probability of finding n minus k 0s
and k 1s
is n choose k times 1, all over 2 to the
n.
If you study the mathematics of these
numbers, you find
that the sequence will be half 0s and half
1s.
Are the most numerals.
And here is the number, I've written it
there, is n, choose n over 2, which is
very, very close in the limit of large N
to 2 to the n, but 2 to the
n is the total number of sequences.
This means that long sequences
almost certainly, we'll have n half zeroes
and n half ones.
Of course there is still in the arm,
with the only sequence with all zeroes,
but essentially
all the sequences will have probability
one half of
0 and one half of one, compatible with
statistics.
The next question is the statistics within
a sequence.
So now you have drawn your sequence out of
the urn.
And you want to see inside this sequence,
how
many strings of some number of beats are
there.
For instance, in the first line of
these lights, I've highlighted seven bit
strings.
There is a rule of thumb that, there was
proof I'll show in the next slide.
That essentially all the strings that are
sufficiently short should
appear in a sequence of length n.
Let's go for an example.
So let's suppose that n is only 4096.
How many zeroes and ones do you expect?
Well, you expect more or less half zeroes
and half ones.
And the length, these are the sequences,
the strings sorry of length one, 1 bit.
And if you do the statistics again, the
proof would be in the next line.
You find that indeed, you expect for a
fair coin 2084
0s, and just as many 1s, with fluctuations
of only more or less 32 units.
Now how many two bit sequences do you
expect?
0001, 10 and 11?
You, again the, the calculation is simple,
you find, you would expect 512 of each,
with fluctuation of plus or minus 20.
Again pretty clear.
All of them must appear, and all of them
more or less in the same number.
Three meets three, 170 plus or minus 12.
And so on.
I have the, the four bit strings, 64 plus
or minus 8 when does this stop.
It stops around eight.
The sequences of eight bits, the strings
of
eight bits, you expect each of one to
appear
twice plus or minus two.
It means that some of them might not
appear at
all, some of them might appear four or
maybe five times.
And indeed, there is a calculation that it
would show that my rule of thumb is
correct.
This is the proof of those statements.
I will not go through it.
If you're interested in it, pause and read
the slide.
Otherwise, for myself I move on.
Now we can state something that I like to
call the randomness dilemma.
Take the string 00000, all 0s.
Clearly, it does not look random.
Pick another string that I've written
there, same length.
It does look random.
Nevertheless, for a fair coin, they're
equally probable to be drawn.
So,
the question is how to define randomness.
We want to define randomness from the
probabilities, from the
statistics, because that is the
mathematical description we have of them.
But we see that the statistics seem to be
a
bit ambiguous here, the same probability
for those two sequences.
So, we want also the definition that
captures what we do believe intuitively
random to mean.