We have just seen that it is not
easy to define randomness starting from
the statistics.
Let us now consider the first possible
definition that has been proposed.
it is the definition of randomness of a
sequence.
The idea of randomness of a sequence is
based on a
notion, that is called Kolmogorov
complexity in the name of Kolmogorov.
Who was one of the most important
theorists in probability
of the 20th century, also called
Algorithmic complexity.
And this refers to the complexity of a
sequence
like the sequence of beats that we have
seen before.
The definition is the following.
The complexity of a sequence is the length
of the shortest algorithm that can
generate it.
The shortest set of instructions that can
Let's put it into practice
with the two sequences I showed before.
Here is the first sequence, all zeros.
The algorithm is pretty simple.
It's just one line.
Print a list of 16 zeros.
Take the other sequence that looked more
random, and, okay, here is a possible
algorithm.
Of course, again, written in English.
All these notions should be formalized in
some formal language.
Print twice a one followed by two zeros.
You see that these sequence of three beats
one, zero,
zero appears twice, so it could compress a
little bit.
After that, I can't compress much more.
I don't see any structure, so I have to
say then print five
1, one 0, two 1, two 0.
You see that the second algorithm, the
second
set of instructions, is longer than the
first.
And in this sense, Kolmogorov complexity
of the second
sequence is higher than the complexity of
the first.
This not unclearly captures the idea that
randomness is lack of
pattern, that when something is random, it
should be hard to describe.
Based on the definition of Kolmogorov
complexity, a
Swedish mathematician Martin-Lof, defined
algorithmic randomness in 1966.
The definition Martin-Lof is very
technical, but later developments have
shown that it is equivalent in many
realizations.
To the following two statements, that are
themselves equivalent.
So a sequence is random
if, first possible definition.
It passes all possible statistical tests.
The statistical tests are made with a fair
coin as the ideal case.
So imagine you check all possible
statistical criteria.
Satisfied by the statistics of a fair
coin?
And then you check that your sequence has
those statistics.
The second possible definition, this is
the
one most inspired by Kolmogorov
complexity, is that
a sequence is random if it cannot be
produced by a program shorter than itself.
So these are sometimes called that the
sequence is incompressible.
It says clearly the sequence of all zeros
is not random.
Because it can be, you can type as many
zeros
as you want and it is captured in a very
short algorithm.
Another object that is not random in this
context is digits of by, they look random.
They look, there's no order, there's not
much structure there.
But they can be described by saying I am
the 15th digit of pi.
I am the 125th digit of pi and so on.
So these are not random
in the sence of Martin-Lof's.
This definition of randomness has a
problem when it comes to computing it.
The Kolmogorov complexity is, in fact,
un-computable.
These are very interesting notion, in that
in mathematics there are un-computable,
undecidable statements or quantities, is
related to Gödel's theorem.
Is one of the most important notions in
mathematics of 20th century.
So I want to spend a little bit of
time showing to you that Kolmogrov
complexity is un-computable.
First of all what does it mean?
It's not that it is difficult to compute,
it's
just that there's no consistent way of
assigning number.
There is no consistent way of defining the
shortest algorithm.
I will show a sort of formal proof later,
but let me relate it to a paradox.
It's called Berry's
paradox, attributed to a guy called Berry,
was a librarian
probably first written down in a book by
Bertrand Russell.
That's the written hypothesis, that a
similar to
the one of the shortest algorithm, that
positive integer
numbers can be ordered by the smallest
number
of English words needed to describe each
of them.
So, the algorithm.
An algorithm written in English words.
Then consider the following sentence.
You have to think a little bit of this,
it's a bit
tricky, but once you read it a couple of
times it becomes clear.
Take the following sentence.
The smallest positive integer that can not
be defined in less than N English words
and you can then describe this by 13
English words.
So if N is larger than 13, let's say 15, I
have a paradox.
Let me go through it again.
I listed, ideally, that's what's
impossible to do, all the
numbers by the number of English words
need to define them.
At some point, there must be a number that
needs at least 50 words to be defined.
This will be the smallest positive integer
that cannot be defined in less than
15 English words.
And this sentence is less than 15 English
words.
So we have a paradox.
This shows that there's no way of listing
numbers, in terms
of the smallest number of English words
needed to describe them.
Now let's go to the proof, a bit
more formal, the same proof of Kolmogorov
complexity.
So, let's suppose a Kolmogorov
complexity is computable.
So there is a function, K of s.
That for any string s that you
give to this function computes the
Komolgorov complexity.
Here's your number that quantifies the
The length of the shortest algorithm.
Okay, then let's use this function.
Here's an algorithm.
Take as a value of k, Called k0 as an
input.
And then it generates many lists.
Starts generating the list of length 1,
well, not many of them, 0 and 1.
Then, generates a list of length 2, 00,
01, 10, 11.
And so on.
For every length generates all the list,
and then
you compute the Kolmogorov complexity of
each of these lists.
Again, that's the assumption.
We can compute it.
And the Algorithm does following.
Assume as your Kolmogorov complexity
exceeds the
value k0 you put in at the beginning.
You output the list and stop.
In words, what does that box do?
Well, that box generates a complex string.
Generates a string, S, with complexity at
least k0.
That's what it's supposed to do.
And now let's call it U in
whichever formal language, in whichever
computing language.
The length of these blocks of this
algorithm.
What do I need, in addition to that?
Well, I need to input my k0, and to read
the list.
Now inputting k0, it requires log k0
reads.
K0 is is a number.
And remember that you take the log 2 of
any number, you
get the number of beats in which this
number can be written.
So the total length of this operation is u
plus the log of k0.
And it's
supposed to generate a sequence with
complexity larger than k0.
But this means by definition that, by
assumption of Kolmogrov
complexity, that log of kz or plus U, must
be larger than kz or white.
Because k0 is the length of the shortest
algorithm that can
generate a sequence s and now you see that
this is wrong.
If you know, you should know,
a little bit of functions, a logarithm is
a very slow varying function.
It certainly varies much slower than
linear, than k0.
So it is not true that log of k0 is always
larger than
k0, even if you displace it a little bit
by a constant U.
So here's the contradiction.
There cannot be a function, so what is the
assumption here?
You see that the assumption was that there
is a function Ks that computed Kolmogorov
complexity.
And there is the assumption, we got a
contradiction.
Therefore, the Kolmogorov complexity is
not computable.
There is no function that can compute that
number.