[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hello.
Welcome to this course on Unpredictable
Randomness, Chance, and Free Will.
We are going to be together for eight
weeks.
Let me first share with you some technical
points.
every lecture will be divided in four to
six, four to six segments.
And at the end of the segment, we're going
to put some
references and some links for you to
click, and to deepen your knowledge.
Okay I have to say that,
this list is not a exhaustive, and
sometimes I
don't fully agree with what's written in
these references.
But, I let you build up your own knowledge
by surfing on the Internet.
That's ultimately the internet module, you
can use this tool.
concerning evaluation, we are going to
have
in-video quizzes in most of the segments.
These ones are not marked.
It's just for you to check if you are
following what I'm saying.
And we are going to have no homework
but two tests.
The first test at the end of Lecture Four.
And the second test at the end of the
course.
So at the end of lecture eight.
The test will be multiple choice
questions,
and the passing grade will be 50%.
The statement of accomplishment 85%.
for your questions and discussions there
will a forum as is usual in Coursera
that will be managed by myself and by my
two teaching assistants Melvin and Yulsa.
This is
all that I wanted to say for the technical
things, really very simple.
So now let us move to the interesting
part, to the content.