Hello, welcome to the seventh lecture in
which we will
finally discuss this topic of intrinsic
randomness from quantum physics.
And also we'll finish by stressing its
practical uses.
Here is the plan of our lecture that will
be focused on this notion of violation
of Bell inequalities that are the proof
ultimately of intrinsic randomness.
In the first segment,
I will discuss the notion of
pre-established agreement, that
is, the opposite, if you want, of
intrinsic randomness.
Then, in the second and third segment, I
will
discuss this theorem by John Bell and its
implications.
And in the fourth segment, I will discuss
quantum information, which are the
applications of intrinsic randomness.
There are only four segments here but they
are pretty dense so stay
with me.
We start with the pre-established
agreement.
Remember what we saw in the previous
lecture about black boxes.
We have one box in which we can put an
input.
In that case it was the difference of
length in a, a
[UNKNOWN] thermometer, and we get an
output plus 1 or minus 1.
And we were asking whether, what is inside
this
box can be certified to be quantum or even
can be certified to be intrinsically
random.
And as you remember, we found out that
this cannot
be done, because in the box, there could
be a simulator,
someone, or even a computer, who has the
instruction how
to react to the input and how to produce
the outputs.
Now I want to extend a little bit just
to notice that these instructions in
particular could be predetermined.
So a way
to generate this particular probability
distribution would be
to have decided it in advance, whatever,
what
to do for every call, for every time an
input is put and an output is given.
And for every value of delta l.
Of course, it's not very economical to
have such a long list.
It's easier to have a sort of random
number generator here, but this is
certainly possible.
So this user or
this computer could just have a list that
says in the first
call, if delta l is equal to 0, you should
output plus 1.
If delta l is equal, let's say, to lambda
over 10, you output plus 1.
If it's lambda over 5, you output minus 1,
and
so on for all possible values of that
delta l.
And then as a similar instruction, but
different in values here, for the
second call, for the third call, for the
fourth call, and so on.
And if the box
is queried many times, ultimately the
promise is
that all these will give the correct
statistics.
Okay, for instance as you see here,
whenever delta l is equal to
0, the output must be always plus 1, and
here is what I put.
So this is the important point to stress,
that whenever
such a simulation is possible, the output
may be predetermined.
Maybe it is not, but it is certainly
possible that it is predetermined.
Now let's see what happens if we try to
do the same, these pre-established
strategies, with two parties.
And this time, I will only use two
inputs instead of the whole possibilities
of delta
l in order to simplify the argument.
The argument works already with two
inputs.
So here we have Alice, in her lab.
And she has one of these pre-established
strategies.
If x is equal to 0 or if x is equal to 1
in the first call out, plus 1.
In the second call, if x is equal to 0,
you output minus
1, if x is equal to 1, we output plus 1,
and so on.
Bob has a similar list.
Importantly Alice and Bob may share the
other persons' list.
So Alice and Bob might have met in advance
and have agreed upon a strategy.
So now Alice in addition to having her
list.
She may also know Bob's list and similarly
Bob may also know Alice's list.
Again, because they came together,
that's why it's called, pre-established
agreement.
That it's pre-established because all of
the values are
guessed in advance, and is agreement
because
Alice and Bob share each others' lists.
So what can you do with pre-established
agreement?
What kind of games, if you want?
You can simulate, you can win.
But clearly a game that you can win is
this one.
If you are given the same input, given the
same output.
How do you do that?
Well just take identical lists.
And clearly here, you see that if,
for, let's take a non-trivial case.
If Alice receive 0 and Bob receive 0, they
both output minus 1.
If Alice receive 1 and Bob receives 1,
they both output plus 1.
And that's it.
In fact, it is pretty obvious.
You just share the same list of
instructions,
then you would behave exactly in the same
way.
Now, this is not purely academic, this is
done almost every day, for instance, take
an example
in which two agents of the same company
are going to the stock market.
And bidding for something.
But what they have to bid for depends on
whether a given
party wins the elections, or the other
party gives the wins the elections.
So, they are the agents are in different
locations, in different stock exchange
buildings, and they have to wait for the
information, say which party has won.
And this
would be the input, x and y, and upon of
receiving this input,
well, if party number one has won, they
sell, if party number two
has won, they buy.
This is a very natural situation.
Is there something you cannot do with
shared agreement?
And the answer is yes, there are
things they cannot do with pre-established
agreement.
Take the following
game, Alice and Bob should output the
same,
always the same, systematically the same,
this seems trivial.
Unless in one case, unless both receive
the input 1.
In this case they have to output
different.
So see what happens.
Suppose that Alice has decided, okay, what
she has is fixed.
So here for instance, you decided the
output plus 1.
Now, here, Bob also outputs plus 1, but
here what,
what Bob has to do depends on x.
You see if x is equal to 0, then Bob has
to output plus 1.
If x is equal to 1, however, Bob has to
output minus 1, because
when x is equal to y is equal to 1, they
have to output differently.
So here you see that, on Bob's side, the
instructions are not complete.
In order to win this game, Bob needs to
know something about Alice,
and, concretely, about the actual input of
Alice.
What is the input that Alice received?
Now, how do you solve this game, this
problem, classically?
Alice should call Bob.
Should send a message to Bob, and tell him
I received X equals 0.
ha, Bob knows this, and therefore act
accordingly.
Okay, suppose now that we leave Alice and
Bob
in peace, and we have back our black
boxes.
We run these black boxes, we'll put
inputs, get outputs, put inputs, get
outputs.
And we notice that these black boxes
achieve successfully this game,
same output unless x is equal to y is
equal to 1.
So what do you conclude?
You see these, this is unquestionable.
That's the statistics you observe.
Don't go too fast!
There is a necessary conclusion.
The necessary conclusion is that at least
one
of the outcomes was not pre-established.
Remember that before, it was Bob's outcome
that needed an input.
It could be Alice's outcome.
But one of the two, at least, or maybe
both, are not pre-established.
That's necessary conclusion.
Now, of course, since we are accustomed to
the
classical world, you would say, oh, then
these boxes are
signalling, one of the boxes is sending a
signal to
the other, and that's how they can win
this game.
But, what happens if you're in a situation
where no signal can have been sent.
Is there such a situation?
There is.
As you know, no signal should propagate
faster than light,
so if these two boxes are very far apart,
a
signal from x to b, as is drawn here in
the slide, should travel faster than
light, and this is impossible.
Now, this is exactly, however, or similar
to what two
quantum particles, separated by the large
distance, can do.
Two quantum particles can win this game,
or
aproximately win this game, I'll come back
to this
later, at a distance such that if you want
to explain what you see by a signal.
You need the signal to travel faster than
light, which is essentially impossible in
our universe.
So, how do you explain it?
Well, this is the question we are going to
see in the next part.