Now that we've stated and demonstrated
Bell's theorem let us consider its
implications.
First of all, little bit of history of
this concept.
A lot has been written on these.
I will just sketch it and then you
can go online and find whatever you find
suitable.
The idea that the outcomes of measurements
are
not pre-established was an early dogma of
quantum theory.
Early 1920s, 1926 when quantum theory was
firmly established,
most physicists accepted it especially
Niels Bohr was very vocal
about this but whole the young generation
and essentially followed him.
Only Einstein, Schrödinger, maybe de
Broglie, and a few
others, but not many, did not like this
idea.
And they were hoping to save
determinism with something that came to be
called local hidden variables and
sometimes written LHV.
Now what is the, what are these local
hidden variables?
Nothing as that pre-established but one of
the problems at the time was that it
was not formulated in a clean operational
way like the one I did in this lecture.
Like the one we have been, we have been
doing in physics for a
couple of decades now.
It was rather abstract and sounded
philosophical.
It had some variables that are hidden.
And indeed, until John Bell came in onto
the scene, the debate between local hidden
variables and let's say, no
pre-established, so intrinsic
randomness remain purely conceptual.
Some people like local hidden variables.
They are free to believe in them.
Some others don't like local hidden
variables.
They are free not to believe in them and
to believe in instrinic randomness.
It's a matter of just coffee table
discussion.
John Bell was apartism initially of the
hidden variable model, or at least he
tried to write down an explicit model
that reproduces the prediction of quantum
theory.
After all, if it's possible to reproduce
the prediction
of quantum theory with such a model it
would
be nice to write down one and see how it
works.
And that's when he found out that it is
impossible to write down a local variable
model, because
he found the Bell inequality that shows
that the
predictions of quantum theory are not
compatible with pre-established agreement.
So really the, the, the, the first scam,
the orthodox scam, was right in a sense.
Einstein was wrong.
Now the story's not finished, because
when,
Bell wrote his inequality, even if quantum
mechanics has been successful
for decades, predicting many things, and
many experiments have been made, there
were no available data, that matched the
kind of data needed for a Bell test with
two separated articles being measured
almost simultaneously.
And collecting the statistics separately
for, for each particle.
So there was a need for a dedicated
experiment, not that many
people cared, because anyway, everybody
already believed in the absence of local
variables, but some people liked the idea,
liked the challenge, took it up.
In the 1970s, there was some attempts of
doing this experiment.
They were not conclusive, unfortunately.
The first conclusive attempt, the first
conclusive Bell test, is the one performed
by Alain Aspect and his coworkers in Orsay
in Paris in 1981 and 1982.
In fact, is a series of three tests.
What Alain Aspect and coworkers used were
two photons,
so, two particles of light, if you want,
sent
away from a central source to two
different locations
in their lab, and measured at these
different locations.
And since Orsay experiment, there have
been many,
many, many others, confirming the
violation of Bell inequalities.
I mentioned just two of them, why, because
they are famous.
Both in 1998 in Geneva,
the group of Nicolas Gisin managed to see
a violation
of Bell inequalities by photons that were
detected ten kilometers apart.
So really macroscopic distance and the
photons were sent
in optical telecom fibers installed by the
Swiss telecom.
So commercial fibers.
They just borrowed, the, the physicists
borrowed
the commercial fibers, they put the
photons into
them, and their detectors at the end, and
managed to see this violation of Bell
inequality.
Same year, essentially also same month,
the group of Anton
Zeilinger, then in Innsbruck, now he is in
Vienna, implemented for
the first time Bell's experiment where the
choice X and
Y, the inputs, were really chosen at
random in each run.
Since then, in the 21st century, so, from
the
year 2000 onward, there have been many,
many more tests.
Tests involving more than two photons.
Tests involving two ions, two atoms
separated.
One atom and one photon, and so on.
All of them confirming the predictions of
quantum theory that the Bell inequalities
have violated.
So let us stay within our universe for a
moment.
If the Bell inequality is violated, there
is no pre-established agreement.
So this means that the outcome of at least
one of the boxes did not pre-exist.
What can we conclude from that?
We can think, hey, there is a signal.
If there is a signal, the process can be
deterministic, as we have seen.
Remember the very first example we saw of
a
process that cannot be done with local,
with pre-established agreement.
If Alice sends to Bob the X, Bob can
have chosen in advance what to apply for
each X.
Or there is no signal.
And then the process is even worse.
It cannot even be deterministic.
It must be some really creation of
information on the spot.
Now to explain quantam exexperient with a
signal, as
I said before, the signal should propagate
faster than light.
And in fact, some recent theoretical
studies proved that
not only faster than light but at infinite
speed.
Which is really very hard to conceive.
I just want to convey a
little anecdote, even Newton did not
believe in infinite speed signals.
So when he realized, and it's written in
his book,
that his gravity theory implied that the
moon reacts immediately
to the earth, instantaneously, with
infinite speed, he clearly wrote,
this cannot be, but for the moment, I
cannot do better.
And indeed, it took until Einstein to find
out that
even gravity propagates at most at the
speed of light.
So you see,
something at infinite speed is not
something
that a physicist should be at ease with.
In fact, you may ask if this corresponds
to
our universe, something where it goes at
infinite speed.
But okay, let this debate aside.
So let us now come to our famous topic of
Intrinsic randomness.
Let us consider what kind of randomness
can we infer
if we assume that there is a signal or
that
there is no signal.
Before starting I need to make a
disclaimer.
Disclaimer is that the overwhelming
majority of physicists accept that
no signal is involved in quantum violation
of Bell inequalities.
So if I appear here to treat the with
signal and without signal options on the
same footing, it
is just because as you will see, at the
end of the day, for my message of
intrinsic randomness.
It doesn't really matter.
In both cases we are going to conclude
that there is a form of intrinsic
randomness.
However, I really want to stress that the
with-signal approach is accepted
only by very, very, few physicists, and I
am not one of them.
So let's start with it.
If there is a signal, as I said before,
the process could be deterministic.
Nevertheless, the outcomes
are still unpredictable for anyone who
cannot
read the signal, who cannot read the
communication.
Now we call that the wave of Bohm that
essentially
would be the mechanism responsible to
carry this signal around.
Or any similar mechanism is postulated to
be unobservable.
So here there is a form of intrinsic
randomness in the sense that if, indeed,
the object
that carries the signal, this infinitely
rigid ether that carries
an infinite speed signal, however crazy it
sounds, sounds pretty crazy.
If we cannot read it, if we cannot measure
it,
if we cannot assess it, then we cannot
predict the results.
Even if nature, if you will, a being
that could read that signal, would see
determinism.
Now without signal well, that's even
simpler for randomness,
the outcomes are unpredictable for anyone
in our universe.
Now, you may have heard that there is
something called the "Many-worlds"
interpretation of quantum physics.
I'm not going to enter into detail on what
it is, also, because
people, even the supporters of the
interpretation
sometimes differ on what exactly it means.
Essentially, this interpretation is a way
of recovering determinism
for an observer who would see many
parallel universes.
So the idea is that there are many
parallel universes,
each one apparently behaving at random,
but
on the whole scale, everything is
deterministic.
But again, here we are speaking of an
observer who can look over all possible
universes.
So my conclusion is that even if you're
willing to invoke either infinite speeds
or parallel universes in order to save
some form of determinism out there in
nature,
the violation of Bell inequalities implies
intrinsic
randomness for us users in our universe.
And remember that I don't think we can say
much more than that.
But remember that we always have to say,
is it random for whom?
And if you start asking, is it random for
our being?
That does not obey the laws of physics of
our universe.
So this is outside our universe, so
comtemplating many universes,
well, we cannot say much about that.
But in our universe, for you and for me
and for all human beings, the
violation of Bell inequalities of quantum
physics
implies intrinsic in the sense of
irreducible randomness.
A last point I want to make before moving
to quantum information
is that the violation of Bell inequalities
is what we call device independent.
For that I want to stress that contrary to
what I did in the previous lecture
I did not describe the devices inside the
boxes.
Remember, in the previous lecture, I have
beam
splitters, I have photons and neutrons and
so on.
Okay, here I didn't speak about beam
splitters, I didn't speak about
detectors, I just spoke of, there's an
input and there's an output.
That's the power of the Bell inequalities,
that
you don't have to specify how to do it.
Of course, If you have an experiment that
is in
a lab that you want to set up such an
experiment,
then you need to know a lot.
You need to know how to create what is
called quantum entanglement
between these two photons or two ions or
two atoms or whatever.
They must be created in a particular
configuration
with particular properties You need to
know which
beam splitters to use, which detectors to
use, how to align the beams and so on.
Yes there is a lot of technical skills
involved.
It's not plug-and-play.
It's not a Lego blocks.
But if you want to asses the violation of
Bell inequalities, if you
want to just check that there was
intrinsic randomness in that set up, this
can be done by any one of us with a little
bit of knowledge
of statistics, if you can compute
probabilities
and check the violation of Bell
inequalities.
So in this sense, the assessment of
intrinsic randomness is really
black box, or as we like to call it,
device independent.
We don't need to specify if it's photons
or atoms or ions,
what kind of measurement, what kind of
beam splitters or other devices are used
inside.
It can be assessed in a completely blind
way.