So, having seen that some abilities can be
achieved
with a pre-established agreement and some
others not, I'm going to present to you
the correct theorem that allows to
discriminate between the 2 possibilities.-
So here is our assumption.
It is the fact that for every
call, Alice and Bob in their box, in their
laboratory,
in their room, wherever they are, they
know how
to reply if they get the input 0 or 1.
And these numbers a0, a1, b0 and b1 are
always either plus 1 or minus 1.
So this is the assumption: the
per-established agreement means
that for each call, the 4 outcomes a0, a1,
the [UNKNOWN] 2 and b0,
b1, the 2 for [INAUDIBLE] are
predetermined.
They are preexisting.
They are already written somewhere or they
could be written somewhere.
In order to [UNKNOWN] theorem, we start
with simple algebra.
So here is again our assumption.
If you have these 4 numbers, if these 4
numbers are written somewhere on a piece
of paper or on 2 pieces of paper, it would
be possible to compute
the number S defined like that, is the
product of a0 and
b0 plus the product of a0 and b1 plus the
product of
a1 and b0 minus the product of a1 and b1.
It may be not natural why this number, but
it's certainly something you can compute.
And in fact it's very simple to compute
this number, because this number is either
plus 2 or minus 2 for all possible values
of a0, a1, b0, and b1.
Let us prove it.
By trivial algebra, you can regroup the
terms in a way that S is written
now in that way.
And now there are 2 possibilities.
Either b0 is equal to b1, or b0 is equal
to minus b1.
If b0 is equal to b1, the second term is
0.
The first term is just plus or minus 1,
whatever a0
is, times plus or minus 2, whatever b0 and
b1 are.
So this is plus 2 or minus 2.
And of course symmetrically, if b0 is
equal
to minus b1, it's the first term that is 0
and the second term that is plus or minus
1 times plus or minus 2.
So this particular number is a complicated
way to write plus 2 or minus 2 as a
function of a0, a1, b0, and b1.
Assuming that all these numbers are
predetermined.
Now we are facing a small problem, is that
in each call, Alice can choose only
one input, either x equals 0 or x equals
1.
And she will get only a0 or only a1, the
same for Bob.
So it is impossible for us to measure S on
each
call, because to measure S, we would need
All 4 numbers.
But what is interesting is that it is
possible
to measure the average of S over many
calls.
And this is because the average of a sum
is the sum of the averages.
If you don't find it obvious, just think a
little bit, and you will realize that it
is obvious.
For instance, the Average in a series of
exams,
of all your exams, of a class, you can
compute either the average per student and
then compute
the average of all of the class of that
number.
Or you can compute the average for each
exam and then again average of all the
students.
So the
average of S is the sum of the average of
a0b0 plus the
one of a0b1 plus the one of a1b0 minus the
average of a1b1.
And now, the average of a0b0 is nothing
else than the average of the product
a times b over all the cases where x was 0
and y was 0.
And these I think, are possible
experimental situations.
And so on for the others.
And now another observation.
This one is even more trivial than the
previous one, that
the average of S must be smaller than 2
for pre-established agreement.
Why?
Well, remember that S for pre-established
agreement is
either plus 2 or minus 2 all the time.
And if you take an average of a number
that can only be plus 2 or minus 2.
You cannot possibly go above 2.
So here's Bell's theorem.
Yes, the famous Bell's theorem is nothing
else than this.
It's that pre-established agreement.
implies that this number S on average must
be smaller than 2.
It's called Bell's theorem because the
first such inequality.
You see that this is smaller or equal, so
that's why it's
an inequality was derived by John Bell, an
Irish physicist, in 1964.
The presentation
I followed here is the one by Clauser,
Home,Shimony and Holt.
In 1969, it's called CHSH, by now it's the
most famous of these Bell inequalities.
What is important to stress, and I will
stress it a few
times, is that this average value of S is
a measurable number.
You put inputs, get outputs, and compute
averages.
So it's something you can check.
And now the
logical converse of Bell's theorem, so
just reversing, writing the not,
of, the negation, of the statement, is
that, if one would
would observe that S is larger than 2,
which is a
violation of the Bell inequality, because
S should be smaller than 2.
If you find that S is larger than
2, then pre-established agreement cannot
be the explanation.
And quantum theory
does predict a violation for suitable
experiments.
And the experiments once realized,
confirmed
the violation is there in nature.
Well, this is an important point.
So you can't only just check the theory.
You have to check that nature does it.
And again, it can be checked because this
S is a measurable number.
Here is an example.
Lets take our game that I discussed in the
previous segment.
The, the game where Alice and Bob have to
output the same.
Unless they both received the setting, 1.
So what is the ideal case?
The ideal case is that when x and y are 0
and 0, a and
b must be equal, so the product ab must be
+1.
Similarly, when x is 0 and y is 1, x and y
and y Is 0.
When x is 1 and
y is 1, a and b must be different.
So the problem might be minus 1.
Now plug these 4 numbers into our S value
and you find 4.
4 is larger than 2.
This confirms what we had already guessed
before with our more intuitive argument
that again, same output unless x is equal
to, y is equal to 1, cannot be achieved
with preestablished agreement.
I want to make a remark that something I
mentioned before, that quantum systems
cannot win this game perfectly.
So this kind of correlations, this kind of
statistics cannot be made even with
quantum physics.
But, quantum physics can reach in a
approximate version of this game, can
reach a value of S that is 2 times square
root of 2,
which is 2.83, which is a clear violation
anyway.
So now that we have the bending equality,
we don't need to win this game perfectly.
We can just check the inequalities
violated.
And, quantum physics, quantum theory can
violate the inequality only after 2.83.