The last segment of this lecture is a
short
introduction to the research field of
quantum information science.
Quantum information is maybe, first of all
a matter of attitude.
This is the attitude that many people have
had along the last century about quantum
physics.
And certainly, the attitude I was taught
quantum physics with.
It's a very predictive theory, you need to
know it, otherwise you're not a physicist,
but
you are essentially, you can forget about
understanding
it, because you cannot know both position
and momentum,
you cannot predict the outcome of a
measurement
with certainty, only the statistics, and
so on.
So it seems something, a pretty bleak
picture.
Of essentially giving up knowledge.
Well it is not, of course.
Quantum physics is a great discovery of
human spirit.
Now the attitude of quantum information is
rather hey, look up
they are, there is a source of real
randomness out there.
So we can use it.
Let's stop complaining, let's stop whining
that we cannot know position and momentum.
If we cannot know position and momentum,
we can get randomness out of it.
Let me give a brief overview of what
quantum information is.
There essentially 2 big, big fields and
then a lot of other
things that I cannot tell you now because
we cannot go so specialized.
One of the main tasks of
quantum information is called quantum
cryptography.
We know about this cryptography.
And in fact, the main help of quantum
physics
is to distribute a key for use in one-time
pad.
For some reason, quantum physics does not
help
for instance in protocols like RSA, in
public-key cryptography.
Another task is the generation of
secure random numbers, cryptographically
secure random numbers.
The idea of quantum cryptography
was discovered independently by Bennett
and Brassard
in 1984 and by Arthur Ekert n 1991.
And I will describe these 2 ideas shortly
later.
The present state of, of quantum
cryptography
is that essentially it's a regular
commercial product.
Then I see a little bit of development in
the academic world, but
in its basic configuration it, it has
already being developed up to the
point of being first a prototype and then
even now
probably you can buy it, if you have
security needs.
The other big chunk of quantum information
is quantum computing.
The main task of quantum computing is,
speed
up some protocols, and in particular, a
scary one
is that a quantum computer would be able
to factor integers faster than any known
classical algorithms.
Now if you remember that factoring
integers
is a crucial step in the security of RSA,
the public key cryptography.
If one is able to factor integers faster
than, than, than, than exponentials.
In fact, if [INAUDIBLE] in a polynomial
time then the RSA becomes insecure.
This is the main result of Peter Shor in
1994, it's called Shor's algorithm.
Okay, since of course, there have been
lots of developments and research and so
on.
But in terms of realization of a quantum
computer, the present status is still very
far away.
People are working on simpler, relevant
applications.
If you have heard of the...in the
press of some companies buying some
quantum computer.
It's still debated whether this is really
quantum.
Anyway, it's not a full quantum computer.
Those quantum computers cannot factor in
figures, but they can do something else
that is already a speed up over what you
can do with classical computing.
I'm not going to speak of quantum
computing anymore here.
I will focus now my little examples of
quantum cryptography, random number
generation, and the key distribution.
So here is a trusted random number
generator.
In fact, you know it already, it's our
beloved beam splitter.
So we have a source sending some
particles, typically photons.
For beam splitter, and then there are 2
detectors.
If the first detector clicks, the
transmitter detector
clicks, we call it a 0 now, and if the
reflected detector clicks, we call it a 1.
We have to recall that this is a trusted
random number generator in the sense that
these kinds of single particle devices do
not withstand a black box test.
If you don't trust the vendor and you just
see the statistics, one
half here, one half there, it
might have been generated by
computer-deterministic means.
So this means in other words, that you
have to characterize, both
as the producer and as the end user, you
must characterize the
source and the beam splitter, or trust the
source and the beam
splitter in order to be sure that this
device is generating randomness.
Now, this is not a big deal.
Remember that we have to do the same in
classical physics, for a
classical random number generator, we have
to do the same for the resistor.
In order to extract the randomness
from the resistor, we had first to check
that it behaves as a resistor should
behave.
So this is not a default of this.
This is just using quantum physics in a
sort of normal way.
Of course, thanks to Bell inequalities, we
can
use quantum physics in a more paranoid
way.
Here, if you generically run the numbers
using Bell inequalities, then a and b.
Are random,
even for the producer, even for the one
who has sold you the source and the 2
boxes, black boxes, provided of course the
Bell
inequality is violated and provided there
is no signalling.
So this box cannot be fully black, you
must trust that there is no radio inside.
Of course if the.
The vendor has put a radio here that
reveals to the
world or to the NSA the list of bits, then
the randomness
would be compromised.
But if there is no signal from this box to
the other, if you put the boxes
far apart, so that no signal can
propagate,
then this certifies randomness in a black
box scenario.
The fact that the users don't need to
characterize the devices is what I call
device-independent.
Another interesting feature here is that,
remember, we
have to assess min-entropies in order to
extract randomness.
Now, the min-entropy
is a function of the violation of Bell
inequality.
So if you observe the violation of Bell
inequality,
immediately you can say, How much is the
guessing probability?
How much is the min-entropy of that
source?
And a particular case I want to mention is
that if you would violate the Bell
inequality to
the quantum maximum of 2 square root of 2,
then both a and b are perfect fair coins.
Not uncorrelated, so each one depend a
little
bit on the other, but taken apart, each of
them is a perfect fair coin.
Now let's go to key distribution.
Again, there are 2 possible scenarios, one
using only
one particle, the other one using Bell
inequalities, 2 particles.
The BB84, Bennett and Brassard 1984
protocol that I'm not going to describe in
detail, but it essentially uses one of
these Mach-Zehnder interferometers, so a
version of it.
Between the lab of Alice that is the
source and
sent something and the lab of Bob who has
the detectors.
Now the idea here why quantum physics
helps is because measurement modifies the
observation.
And who is going to measure?
Well Eve.
Eve is the eavesdropper in the middle.
Who wants to get the information about
what is being sent by Alice.
But if Eve comes in and listens and tries
to
measure, get some information, Alice and
Bob will notice it.
So you see here how an idea
of quantum physics is, one of these weird
ideas that we
don't find very comfortable, like
measurement
modifies the observation, becomes an
advantage.
If measurement modifies the observation,
The
eavesdropper cannot measure without being
noticed.
Again, there's an element of trust here.
This is a one-particle device.
Alice and Bob need to characterize their
devices.
They need to know how the source works,
how the beam-splitters work, and so on.
Rebuild Bell.
Again, you can do it device independent.
That's the idea of Ekert, although the
idea of device independence is much later.
And in fact, I'm very happy to be one of
those who had these ideas.
But Ekert already in 1991, had the correct
intuition, namely that
if a Bell inequality is violated, the
results do not pre-exist.
So if Eve is listening out there, there's
just nothing to listen to.
There's nothing to learn.
The results do not exist.
The results are sort of created At the
moment of
the measurement in the locations of Alice
and
Bob that of course is supposed to be
secure.
So here Alice and Bob need to ensure
no-signaling.
Again, no radio inside the black box.
But do not need to characterize their
devices otherwise.
So again, this is one of these
device-independent scenarios.
And again notice that okay, we used the
violation of Bell
inequality, the effects of the results of
the measurement do not pre-exist.
We use them for something useful, to hide
this information
from an eavesdropper, even one with
unlimited computational power.
So I've come to the end of this important
lecture 7, in which we
discussed the intrinsic randomness of
quantum physics
used in the violation of Bell
inequalities.
What have we seen?
We have seen that 2 black boxes cannot
always
be simulated with pre-established data,
contrary to one black box.
So it's really useful to have these 2
boxes instead of one,
because there is something that suddenly
you cannot do anymore with pre-established
agreement.
You need either signalling or quantum
resources.
So if a Bell inequality is violated, the
outcomes are not pre-established.
If the outcomes are not pre-established,
of course, they cannot be predicted.
The violation of Bell inequalities has
been observed in many experiments,
and quantum information, this whole
research field, can be seen as
a way of making all these Outlandish
claims
of quantum physics, accepting them and
making them useful.
Thank you for your attention and see you
next week.