Welcome to this last lecture of this
course on randomness chance, and free
will.
It's time to speak a little bit about free
Of course not in an exhaustive way.
Just some ideas to trigger your curiosity
and to
link to what we have seen in the previous
lectures.
So here is the plan.
My main goal being, as I just
announced to discuss some connections
between randomness,
physical determinism, indeterminism, and
free will.
There will be four segments in this
lecture.
The first one will be a tentative
definition of free will, getting some
ideas.
In the second, we will discuss the
relation
between free will and the practice of
science.
Science is something that the human being
does, and as such does
reflect that the human being has free will
and influence on the possibility
of science.
Then I will sketch some quick notes on the
brain, by far not exhaustive.
It is not going to be, is not going
to be a course on neurosciences in any
possible meaning.
And finally we will finish with Libet's
experiment that is, the
traditional experiment that started
inquiring about free will in a sense.
So let us start with a definition,
what is free will?
Before defining free will I, two reminders
of
two notions we defined in the previous
lectures.
One is randomness of course.
We spent a lot of time discussing this.
Randomness is essentially
unpredictability.
It's a very neutral notion, because we
can just specify for whom something is
unpredictable.
For that person or for that physical
process.
The unpredictable events are random.
Then we spoke of physical determinism.
This is the question of whether all that
happens in
the physical world is predetermined, and
we have seen that whatever
your view of, ultimate view of the
universe is,
not everything is predictable for someone
that acts only in our universe.
Even if this being has
unlimited computational power, quantum
phenomena are
intrinsically unpredictable at some point,
and
in particular, if, also, we have limited
computational power, like all of us.
Also some classical phenomenon can be too
complex, or even, simple one,
deterministic, can be hard to predict,
because of susceptibility to initial
conditions.
That's what we have seen in some of the
previous lectures.
Now, when it comes to free will, I
want to take a definition from experience,
because, again,
I don't have time to enter into all
the philosophical debates on how to define
Free will.
So our experience tells us that what we
call free will,
is the capacity of making some choices
that are not completely pre-determined.
In this course I will argue from the point
of view that
any definition or any presentation of free
will must try to capture this
experience, because this is what we want
to describe at the end of the day.
Why human beings have this feeling of
being capable of choices.
It has an unquestionable relevance for our
lives
at the, of course, the level of moral
responsibility.
And it's impossible to keep the discussion
of free will fully separated from my
or your Weltanschaaung, your view of the
world, because it touches on,
what is a human being?
It touches on the meaning or lack of
meaning of our lives.
So depending what are your positions in
life
you may have a different attitude to
freewill.
And we have to remember that very often in
human
activity all these notions and beliefs of
servitude are very entangled.
We cannot just do a bare scientific
analysis, and then after that,
shatter all our convictions.
We are going to see these, especially in,
when it
comes to the practice of science in the,
the, second segment.
Needless to say a proper introduction of
all the notions, debates, people,
philosophers, scientists,
and so on, would take a full course, and
we don't have time for that.
This will be just an appetizer to trigger
your curiosity, as I said before.
Something of the ratio between freewill
and randomness.
My own choices are unpredictable
for someone who does not know me.
So if you don't know me and you see me
somewhere thinking about more choice.
You can use that as a random number
generator.
It's not going to be very fast because
nobody of us
takes more choices every micro second, but
it could possibly be done.
However it's clear that I do not make my
choices by tossing a coin.
So what determines a moral choice?
A choice of mine.
A choice of performing some action.
At a very phenomenological level, we
can speak of three constituents, some
predispositions.
The immediate circumstances and then my
judgement or my decision to act.
The predispositions can be of types.
Again it's very phenomenological.
People who have a given theory may have
different
opinion how these notions are related but
clearly at
the basic level, we can discuss of Somatic
predisposition, something that
is in our body, and formation, the
formation that we received.
Of course, the formation we received
partly shaped our brain,
you know, so it's not, the two are not
completely uncorrelated.
But, okay, clearly there is a difference.
Now, this is what is in my control or not.
The somatic predisposition clearly not in
my control.
If something
is influenced by my genetic code, I can't
do anything for it.
The formation and immediate circumstances
are partly my control, though not fully.
For instance formation, clearly if someone
chooses to be formed in a terrorist
camp, his or her future actions may be
influenced by this choice.
And this part of the formation, the choice
for
being formed in a terrorist camp rather
than in
a school or in any other environment, is
partly,
at least, normal, in the control of the
subject.
No, nobody is obliged, alright?
As we know, life is complex, but nobody's
really obliged to take these kind of
decisions.
Similarly the immediate circumstances is
clearly if I go
to a place where I know it's, I'm going to
be like to do something nasty because I'm
going
to meet people that I don't like, I'm
angry with.
I can get mad
at them.
Maybe I can also choose not to go.
Then once I am there, I, maybe I'm not any
longer
too much in control of my actions when I
see these people.
Finally, there is this part that I wrote
there, my judgment and the decision to
act.
That is the part where we're believed to
be fully in control,
that's the component of the action where
we have something to say.
Of course, various philosophies of action
differ on
the values and the relative importance of
these factors.
Some may even deny some of these factors.
Now let me illustrate these with a very
famous story from the western culture.
It's in fact from the Christian leaders
tradition, it's the famous denial of
Peter.
You may know that Peter is the, one of the
disciples of Jesus and one of the, in fact
the one that Jesus has chosen to be the
leader after he would go away.
So on a fateful day, the famous day of the
Last Supper, around 6 p.m.
During the Supper, Jesus announced that
He's going to die, and Peter says very
clearly, Lord, I am prepared to go to
prison and to die with You.
That's his moral decision, that's what he
would like to do.
A few hours later, I put 9 p.m just to
have
a, sort of, time framework, Jesus is being
captured by his enemies.
And Peter indeed starts fighting for him,
until Jesus
tells him to stop because he doesn't want
to fight.
In a few hours later, or less, midnight,
Jesus is being interrogated somewhere,
Peter is waiting outside to see what is
going to happen to his master.
And a maidservant sees him there in the
courtyard,
some unknown fellow that she has never met
before.
And she inquires if he's a disciple of
Jesus,
without maybe too bad intention.
And Peter tired, scared by the
consequences that can
be he immediately replies, woman, I do not
know him.
And then later, he denies Him two more
times.
So we see here a very interesting
experience that,
maybe we have felt, some of us, many times
also.
That's what Peter wanted to do.
He wanted to be strong, to go to prison
and to die with Jesus.
And that's what ends up doing.
Because of tiredness, because he was at
the wrong place, because whatever had
happened
to him, he ended up a few hours later just
denying even to know Him.
I brought up this story just to show that
it's known
to humanity that we're only in partial
control of our actions.
So let us make a balance of elements here
what free will is not.
Free will is not the possibility of
completely unpredictable behavior.
Normally, we call this, to lose one's
head,
if someone does something unfortunate or
something bad that
was completely unpredictable, and all the
neighbours and
friends say it was unbelievable of him or
her.
Well, then, normally, this means, to lose
one's
head, not to take a more responsible
decision.
Free will is also not the denial that
somatic or external factors may influence
our choices, as
we have just seen in the story of Peter.
This is not what is meant by free will.
It would be stupid to deny that our
genetic constitution,
that our external circumstances, and so
on, do influence our choice.
Free will is what, is the capacity of
making choices
that are not fully determined, and the,
the ensuing responsibility.
The people that did not, maybe strong way.
Whatever your philosophy is, if your
philosophy reaches the conclusion
that Hitler has done nothing wrong, you'd
better think again.
Such a conclusion would be abhorrent.
So somehow Hitler was responsible.
And of course not only such a terrible
case, but somehow
we are responsible for our moral
decisions, in one way or another.
Now I'm not going to continue on the
general
philosophical moral theoretical question.
I'm going to focus the next segements on
what has science to say about this.