Now we are going to consider the role of
free will in the practice of science.
Science being a human activity.
One may ask whether the free will of
humans plays
a role in the practice or even the
possibility of science.
I want to spend most of the
time explaining a notion that is extremely
important.
It is called measurement independence.
This is a fundamental tenet of the
scientific method,
and it is the possibility that the
experimenter performs
different measurements, or the possibility
of changing only some parameters.
Let me illustrate what I mean by a few
examples.
In lecture four, for instance, we have
seen in the lab
that the student was changing only the
value of the resistor.
Temperature, and the bandwidth, and all
possible
other relevant parameters being kept
unchanged.
Now, imagine that this is not possible.
Imagine that by changing the value of the
resistor,
one also changes the temperature, one also
changes the frequency.
One also chances, in fact, the whole
configuration.
Then it would be impossible to perform an
experiment and check that the noise is low
that we wrote down, that the square of
the noise, of the voltage is proportional
to the
resistor, is in fact true.
A similar example if you want to measure
gravity, very trivial, you have to try for
instance
one ways, one way of doing it is to
try and drop the same mass from different
heights.
Now we making that the stone that you have
in your hands conspires against you
to change its properties when you go to a
different place to throw it down.
Then again, it will make sense to check
the law of gravity.
You are to assume that the story is the
same, you are just testing it in different
situations.
Another very important procedure that you
certainly know, calibration.
When you calibrate a measurement device,
what you do is to see
what is happening at the detection before
you put the sample into it.
So that once you put the sample, the
difference between what you are
seeing before and what you see now, is
presumably due to the sample.
Again, if it's due to a conspiracy that
the device behaves differently whether
it knows that there is a sample or not
there, then science becomes impossible.
Last example, I think by now you
understand
what I'm speaking about, but if you think
of drug tests, same, you have to give
the same drug to persons with various
conditions.
And again, if the drug knows, whatever
that means, that the person it
is going to be eaten by has a
given condition, behaves differently
according to this knowledge.
Then the test doesn't make any sense.
So, the whole possibility of science,
relies on the fact that, you, try to
keep all the other meaningful parameters
unchanged, and you just change one or two.
This has little to do with morality, with
consciousness, but
it says that there must be some events
that are uncorrelated.
There's some events that do not depend on
each other.
In the theater, theater of conspiracy I
defined at the beginning of lecture
five, also science becomes pointless,
like, probably
most of the rest of our lives.
Now let us see what is these, an example
of this independent chain of events.
So, in order to do science, the science of
measuring my resistor.
I have to start by assuming
that there is no initial correlation
between
myself, my mental state and the resistor.
That the resistor doesn't know that I'm
going to measure it and that I
have now chosen our resistors specifically
fabricated
for me to show a particular behavior.
So, at the beginning, there is a resistor.
They are living its own life, fluctuating
its own way, and
there is myself, thinking that maybe I
should do some experiment.
A later
time, still no correlation, I decide to
make a measurement of the thermal
noise of the resistor, and my resistor is
still perfectly independent of me.
Now comes the dependence.
This is the measurement, the interaction
between the physical
object and what I know, and I get some
knowledge.
Now there is correlation, in the sense
that
my mental state has some information about
the
fluctuations of voltage in the resistor.
Now you may think, well what guarantee is
this?
Because at the, at the beginning maybe
there was
some event, let's call it the Big Bang,
that created
some correlations so maybe it's impossible
to have physical processes,
my mental state and the resistor that are
really independent.
Now even physics, without or
yet invoking freewill has a good answer to
that question.
So, assume that indeed there was an
initial Big
Bang or whatever event, such that in fact
the atoms
that now compose the resistors and the
atom that now
compose my brain, have interacted in a way
or another.
The resistor on myself, I'm not the only
physical object present in this universe.
Both have, we have interacted with plenty
of other things.
All these small explosions represent
collisions in the
sense of exchange of information between
different systems.
So, even staying at the classical level.
If I have shared my information and also
the resistor, I shared its
information with many other events, and
these
events now have disappeared from the
scene.
You see that the arrows point outwards.
I don't control them.
I don't know where they are.
Then, in practice,
it's as if the resistor and myself would
be uncorrelated.
Because the initial may be strongly shared
information, has
been diluted into all these possible
degrees of freedom.
So for all practical purposes it's as if
we had no, no common past.
Moreover, remember that there is not
only classical physics, there's quantum
physics.
There maybe have been, and there have
been, quantum
events on all these causal chains, which
are really creation
of information.
So we see that physics itself, within
physics itself, within science,
within physical processes in the universe,
we have good reasons to believe,
to accept, that at the beginning of the
experiment, the resistor and
my mental state are not correlated, do not
depend on each other.
So, let me go back now to the question
with
which I started, is free will needed to do
science?
As we've just seen the scientific method
itself requires measurement independence.
Free will is not strictly needed.
We can justify measurement independence in
a
sort of deterministic of purely material
physical universe.
Of course, if we accept from all kind of
other evidence that there is free
will, then some measurement independence
comes for
free, especially the measurement
independence where really I,
a human being, is involved in making a
measurement.
There is another topic that I have not
brought up,
and I don't want to spend much time on it
now.
It would deserve also a full course.
Is the moral responsibility of the
scientist.
Let me just put it like this, if you have
a
favorite, favorite ethics theory of
behavior, that denies free will to
the point of approving cheating, bullying
in the workplace, falsification
of data, and so on.
Then I think you should think again
because these behaviors are universally
acknowledged as unacceptable.