We've just seen how freewill and the
practice of science are related.
Now let us study the brain a little bit.
Just the science of the brain.
Can the science of the brain tell us
something about freewill?
A couple of no-brainers.
The human brain and not only the human
brain in fact.
Many brains are extremely complex.
Physical and chemical processes happen in
the brain.
This is also something absolutely obvious,
and well, the brain
is somehow related to free will, to
consciousness, and these notions.
Because we know that the processes that
happen there, are related precisely to our
decisions.
So the science of the brain is certainly
relevant for the discussion of free will.
This is just the introduction of why I'm
speaking of the brain and not about the
hands.
Given where we come from in the previous
lectures, it is relevant
to ask whether quantum physics Has
something to do with a brain.
And again a no-brainer, something clear
that quantum physics describes, chemistry
describes processes.
So ultimately quantum physics describes
the chemical processes
or the electrical processes, that are
happening in
the brain like everywhere else.
That's not the question.
But the question is, maybe the tempting
question.
The further tempting question is, can
quantum
indeterminism be somehow related to free
will?
I want to make a couple of comments about
this question.
First of all, I think it's a
valid scientific question because it's in
principle testable.
It has a funny status
in the sense that people who are
materialist.
Like the idea, because in their approach
this would prove
that our free will is nothing else than a
physical process.
Quantum of a physical process.
Interestingly enough, also people who are
dualists like the idea, because this
idea would allow the, the ghost that is in
us to shape
decisions without violating the laws of
physics.
So it's a intriguing question, whether
quantum indeterminism is related to free
will.
My stance is negative.
I think the answer is no.
Most people do think like that, but there
are also quite
a few people who still hope that there is
something there.
Let me list the prudent objections
that one can make with this idea of
quantum indetermination
having something to do with free decisions
in the brain.
First of all, there is no evidence of the
use of quantum statistics.
In the brain, of the use of these quantum
phenomena, like the measurements, like
interferences, and follow the measurement
as we
have seen in the lectures six and seven.
In particular, recently, some people have
asked whether the brain could be a
quantum computer, and I like the reply
that Scott Aaronson and other people give.
To these questions, they, well, we don't
seem to be particularly good
at factoring integers, which is the task
that would distinguish a quantum computer.
In fact, even more, there is still very
little
evidence of quantum phenomena, or let's
say purely quantum phenomena.
Again, in all of chemistry, ultimately
there is some quantum
there, but.
Purely quantum in the sense of intrinsic
randomness in
environment that are hot and wet, like the
brain.
For me, even more important than this
objection that there
is little evidence at the end of the day
one
would find evidence one day, is the fact
that the
explanation does not take into account the
complexity of the brain.
All that people do differently.
If it would be true that
quantum indeterminism is the ultimate
source of our free will, then a photon
on a beam-splitter would exhibit something
that is similar to our free will.
I do think however that the complexity of
our brain
must play a role in allowing free will to
be possible.
I think that maybe emergence is a more
interesting concept.
Emergence is defined as, cooperative
phenomenon in complex systems that
could not have been predicted by studying
the individual component.
And clearly, complex systems does fit the
brain.
In fact, the brain is probably the
paradigmatic example of a complex system.
Another instance of a widely used concept,
in this course we
didn't have time to speak about
complexity, again, follow the video
with someone else teaching a full course
on
complexity somewhere on the internet and
on the MOOCs.
Anyway, just to give an example of what
emergence means, how comes that many
atoms under some conditions form a solid
or under other conditions form a liquid?
And with higher order imposed on them, the
same atoms,
or atoms of the same species, form a
living being?
Where does this order come from?
Clearly A living being is not just a lump
of atoms.
There is some organization.
There is some order there that matters.
This is the idea of emergence that
starting from the individual atoms, it
would be
very, very hard if not impossible to
reconstruct
the functioning of a living being for
instance.
Without going so far, you will have seen
photos
of the wind shaping the fumes.
So this means, we have many grains of sand
that form some patterns.
The patterns cannot be predicted by
studying each individual grain of sand.
You really have to think that are many
grains of sand and somehow would have
put them together under some influence,
external
influence of the wind, that create those
patterns.
And a dramatic example of the behavior of
crowds, it
is well known that if you are in a crowd,
you may end up doing things that you
alone, you would not do,
just because the crowd, it's doing it, so
you go along with it.
Applied to the brain, Emergence means that
it is probably impossible to describe the
activity of the brain, by focusing only on
elementary constituents or processes.
Like focusing only on the neurons,
focusing
only on how the neurosignal is
transmitted.
It probably does not recover It certainly
does not recover what the brain does.
And now if we think of something very
advanced like our free will, then most
probably
elementary processes will not be enough to
describe
this process, this, this, this evidence of
free will.
Let us relate complexity with randomness,
since at the end
of the day, also it is a course of
randomness.
So how do complexity scholars look at
randomness?
Here's a graph, and you have on the
horizontal axis, disorder, on the vertical
axis, complexity.
In the corner down there.
Low, low complexity and low disorder,
they're the simple pattern.
You can think of a triangle and geometric
patterns, there are geometric patterns or
you can
think of a sequence, very orderly
sequence.
We know also that there, there is no
random.
And it's other angle with very
high disorder, you would put precisely
randomness.
The outcome of a fair coin is
completely disordered, it's unpredictable
what's going to happen.
But it's not very complex.
You don't need a lot of complexity, you
just need a fair coin.
Now,
what is complexity?
Complexity is something in between, what
maybe is not
completely random, in fact, there is
higher order in patterns.
But it requires complex precisely systems.
An example I want to give here is the
digits of pi.
If you look at the digits of pi and nobody
tells you what they are, well it looks
completely random.
However if someone tells you what they
are, well there is order.
It's clear algorithm.
Related to something that you would not
have seen by just looking at the digits.
This is an example, of course, there are
many other examples.
The brain is clearly an example of high
complexity, and
there must be a little bit of disorder,
because otherwise,
brain would be a crystal, with all the
atoms arranged
in perfect patterns, it would not show
such a complexity.
But is not a random
object, clearly the brain is not a random
assembly of atoms.
Is not a random assembly of neurons.
So the takeaway message from, for us.
Again you can read books and website.
So we'll put some links later on
complexity.
Is that complex is different from random.
And the brain is complex rather than
random.
Of course, you could use a complex
phenomena as a random number generator in
suffice it's how to predict, but it is not
the same.
So this is my bottom line, that the brain
is probably more complex than random.
Now I've brought up so far a lot of
interesting topics, extremely exciting.
Free will, moral responsibility, the
brain, complexity.
The moral responsibility of scientists.
Why we should not cheat, and so on.
I would have to leave any deepening of
these notions to your personal inquiry.
We don't have time in this course, it was
not the focus
of this course to develop these topics, at
least not this year.
If I repeat it next year, maybe I will
spend more time on this.
The last segment will be devoted, however
to presenting one of the
most discussed experiments in the science
of the brain which is Lebit's experiment.
So, let us conclude with that.