The last segment of this lecture is
devoted to the great milestone of the
neuroscience
of freewill, which is the series of
experiments conducted by Benjamin Libet in
the 1980s.
In order to describe what Libet has done I
have to introduce some observable quantity
that has been noticed.
A few years before he started working, is
called the readiness potential.
So the task is very simple, is a subject
is asked to move a finger, and the fact
the
finger moved would be detected by the fact
that a
button would be pushed and the button
sends the signal.
So the subject moves the finger at some
point
and this defines the time 0 of the
experiment.
What was done on some patients that were
undergoing
some open brain surgery with of course
their consentment was to measure.
The voltage of the electric signal, the
neuronal signal,
in the relevant part of the brain, and
what was
observed in that particular experiment is
that the signal starts
more or less half a second before the
finger moves.
This is certainly longer than the time a
signal just needs to
propagate from the brain to the arm and to
the finger.
But it's not a big problem in the
sense there is nothing mind-boggling here,
just the brain.
Half a second before moving the finger
starts some electric
signal that will ultimately end up in the
finger moving.
Libet added something to this.
What he added is a clock.
He asked the subject
not only to push the button at some point
when he or she feels like, but to indicate
at what time on a clock he or she
has taken the conscious decision of moving
the finger.
So the clock is moving by discreet steps,
there is a dot there moving.
And the subject will say, I took the
conscious decision of pushing the
button when the dot was in that particular
position.
And now the amazing result is that when
all the data are processed.
Libet and his team found out that the
conscious is
taken only 0.2 seconds approximately,
before the motion of the finger.
Now, the fact that it's before the motion
of the
finger is not a big deal, of course, as
expected.
But what
is really mind boggling is that the
consciousness seems
to happen after the electric signal has
already started in the brain.
So the big question is, does our brain
decide for us?
What happens in our brain?
Is it only a series of neurosignals, and
at some
point these neurosignals amount that of
things trigger a sort
of thing called consciousness where,
whereby we think that.
We take a decision, but the decision in
fact
was already taken by the signal, by the
neurons.
Well, things are not that bad because
Libet
has also done some other observations, in
particular while
doing his observations he also noticed
that there are
signals of a different type, of this
particular type.
And then
he asked the subject to say what happens,
what feeling did he
or she have in the brain when these kind
of signals were observed.
And what the subjects said is that in
those cases, they had
felt like moving the finger, but then they
had changed their mind.
So it seems that our consciousness is not
the same at all as our mental states.
On the one hand, the mental
states influences the consciousness and
tries to take a
decision, but the consciousness is somehow
free to say, no.
Of course, this is very rapidly said, and
I am summarizing at a very
phenomenological level a lot of
discussions, and
some people may not even agree with this.
Conclusion in fact there is a lot of
debate about the real meaning of Libet's
experiment.
Let me mention a few
comments that I have sorted out from
internet but
you can find many others if you google for
it.
Some people have criticized the original
experiments by the
fact these critical of saying where you
have seen the
dot when you have taken a concscious
decision is
not very precise and it is indeed it is
not.
Also because there is a lag from the eye
to the brain.
Now I have to instead of criticizing
there,
I have to say that I would praise Libet
for coming up with such a simple
arrangement, just put
a clock on the wall and ask the person to
look.
This smart idea triggered the whole
debate.
And this has also let to later.
Do more precise experiments with more
direct measurements and let us
confirm in fact the initial observation,
with some difference in the times.
Another objection is that the task
of pushing a button that has no
consequence at
all other than pushing the button is not
particulary meaningful.
Recently, some experiments have tried to
address more meaningful tasks.
It's always about pushing buttons, but now
there are two buttons,
and well, nothing really bad happens if
you push those buttons, but
the goal is rather to try to guess what
another person
is doing and if you guess correctly then
you get some reward.
So there is a little bit
of meaning there.
Again, it is not exactly what we would
call a very strong moral decision.
But the conclusion I want to say is that,
no fundamental discrepancy
from Libet's findings have been observed,
even with much more refined experiments.
Of course, many people are also discussing
whether this very simple description
with a consciousness, the mental state,
and the finger moving, is enough.
There are probably
many more physical and neuronal processes
in between.
And again, these are, goes far beyond the
course of this course.
I hope that at least your curiosity has
been
triggered to look a bit more into these
topics.
So let's throw a balance of what we have
seen from this little experiment.
The first observation is that mental
states and consciousness
are not identical, and in particular, it
is not obvious
at all that consciousness is just an
emergent phenomenon of the mental states.
There are lots of debates there, there are
many serious
people who maintain such a position, but
many others who don't.
And again, it's an exciting debate worth
following.
But clearly, Libet's experiment shows that
there are some
physical mechanisms in the brain that bias
our decisions.
At some point, if I may put it like this,
the brain sends a message saying,
hey, please, push that button.
But apparently, we can also tell the
brain, no, sorry, I don't do it now.
This is not particularly astonishing.
We started this lecture by stating that
freewill does not mean complete lack of
determination.
And I repeated these tests are always
done so far in simple and controlled
situations.
The very meaningful decisions of our life
cannot be brought back to
this kind of tests.
For instance, if you think of a decision
to this but is
not very, is not a moral problem sometimes
but have very important implications.
And we think we take it freely, namely the
decision to marry someone.
Well, that decision is not taken half a
second before proposing.
It's a result of a lot of processes, a lot
of deliberations and reflection and so on.
Certainly these kind of decisions and
other complicated moral
decisions are not captured by these kind
of experiments.
They are nonetheless extremely relevant,
and it's worthwhile, again,
following, at least, to see what the
future will reveal.
So we've come to the end of the lecture
eight, in which I
try to highlight the connections and the
differences between randomness,
indeterminism and free will.
We've seen that free will is not
randomness.
Neither it is total lack of determinism.
It is the possibility of shaping our
choices.
Limited maybe, and it relates to our
responsibility.
We'll discuss the important notion of
measurement independence; that is
one of the conditions for scientific
method to be possible.
We've mentioned the science of the brain,
very, very rapidly of course.
But mostly to mention, that in my opinion
and the opinion of many people,
complexicity is a much more relevant
notion then
quantum determination when it comes to the
brain.
And finally we have seen Libet's
experiment.
Now, I'm sorry, I'm very bad at
conclusions, so
I will conclude very rapidly this series
of lectures.
Now you should be able to talk about
randomness, the
fact that randomness is useful, how to
define and quantify randomness.
You should have some idea how to generate
randomness.
You should be able to speak, also, about
physical determinism and indeterminism,
predictability, chaos, all these notions.
You have a little bit of notions of free
will,
at least insofar as free will relates to
the previous topics.