This is going to be a rather short
segment.
I just want to introduce to you another
setup that also is used to show
interferences.
This is called the double-slit setup and
is used in many discussions.
It is based on a different way of
splitting waves.
The beam splitter I showed you before
[INAUDIBLE] is called amplitude splitting.
You have a wave coming in, and it splits
it in, let's say two waves of half
intensity.
The other kind of way of splitting waves
is what is called Wavefront Splitting.
The wave has it is not a localized object
in space.
It's propagating in this direction but
it's a, sort of, spatial wave like that.
And upon finding a slit, part of it would
be reflected,
and part of the transmitter is transformed
into, essentially, a spherical wave.
So Young's double-slit
interferometer is based on that idea.
You have two slits, as the name indicates,
a wave impinging on them.
What remains of the wave are two spherical
wave that go towards
a stream, and in the stream
there will be constructive and destructive
interferences.
So, you will see some regions where a lot
of light is detected, some
amount, or a lot of particles is
detected and some regions where nothing is
detected.
Typically the intensity
profile goes something like this.
Historically these interference
was first reported by Thomas Young in
1803, using light.
And, of course, it was far before quantum
physics started.
In fact, it was one of the strongest
pieces of evidence that light is a
wave and not a particle, together with
something observed in France, which is
called [FOREIGN].
Now interestingly,
Young was British.
He presented his results in the Royal
Society,
and he was strongly attacked on strongly
unscientific grounds.
The reason was that, as you may know from
the history
of science, the description of light has
been controversial for many centuries.
And Newton, the champion of the British
Islands was
supporting the view that light is a
particle, whereas some
people in Europe, in the continental
Europe were
supporting the view that light is a wave.
So the poor Young demonstrated that the
light is a wave in the British Islands,
was attacked by his peers because he
was attacking, in fact, the founding
father Newton.
Of course, at the end of the day, the
thing was peacefully
settled and light was considered the wave
until the Quantum Physics came.
So, where has this Young double-slit
experiment
been observed, been performed with this
matter wave, with these particles?
Well, again, many with electrons, for
instance, propagating electrons,
this times from a electron microscope,
with atoms, atom interferometry.
I'm going to speak about this a bit later.
Interesting this kind of interference, the
Young’s one or some
other one called Talbot-Lau called now the
record of mass.
Some experiments done by Mark Passau
in Vienna, since 2001 have shown this kind
of interferences for what one would call
large molecules.
At the beginning they started with the C60
molecules or C70 molecules.
These are molecules involving 60 or 70
atoms of carbon.
C61 is the famous foolery is the one where
the atoms
are arranged on the vertices of, it look
like a soccer ball.
C70 is like an elongated soccer ball or a,
American soccer ball.
And then later the same group change a
little bit the experiment,
technically, in order to study, several
complex molecules, like the ones listed
there.
They are also very particular shapes, so
they are not symmetric and nothing is
still.
With all these complex objects, you still
see the single particle interference of
quantum physics.
And in principle, there's nothing that
prevents people from going beyond
that, apart from technical difficulties of
the really serious ones like how to
obtain a source for these particles, these
molecules that do not destroy them.
The larger the object, the slowest must be
the speed for some reason.
So, maybe, it's not tomorrow that we're
going
to see interferences on really a
microscopic object.
But several other experiments have been
performed
to show quantum effects of large objects.
Now I'm going to show you a video
of some Young's slit interference has
built up by some matter waves.
Before the video itself, let me describe
rapidly how the setup looks like.
These are, we are going to see data
collected by Christian
Kurtsiefer, one of my colleagues presently
here in Singapore, doing his Ph.D.
thesis in Constance in 1996.
The set up, you can imagine, in a lab, is
from the source to the detector,
approximately three meters long.
The source is cell
of gas of Helium atoms, so the nucleus is
two protons and two neutrons, and some
electrons around.
And these atoms are going to be sent
through a
first slit, before the two slits that will
do the interference.
This is meant as a preparation for the
incoming wave.
If you remember from the previous slides,
in order to see the double-slit
experiment,
ideally one should arrive onto the
double-slit
with a flat, with a plain wave.
And of course, an atom, emitted in a very
well-defined
direction from the, from the source is not
a plain wave.
So in order to create this wave, the atom
is first sent through a narrow slit,
narrow enough to transform this localized
atom into a wave, as drawn there.
And then after one meter of between the,
the first slit and the
two slits, this wave is essentially plain
and it can give isol interference better.
Some numbers, the de Broglie wavelengths
or the wavelength of this
matter wave, of this atom wave, would be
approximately 50 picometers.
The slits are one micrometer wide and
eight micrometer apart from one another.
And what you're going to see is
a circle of detection of 150 micrometers
wide.
After, again, approximately 1.5 meters
from the double-slit.
So here is the video.
You see here, every atom arriving on the
screen, and giving rise to a single
detection.
But when the detections accumulate, the
color
code means how many atoms have detected in
a given pixel of the detector.
We see clearly the interference fringes
appearing.
This figure has been taken over 49 hours
of
measuring, so of course, this is a
fast-motion movie.
I'll show it again, and just appreciate
how amazing it is,
this effect where each atom indeed lands
at a very well-defined position.
But when you accumulate over many items,
the interferring
fringes appears.