So, we have just seen that a particle has
an unexpected behavior
depending on whether the path that it
takes are distinguishable or not.
And this is the essence of the phenomena
of interference that
we are going to describe in more detail in
this segment.
So, here is again the experiment we have
just seen.
And in particular one assumption that was
made in
this experiment was that the two paths are
of
the same length.
And in that case we have seen that all the
particles in
that order, the only detector that fires
is the TR or RT.
Now let us introduce a difference in
length.
So, just by making one, one of the two
paths slightly longer, in practice is
not done as, as predict, as plotted there,
but just as to have an idea.
What happens?
Well, remarkably, if one of the paths is
made a bit longer, then the probabilities
change.
So now, they behave, well according to
these two functions, sin
of square of, essentially the, the path
difference divided by some wavelength.
A cosine squared divided by some of the,
of the path difference divided by the
wavelength.
Of course as you all know, sine of
square plus cosine square is equal to 1,
so and the probability of [UNKNOWN].
Now, what does that mean?
It means that the statistics, the observed
statistics of the particles, of
the clicks in the detectors, depend on the
difference between the two paths.
Still, remember that from the clicks we
know that
the source is sending one particle at a
time.
It's not a continuous beam where many
particles
take each path and they meet at some point
and they inform each other.
Further, notice that if I take a
difference in length, that is equal
to half the wavelength, then all the
particles have changed their behavior.
Before all of them were going here.
Now all of them will end up here.
So by changing only one of the paths, I
can
influence the behavior of all the paths,
in each one
of them because I'm sending them one at a
time.
There is only one conclusion to be drawn
from this, is that
each particle, whatever particle means in
this context, must have explored both
paths.
You cannot compute a difference by staying
only on one path.
Each particle must know the length of each
of
the paths and compute the difference
between the two lengths.
This is what is called delocalization.
As you see, it's a word that sounds very
particular but it's
a precise technical meaning and is related
to something that is really absurd.
All these experiments, I want to repeat it
again and again.
They can be done, and have been done.
Now you may think, hey, I want to learn by
which path the particle really came.
So, what can I do?
When you can send a probe, whatever that
is again.
What is the probe depends
on what the particle is, and in fact
sometimes it's not easy to send a probe.
Sometimes easy, it depends on the system.
Anyway, suppose you send this one of these
probes, and you find that the particle is
there.
Then what do we observe?
Oh, suddenly the statistics become
independent of the path difference.
They become one half, one half.
As in our original, sort of intuitive
prediction.
Now, it is again madness.
No, no, this one is not madness.
It's entirely consistent.
Look here.
If you look at what we have there in the
corner.
It's nothing else than the first
experiment.
Because now we saw, we know that the
particle is here.
So, it's as if having the source there.
And it is just a particle going onto a
beam splitter, and with probably the
one half going here, we probably have one
half going there, so everything is
perfectly consistent.
Nevertheless, we have learned that
indistinguishability of paths
really matters.
Sometimes this fact is called in quantum
physics generically, as measurements
modifies the properties.
Again, is one of these sentences that has
a
precise technical meaning, and here we
know what it means.
An object that before the measurement, or
in the
absence of a measurement, would have given
rise to interferences.
Because the measurement has been done,
suddenly the interferences
have disappeared, and this object now
gives only random results
like a fair coin.
These, if you are a bit familiar with
physics,
is very much the behavior, in fact, of
waves.
Forget about the particles, and suppose
now that
I tell you the same story with waves.
Okay, so the source is emitting a wave,
the wave is split in two.
And then one of them is delayed, so when
you when you
reach the second beam splitter there
is contracting and there is contracting
interference.
And indeed, there is a bigger wave that
goes
through the detector, and a smaller wave
that goes
through the other detector.
And this is fair enough.
Indeed, interference is the typical
phenomena for waves.
So, are we actually dealing with waves?
Well, you should still explain the single
clicks.
If you have a wave of this type, as you
see
here in the drawing, the wave is both here
and here.
So it's hard to explain for a wave, why in
this case this detector would click and
this detector would not.
Or the opposite,
by the way, because even if the wave is
molar there must be
still a probability for this detector to
click and this detector not to click.
So clearly, also the expression of waves
that makes the interference phenomena
understandable makes it very hard to
understand what, what is happening at
detection.
Now, what kind of objects manifest this,
this phenomena of interference.
In fact, interference is ubiquitous in
quantum physics.
Everything in quantum
physics is a specific form of
interferences
that we describe with some mathematical
formalism.
When it comes to the Mach-Zehnder
interferometer, the
one that I have shown here with single
particles.
This one has been implemented already in
many experiments.
Probably the first one that was using
really single particles was with
neutrons, is due to the group of Helmut
Rauch and around 1975.
It's probably
the first experiment where each particle,
in this case, each neutron, was
proved to be emitted at the very late time
after the other.
So, there was really only one neutron in
the [INAUDIBLE] at each time.
And still of course the interference
pattern was observed.
With light, well the bad news is that a
laser is not a source of single photon.
So, whatever you do with a laser, or with
a
normal lamp, you cannot really claim that
you are seeing interferences
of these type.
Because there are always many excitations
in the field.
But in 1982 group in Orsay, Paris
demonstrated Mach-Zehnder interferometry
for, let's say single photons, or at least
something that is not like a laser.
And since this phenomenon has been seen
for
single atoms, electrons in semiconductors
and many other systems.
So, again, it's a very important
phenomena.
It's something that is undisputedly there
in nature.
Notice that light is usually thought of as
a wave but
as we have seen here it can also exhibit
particle behavior.
These particles are called photons, it's
the word I was using before.