We're now going to consider the
first interference phenomenon called the
Mach–Zehnder interferometer.
I call this this segment beam splitting
because the first thing I'm
going to speak about is how to split a
beam of particles.
So here is the first experiment that I
want to describe.
There is a source of something that I'm
going to explain later what it is.
Since these particles, these objects, on a
beam splitter.
A beam splitter is something
that splits the beam, as the name
indicates.
So after the beam splitter, we have a
transmitted beam and a reflected beam.
And each beams now go to one particle
detector.
So let's go in detail into these objects.
This can be a source of what Well
essentially of anything you can think of
a source of light, for instance a laser,
but a single photon source or something
else.
You can think a source of atoms,
for instance an oven where a gas is heated
and then
some of the atom escape and can propagate
along the path.
You can think of a source of neutrons.
which would be a nuclear reactor.
But, in principle it can be anything.
And all the physical systems I've
mentioned
here have been used for such experiments.
Now, how the beam splitter and the
detector work,
okay, this depends of course on what the
beam is
made of.
for light, you are very familiar with beam
splitters.
Any piece of glass that is not fully
transparent is a beam splitter.
If you look, for instance, in the
spectacles
of a friend of yours, of course you
can see his or her eyes through the
spectacles, but you can also see your
reflection there.
So this means that part of the light is
transmitted and part is reflected.
Now what is the observation for these
experiments?
Well, first of all, we have to say what
the detector sees.
the detector registers clicks.
So sometimes, one of two detectors makes a
click.
Whatever it is, it means in practice it
means it sends
an electric signal to a computer, but is
an individual event.
And I will also describe this experiment
in a very simplified way, but it's in
principle possible.
so let us assume that when detector fires,
the other never fires.
So this suggests that we are detecting
indivisible particles, so each particle
is going on the beam-splitter Chooses
whether to be transmitted or reflected.
How we come back to this later and
and the detector reveals where the
particle has gone.
And let
us assume also this is a property of the
beam-splitter then if you do
the statistics you find that half of
the particles are transmitted and half are
reflected.
Now, according to quantum physics, the,
the choice of the particle of the
beam splitter to be transmitted or
reflected
is one of these intrinsically random
phenomena.
And we'll spend essentially this lecture
arguing
whether this intrinsic randomness is
justified or not.
At the end of the day, it will be.
Here's another experiment, I complicate it
a little bit.
Now I put three beam splitters arranged as
in the figure.
So now we have four path.
The first path is where both beam splitter
that transmitted the, the particle.
The second path transmitted and reflected.
So the particle was transmitted to the
first.
First is this one, transmitted here and
then reflected there.
There's another path where the particle
was
reflected here and transmitted there.
And another path where the particle was
reflected here, and also reflected there.
Now we can ask what kind of statistics are
we going to observe in this experiment.
This cannot be guessed in advance.
It depends whether to be transmitted or
reflected is
intrinsic random or it is a property of
the particle.
But, in this case let us assume that this
intrinsic random, and so therefore
we expect that each of the possibilities
of P are a probability of 1/4.
So because the, the first particle has
probably the one half to be transmitted
here.
And once it derives here again, a
probability
one half are being transmitted or
reflected, so
in total one half times one half is one
quarter, and so on for all the detectors.
So again, let us assume that this
observation is made
and in fact, as I said before, it can be
made
as ideal as one wants with effort.
And here is our third experiment.
Now, there are only two beam splitters,
here and here, and there are two mirrors.
Mirrors as in the normal word, that
reflect everything.
So here the beam just is reflected.
Now if you look at this setup it looks
like a folded version of the previous one.
The particles that are transmitted here or
here they must be reflected.
And then they arrive here.
They can be transmitted here or reflected.
So the path transmitted, transmitted is
this one.
And the path transmitted reflected is this
one.
Now the transmitted reflected overlaps
with
the reflected here and transmitted there.
And the transmitter transmitted reflects
with the reflected here and the reflected
there.
So what do we guess for the probabilities
of these experiment.
Well, a very natural guess would be that
the probability of finding
the particle in the detector transmitted
transmitted or reflected reflected, is one
half.
Why?
Because you should, you would think to
take
all the particles that previously were
transmitted transmitted.
Plus all the particles that previously
were reflected are reflected,
that is one quarter plus one quarter is
one half.
However the observation is very different
from that.
The observation is that all the particles
end up in the detector TR or RT, in other
words, the other detector never clicks.
The probability of TT or RR is zero.
Now, this sounds like madness, and it
would be madness if there would not
be at least one physical difference
between the two configurations.
So let us look at the two configurations
here.
Experiment two and experiment three.
I remind you of them here.
We have the first experiment with
probability
one quarter for each of the detectors.
The second experiment, experiment number
three, with probability
one for one detector and zero for the
other.
Is there any difference that would allow
us to think oh, it makes sense
at least to believe that there is a, to
believe, I
mean, to, to, to observe that there is a
different behavior.
And there is indeed a difference.
It is indistinguishability.
You see in experiment number two each
detector corresponds to a unique path.
In experiment number three the detection
does not allow to know which path
the particle has taken at the first beam
splitter, whether T or R.
Now in principle this should not matter
for a particle but at least we
have a, physical difference that we can
use as a, to distinguish the two
situations.