And with the help of the Double-slit
experiment, I will
be able to discuss" The Notion of
Uncertainty", in inverted commas.
Let us start with the very famous
Heisenberg uncertainty relation.
It says that the uncertain in position
times
uncertainty in momentum, the product of
these two quantities.
Is, larger than something that is
determined by the Planck's constant.
And since the Planck's constant is
different from zero,
both uncertainties must be larger than
zero, of course.
Also, the smaller the uncertainty on
position The
larger must be the one in momentum and
vice-versa.
Now, what kind of uncertainty are we
speaking about?
This has given rise to a lot of
discussions.
In fact the meaning within quantum physics
is very clear.
But here we are going to see as an example
of,
how these notions are complicated to grasp
even for the specialists.
So, confusions on the left you have some
wrong interpretations
of the uncertainty principle on the right
one will give you the correct one.
Wrong interpretation, very popular one.
We can not measure position and momentum
at the same time.
This clearly not an extremely interesting
statement and it not what is said there.
For instance, as I've read in here, I am
one of the, the persons, like many
others in the world and probably many of
you, who can both ski and ride a bicycle.
But it would be very hard for me to prove
to you, at the same time.
That I can ski and ride a bicycle.
And still, I can do both.
Another wrong interpretation of the
uncertainty relations
is that it refers to the imprecision, or
the uncertainty, of our measurement
devices or procedures.
As in, when you go to the lab, and you,
you have to put error bars.
You have to describe what is the
uncertainty in the reading
of your, of your device or your
measurement device and so on.
This is not, what the uncertainty
relations are about.
In fact, in certainty relations we fell to
ideal
measurements, measurements that are done
with the best possible devices.
So what is the right interpretation of
those uncertainty relations.
The right interpretation is that no
particle can have at the same time.
Well defined position and a well defined
momentum.
So you see it's not a matter of measuring
at the same time.
It's a matter of really the particle
having
these properties.
Of this particle that's being really
present in nature at the same time.
So it's about intrinsic randomness at the
end of the day.
And now, what I want to discuss, is what
happened to the poor Heisenberg.
Who mistaken himself, presented an, an
explanation of the uncertainty relations.
That is based on the wrong interpretation
written down there.
So, what
happened?
This is what the famous Heisenberg's
microscope.
You can still find it in textbooks, of
course, because as we said some time ago.
Quantum physics is difficult and when one
of the authorities,
one of the greatest physicists of the
century, tells you something.
You try to take it seriously until some
people understood that.
But probably there he was wrong.
So what happened to Heisenberg?
He derived the uncertainty relations just
from the quantum formalism.
At the beginning it was a purely
mathematical derivation.
And then he was writing a semi-popular
book.
And he tried to convey an illustration, an
image of what is going on.
To try to suggest that maybe it's not so
unreasonable.
And unfortunately there is where he
missed, somehow, the point.
So let us go through Heisenberg's idea.
Here is our double-slit experiment.
And let's imagine a particle that
can take those two possible paths.
To arrive to the same point in the stream.
And then there is constructive or
destructive interference between the two
path.
And now, Heisenberg say, well, let's see
what happens if we try to probe.
To measure where the particle is.
So we have the probe there, and if the
particle is detected,
it reflects on to a stream that detects
where the particle is.
So, for instance in this particular
instance, the probe is sent and
the particle is detected in the upper
path.
So now we know the which path information.
Now the interference should disappear.
And what Heisenberg says is, yes, indeed
it is a PSY.
Because the probe has given us more kick,
to the particle.
So now has deviated the particle that
doesn't land anymore where it's supposed
to land.
Then Heisenberg makes a back of the
envelope calculation and finds that the,
Product of the kick, of the displacement
in momentum, given by the kick
and the displacement in position because
of the kick, that our final position.
Are related by the photon and electron by
delta p
delta x, sort of the order of magnitude of
H bar.
So everything seems to be okay.
And this is, in fact, correct and wrong at
the same time.
What is correct?
It is certainly correct that if you
learn which path information, the
interference disappears.
No doubt about that.
It is also correct, that the mechanism of
Heisenberg is a possible way of knowing
the path.
So, indeed if one sense photon let's say,
on an electron.
And the photon interacts with the electron
is bounced back.
Okay, is a bit hand waving because photons
and electrons don't
really bounce back in that way.
But if you can do such a, such
an experiment, then indeed you will lose
the interference.
And in the, for instance in the
experiments of
the [INAUDIBLE] that I mentioned before
with the molecules.
They added air, a lot of air pressure in
the vacuum chamber, and
indeed the interference disappeared
because all
these air molecules were hitting the
molecules.
That were supposed to do the interference.
What is wrong is that these facts that are
correct have nothing to do,
with delta p times delta x equal, larger
or equal than each [INAUDIBLE] with
uncertainty relation.
Let us show why.
Here is another possible experiment.
Here is an atom with its electron.
Okay?
Goes to the two possible path.
It's still one atom.
I, I'm just plotting the two
possibilities.
And now, suppose it's on one path.
The probe, what it does is to change the
orbit of the electron.
The energy level of the electron.
Now in
the electron, we have encoded which
path information, so the interference will
disappear.
Nevertheless, the nucleus is much more
massive than the electron
and the kick has been given only to the
electron.
So the whole atom which is essentially the
nucleus has not deviated at all, from each
path.
There's no delta x.
The delta p was given to the electron
which is also negligible.
So those small
delta p and small delta x are both
essentially
zero, for the center of mass of the atom.
And nevertheless the interference
disappears.
Why?
Well because again, we have encoded which
path information into the atom.
So the uncertainty relation has not much
to do, with which path information.
The uncertainty relation is about
indetermination.
It does not reflect to measurement, but to
properties of the physical object on
the study.
So, essentially you can say that particles
don't have well-defined position and
well-defined momentum.
Even before or without anyone trying to
measure them.
In this sense, it is a game.
An argument for intrinsic randomness.
The value of x and the value of b are just
not well defined out there.
I want to finish on a positive note for
you.
If you have to struggle
to become familiar with quantum physics,
as you see, even Heisenberg had too.
And made some mistakes in his popular
explanation, so.
It's really not a problem, if you find
quantum physics a bit outlandish at start.
The solution is look at the experiments.
Try to read more about the experiments
because that's the message from nature.
Don't read too much of the theory.
The theory of mathematics that are very
useful, but try to familiarize yourself
with nature.