We can spend now more time of
course presenting many, many more quantum
phenomena.
But the question that is interesting for
us in this course that is not
on quantum physics but on randomness is
whether this phenomena do demonstrate
intrinsic randomness?
So what have we seen?
We have seen some typical quantum
phenomena, interference of particles,
delocalization of particles.
We have mentioned probabilities all over
the place.
We have mentioned these uncertainty
relations that are more indetermination
relations.
And the question that I want to raise now
is, is this really random?
Or can you find a deterministic
explanation for these observations.
Of course without going all the way to the
theater of conspiracy that we introduced a
few lectures ago.
In which you believe everything in the
world, everything, absolutely
everything is determined which, but it may
be the case.
It can be falseified but it doesn't give a
very interesting view of the world and of
science.
So here is our
[UNKNOWN]
interferometer, perfectly working.
I just changed the notation a little bit.
I call now plus 1 the result of the
measurement when this detector
fires and minus 1 the result of the
measurement when this detector fires.
How would you convince a skeptic that
there is randomness there.
A skeptic may come and say, hey I don't
believe that all these devices are
behaving as they should.
I don't believe that this
is light or these are neutrons.
I don't believe anything of that.
So, how would you do?
Well the correct way would be to put
everything
in our black box, give the skeptic only
input.
The input is the choice of the difference
of length.
Between the two path.
And let the skeptic check the statistics.
And if the statistics match the ones that
are expected then maybe the skeptic will
be convinced.
But the question
is what can there be inside?
Even assuming that all the time, whenever
the skeptic puts a value of delta l.
The repeated measurements indeed produce
the desired statistics.
What can there be inside the box?
Well, there can be a simulator.
There can be a student, a competent
student, Alice, was being
told to stimulate a Mach-Zehnder
interferometer with the value of delta
l as requested by the skeptic.
Of course it doesn't need to be a real
student, a human being,
it can be a computer that has been
programmed to compute those probabilities.
In fact, you can do it in MatLab, just,
program those
statistics in MatLab and then just delete,
produce a list of numbers.
You input, you ask your skeptic friend to
input delta
l in your computer and the Matlab will
produce this
list of numbers.
But there's nothing quantum there.
So the mere observation of such statistics
does not
allow to conclude that there is anything
quantum here.
Not, of course, even worse, that it's
intrinsically random.
For instance, for Alice, what's going on
is certainly not random.
If you use a random number generator of
math lab
pseudo-random number generator, for the
computer, there's no randomness there.
It's deterministic.
Now you can say, oh maybe the black box
scenario is a bit too much.
Maybe my skeptic is accepting that there
are particles there, so how to explain
delocalization?
We have a way.
For a physicist to explain delocalization
of a particle.
And that's how some people
[UNKNOWN]
come up with some explanation.
It dates back to some ideas of Louis De
Broglie, although they have been
formalized by David Bohm.
And the idea is to consider both the
particle and the wave to be real objects.
Whatever happens.
So there is a particle there moving in
a complex landscape that is determined by
the wave.
And then with a little bit of chaos, since
the individual conditions,
since the landscape is complex, the
particle
sometimes takes one path, sometimes the
other.
And these landscapes reproduces exactly
the interference pattern.
The individual clicks are due to the
factor there is a particle
there that is not divided and
interferences are due to the landscape.
Now, these theory called Bohmian mechanics
or Bohmian determinism has.
One feature that is the wave should carry
no energy and should be unobservable.
And the adversaries of this interpretation
of this description of the
world in fact, argue that this is not a
good idea.
Because this determinism postulates the
existence
of something, this wave, unobservable in
principle.
Enough to say determinism.
And of course as people argue in science
to postulate something out
there that is observable in principle that
would never be possible to observe.
The, it's something we don't like.
Now the supporters of this interpretation
will counter arguments, saying
that its better to postulate a way of this
unobservable principle.
Than to postulate intrinsic lack of
predictability, intrinsic randomness.
So we are going to leave it here.
We are going to leave the problem open.
It seems, at least as I've presented them,
that the, so far
the claims of intrinsic randomness of
quantum physics are based on shaky ground.
Or at most, they seem to be a matter up
for endless discussions
between whether you prefer intrinsic
randomness
or determinism with unobservable objects
in physics.
But next week, I will give you the real
evidence for intrinsic randomness.
It takes two particles to convince a
skeptic, not only one.
In particular, our situation, which is
called a violation of
[INAUDIBLE]
equalities, in which no fair simulation is
possible.
Even with black boxes, and where the wave
of Bohm becomes
completely crazy, in a way that I will
define next week.
So we've reached a summary of this lecture
six.
In which my goal was to introduce
you to some phenomena described by quantum
physics.
We have seen single particle interference
with a
Mach-Zehnder setup and with a double slit
setup.
And we have discussed notions of
indistinguishability that matters of
[UNKNOWN]
of delocalization of a particle.
And then issues of uncertainty,
unpredictability, randomness probabilities
that who
have been, we are leaving pending for the
next lecture.
See you next week.