Welcome to this 6th lecture, that is the
first one of two devoted to quantum
physics.
Here is the plan of the lecture, in which
I hope
to introduce you to some phenomena that
described by quantum physics.
They're your first examples of quantum
phenomena.
In the first segment I will just mention
what
is quantum physics, and all the successes
it scored.
And some claims that I call outlandish.
Some of the changes in our world view that
are carried over by this theory.
Then, in the next segment, I will describe
two types of phenomena of interference.
One called Mach-Zehnder interferometer,
the
other called the double-slit
interferometer.
And finally I will wrap up this first
lecture by
discussing what kind of randomness have we
seen in these phenomena.
So let us start with the success of
quantum physics, and
the claims that this theory makes.
A quick history first.
It all started with people observing
phenomena.
That define a description with classical
physics.
Classical remember as we said in
the previous lecture, it means Newtonian
physics.
The physics before the 20th century.
This phenomena the observation of spectral
lines of emission and
absorption by atoms.
The famous Balmer lines, for instance.
The observation what's called the
Black-body radiation,
and what is called the photoelectric
effect.
I'm not going to enter into details of
what these are, because
I'm going to focus on other phenomena
simpler that had been noticed later.
Of course you can find all the details on
the internet.
To discover this phenomena this take us
the development of few partial models was
called
old quantum theory.
That's all patchwork where everybody tries
to address a
different problem and succeeds in solving
that particular problem.
Not many others.
So in 1900 Planck makes his famous
mathematical assumption that he
doesn't understand physically, but he
makes it and he proves it.
With that he can explain the black body
radiation.
In 1905 Einstein takes the same assumption
as Planck would explain the photoelectric
effect.
And in 1913, Miss Bohr comes up with a
model for hydrogen atom that explains the
spectral lines.
Then in 1926, after many other attempts.
A few people, Schrodinger, Heisenberg,
Born, Dirac and others
come up with what we call now quantum
theory.
In the [INAUDIBLE] and the mathematics are
still the same.
Even if of course there have been a lot of
developments.
Some of the predictions of quantum
physics.
One can,
roughly say that traditional quantum
physics deals with atoms and light.
So when it comes to atoms, you can
consider the physics
of one single atom, you can look into the
nucleus, and
then quantum physics explains
radioactivity,
another of, another phenomenon that was
discovered towards the end of the 19th
century that was unexplained.
It explains nuclear power.
It explains the sub-nuclear particles or
that is called
high energy physics of the [INAUDIBLE]
Higgs boson that was discovered very
recently.
And when one looks not at the nucleus of
the one
atom but the electrons, one can explain in
particular all these
spectral lines, that are observed in the
mission of the life
of the stars and was from some lamps also
here on earth.
If you consider more atoms, then quantum
physics code becomes much more broader.
Quantum physics explains molecules, why
two atoms of oxygen
like to come together to form the molecule
O2.
And in fact the quantum physics is at the
basic, bases of all of chemistry.
If one considers all the arrays of many
atoms like solids.
Quantum physics helps explaining sorry
does explain essentially is
the tool for condensed matter physics,
which explains why
some materials are conductors and others
semiconductors, some are insulators.
Why there is magnetism, super conductivity
and so on.
They have left light there in a corner.
Light itself is described by quantum
physics.
It's called quantum optics or quantum
electro-dynamics
and in the interaction between light and
atoms.
One explains not only the photoelectric
effect, the
original one, but many other things and
phenomena of
such things and in particular the laser is
a product of that development.
But there's much more.
So, this is just an idea of how successful
this new approach to physics is.
Then you can legitimately ask, if it
explains
so many things and, in fact, quite a
few things of those are useful in our
world and used very much like the laser.
Why don't we learn this in high school?
Well because there is a price to pay.
Sometimes when he has this kind of
explanation that
a theory is very abstract, or it's too
mathematical.
I don't really believe in these
explanations because at the end of the day
the mathematics are, yes, a little bit
advanced, but are not extremely
complicated either.
One could learn them by making the effort.
The ultimate reason that I will try to
discuss during this whole lecture
and the next is that, quantum physics is
difficult because it relies on intrinsic
randomness and this means that you can't
make an image of what happens.
By the way, this is the reason why indeed
the [UNKNOWN] of quantum
physics, if you open one of them at
random, you would find you need.
Out of focus on the mathematics, because
its hard to
give image or give intuition of what is
going on.
Little by little many people are making an
effort to make, to make quantum physics
more approachable,
but it's totally traditional treatise is
the ones
I studied for instance, they ask the
mathematics.
But the reason is not the mathematical
complication, the reason is
really the presence of intrinsic
randomness
that makes the description very hard.
So here are some quantum buzzwords related
to intrinsic atoms in one way or another.
Unpredicability, you cannot predict the
outcome
of each measurement, only it's
probability.
You make repeated measurements and you can
only predict
how often a given outcome will appear, but
you cannot predict
now in this particle of measurement which
one that will observe.
Uncertainty, that would be better called
indetermination.
That not all physical properties can have
definite values at the same time.
We are going to discuss later this lecture
the famous example
of Heisenberg uncertainty relations that
position
and momentum cannot be known
simultaneously.
Delocalization, a particle, I will put
''particle'', can explore
different regions of space as if it were a
wave.
Where as we, of course we think of a
particle as a localized object, as a
sphere being somewhere.
Entanglement, this would be the object of
the next lecture where two or
more degrees of freedom may have only
common properties and not the individual
ones.
This sounds mysterious and now we spend a
good
part of the next lecture explaining it.
Probably unless you are familiar with
these things, at this
point you would say, what the hell are you
speaking about.
And here is the plan for what I'm going to
tell you next.
For the time being, it is very legitimate
to be skeptical.
You may ask for instance of these notions
only artifacts of the theory.
How can I be sure that these notions,
these [UNKNOWN] Are really there out there
in nature.
A point I want to stress now just to
finish is that, the word quantum itself
comes from discreteness.
Because indeed at the beginning, people
noticed
in, in this phenomenon, like the black
body radiation, the photoelectric effect,
and the
spectral lines, they noticed the
discreteness of
energy levels.
They notice that some physical systems
could only take some discreet values
for the energy whereas energy supposed to
be continuous in classical physics.
But this discreetness is ultimately not
very fundamental.
In fact, we have spent a lot of
time on these lectures dealing with
discrete variables.
The coin, head or tail, the bit.
And we did not feel very bad because we
are playing with the street variables.
So ultimately it's not the discreetness
that is the core of quantum physics.
Although again, it is very important but
is the presence of intrinsic randomness.