Hell, welcome lecture number four.
This will be a short lecture.
In which we are going to describe how
physical
noise can be used as a random number
generator.
This lecture in a sense, is a transition
between
the lectures on generation on randomness
needs characterization that
we had before, and the series of lectures
on
physical randomness that would be number
five, six, and seven.
The plan of the lecture is as follows.
In the first segment, I'm going to
describe the
technical mathematical definition of what
is meant by noise.
The next two segments will be devoted to
an example of thermal noise using an
electrical resistor, and we will first do
some theory and then go to the lab
this time to see the phenomenon live.
And finally, the fourth segment is devoted
to help extract randomness from a signal
like the one of the thermal noise.
So, let us start with the mathematics of
noise.
The crucial idea is that noise is
equivalent to many frequences.
Let me introduce the famous motion of
frequency spectrum.
So here you have a very simple plot of the
curve y equal to sinus omega t.
I plotted it for the value of omega equal
to 1.
Just a normal sin function.
So in this sinusoidal function there is
one frequency which is omega.
Or, okay, sometimes is, the, typically the
frequency is rather omega divided by 2
pi, but, okay, I will use this abuse of
language call it also omega frequency.
So if I plot on a graph, the spectrum,
meaning
where are the frequencies, I would get
that there's only one
frequency at omega equal to 1.
Here are two other curves.
The black and the red one.
The black one is the curve sinus omega t
plus sinus twice omega t.
So there are two frequencies now.
Omega and 2 omega.
With the same amplitude.
The right curve is Sin wt omega t plus one
half times sin wt 2 omega t.
So the, again two frequencies,
one of them has larger amplitude than the
other.
And now we can continue adding
frequencies.
So here for instance I am plotting a
particular
curve, which is a sum of M different
frequencies.
All in the form of cosine omega times t.
If you know signals and waves or other
signal phenomena, you know that
here I could also add in principal of
phase so I could have written
here cross omega t plus phi but let's put
all the phi's equal to zero.
So here, the first graph that I'm showing
you is a plot of a sum of 10 such cosines.
The frequencies are done at random with
MatLab.
More or less according to the spectrum
shown here on the right.
So here all the frequency will have the
same
amplitude in this example, 1 over 10 in
this case.
And there
are ten particular frequencies.
The numbers are not important, and we see
already that the signal looks more noisy
than before.
Now if I add more frequencies, like for
instance I have added 40 frequencies.
The signal looks more and more noisy.
There less and less regularity into it.
So that's the main message, that more
frequency in
the spectrum means that the signal is more
noisy.
Or more precisely, what it means is that
there is little correlation between the
value of
the signal at a given time and the value
of the signal at a later time.
This means short memory, this means that
such a signal is hard to predict.
Now, in many natural sources of noise,
like the one we're going to consider
later.
They are not discreet frequencies like the
ten or 40, or two that I use so far.
But the
possible frequency from a continuous
spectrum, and this is the
case that we're going to consider so, from
now on.
In this case it's easy, also, or
especially the spectrum
is sort of compact like the drawing I have
there.
There are not many, many peaks.
It's clear what is the memory time.
The memory time is just given
by the inverse of the spectral bandwidth.
So, the larger
the number of frequencies, the spectrum,
the shorter the memory time, that
sometimes is called correlation time or
coherence time depending on the physical
phenomena,
but essentially it means the time within
which the signal has some correlation,
the signal at time tau, still knows
something about the signal time zero.
But the signal at later times starts
knowing very little,
ultimately nothing, about the signal, the
value of the signal, times 0.
This is an important relation to be kept
in mind,
that the spectral bandwidth is the inverse
of the memory time.
For those who have some knowledge of
signal
analysis, of course this should not be
confused
with the relation that the length in time
of signal times the bandwidth is larger
than one.
Here, so identity is the temporal length
of the signal.
Can be the width
of a pulse, for instance.
Obviously, we have the relation that the
time, the memory time is smaller than the
identity because there cannot be any
memory once
the signal is completely finished, when
it's zero.
But, delta T can be much much larger than
Tau.
And that a ceiling for which delta T is
equal to Tau is called Fourier limiter.
This is just a remark if you have not
followed these, okay it's not
important for what matters.
What matters in the rest is the yellow
formula.
But it might be important for those who
have some knowledge of these topics.