So after this short introduction on the
notion of noise abstractly let us consider
a particular case of noise which is the
case of thermal noise over a resistor.
So here is our resistor.
A very simple electric circuit that you
will certainly recognize from very basic
physics.
there is a current generator.
And a resister.
And as we all know the voltage drop across
the
resister is just given by the value of the
resistance
times the value of the current.
Now, if I would remove the source of
current, you would infer that the voltage
measured across the resistor is just 0.
But is it really zero?
In fact the resistor is in contact with a
thermal bath, so if we look into the
resistor,
which is in fact a piece of metal with
some characteristics, there are electrons
that are those who carry
the current normally.
Even if there is no current being enforced
on them.
They will feel the thermal excitations and
they will move at random in various
directions.
Each electron changing very frequently
because of collision
sources, because another kind of
excitation arrives on it.
So, in these particular configurations,
for instance, there is
a net current going upwards, at least a
current
of electrons going upwards.
So let's say that by convention the
voltage is positive.
Some time later, the speed of the
electrons has
changed and so now we have a different
voltage.
And so on, across the time because of
thermal fluctuations, the speed of the
electrons changes constantly and as a
result
the net voltage across the resistor also
changes.
What we are learning here is that the
famous formula V
equal R times I gives only the average
voltage.
And this is indeed 0.
But there are thermal fluctuations to the
voltage.
And these are the fluctuations we are
going to use in order to generate
randomness.
This noise is called Johnson-Nyquist
noise.
From the name of John Johnson, who first
reported it and Harry Nyquist, one
of his colleagues at Bell Labs, who
did the theoretical description for the
first time.
In
Johnson's paper we find the description of
how this noise behaves.
The mean-square potential fluctuation, so
the fluctuation square.
Over the conductor, over the resistor in
this case, is proportional
to the electrical resistance and the
absolute temperature of the conductor.
It is independent of the size, shape or
material of the conductor.
In other words, the square of the voltage
fluctuations is proportional to the
resistance times the temperature.
Let us try to derive this formula.
We probably know all from basic physics
that the power dissipated
by a resistor is the voltage squared
divided by twice the resistance.
You may also remember that, when it comes
to thermal fluctuations there
is always a KB times T appearing, where K
is Boltzmann's constant.
In fact the power of thermal fluctuations,
in this
case is given by the formula there, where
delta
f is the bandwidth of the receiver,
essentially it
means how many frequencies we detect
without a voltmeter.
And the two come from the fact that the
cable is a one
dimensional wave guide for electric and
magnetic field and these leads to a
dis-factor of two for reasons that a bit
too complicated to explain in
general but would be explained for those
who are interested in the next slide.
The formula for Johnson Niquist noise
comes by just
equating these two powers that must be
equal to equilibrium.
And we get that the square of the voltage
fluctuations is equal to
4 times k by, k B times T times R times
the bandwidth.
Here is a more rigorous derivation and
some more notes
for those who are interested but I will
not stop here.
Let me just put this predictions
in graph.
So, though it's pretty obvious.
So here is the clearly the graph.
If I plot the voltage fluctuations, as a
function of the resistor is a, square
of the voltage evacuation as a function of
the resistor is clearly a straight line.
Let us put some numbers there.
If I take one kilo-ohm of resistor, and at
room temperature and for a
bandwidth of ten kilohertz, the
fluctuations that we observe should
be of the order of 0.5 microvolts is very
little.
We will need, we will need probably an
amplifier to see them.
But another point I want to stress because
we are going to see
it as well in the lab, is that the
frequency spectrum is flat.
Essentially for, for the relevant
frequencies, all the frequencies are
present.
Remember that previously we're discussing
these frequencies spectrum, and
saying that the broader the frequency
spectrum, the more noise
is there.
Well, here we have a very flat spectrum.
So we expect a lot of noise from these
fluctuations.