And here we are back after our visit to
the lab.
Let us now discuss how randomness, is
going
to be extracted from the noise that we
observe.
The statistics of noise must first be
discussed, because for the
moment we know only little about the
distribution of our goal digits.
We know that the average is zero.
We know that the fluctuations are given by
delta V equal to square root of V square.
Where V square is given by the
Johnson-Nyquist formula.
But for random, randomness extraction, we
need to know the probability
of finding each value of the voltage, in
order to compute entropies.
Now of course, the voltage is a continuous
value, and we, we have to discretize it.
This is done by what is called analog to
digital converter.
I want to stress, however, more than the
technical aspect a more conceptual one is
that.
The observed distribution of the noise
will be enough.
Because we are dealing now with a
controlled source of noise.
We have checked that the noise is the one
that is expected for thermal noise.
And we trust physics.
That thermal noise is a phenomenon too
complex to predict.
You might ask why don't having to put just
an antenna and capture random noise from
any possible source, instead of going to
the
lab and complicating our life with a
resistor.
This is the reason.
The reason is that if you, capture some
unknown
signal, what, decidedly you don't know
what they are?
Probably they may look random to you.
But they may not be random for others.
Or they may have unwanted structures in
them, that
you don't see at first sight, but they're
there.
Where as now we know, that our resistor
noise because of the theory.
Because of a bit of physics we know that
our resistor noise, should really not have
much structure.
Okay, so we can just see what is the
observed distribution, here is
our noise.
And for each line of, with suitable
discretization of noise, we
count how many dots we have in that, in
that interval.
And it gives this distribution, that looks
pretty
much like an ocean, like a bell curve.
So this is the distribution of the noise
sent of zero.
With delta V given by the Johnson-Nyquist
noise.
But now we have the distribution of noise
much more in detail.
Now we can discuss randomness.
So here's a possible processing, you can
try
to get fair coin sequences directly out of
it.
And the way to do it would be for
instance,
out of the noise we just beam in two
intervals.
If the noise is positive you call it 0, if
it is negative you call it 1.
Of course there is much more information
there so,
you may want to try to get two bits.
You may want to get 00 if the noise is
rather high.
01 if it's intermediate high, 10 if it is
intermediate low, 11 if it's very low.
You see here that.
This can be done, but you need to adapt
carefully the
intervals in order to, for each sequence
to have the same probability.
The, the integral of the curve, the
integral of this curve, the area under
this curve here must be the same as the
area under this curve here.
Under this curve
here and under this curve here, in order
for the four sequences to have the same
probability.
You can try now just do it yourself.
Try to do it with three bits.
You need eight sequences suitably spaced.
You see, it's not very easy to do.
So simpler in fact, by employing more
efficient processing.
Is just to estimate the probabilities and
then use extractors,
as we have seen in the first lectures.
This particular analog conversion has 256
channels, so we have 256 variables.
And it's pretty clear what is the
probability of guessing.
The probability of guessing, what would
you guess is
the value of the noise if you were asked.
Well you would guess that the noise is
equal to zero.
So the probability of guessing is around
the middle there.
And how much is it?
But for this particular example,
we computed it is approximately 1%, 0.01.
So this means that the
mean-entropy, is the log on, of base 2 of
0.01, is 6.5 bits per signal.
In other word, in principle each time we
have a point
of noise, we can extract 6.5 bits.
I also want to remark that
since we have a, have a trusted source,
one can
be much less conservative than using the
Leftover Hash Lemma.
And instead of computing randomness for
the mean-entropy
we can compute randomness from the average
entropy.
The suppose Shannon entropy, and one would
get a slightly better result.
So previously we've assumed that each
value
of the voltage independent of the next
ones.
But in fact the finite bandwidth
introduces correlations.
One that we know is that there is a high
frequency cutoff.
Is of course obviously impossible not to
detect very, very high frequencies.
But because of this, we also know that
there would be some memory time.
That values of voltage within the memory
time 1 over delta
omega, that is essentially 1 over omega
max, would be correlated.
There is also low frequency cutoff, is
very
hard also to measure at very, very low
frequencies.
Here the
fact effect is less obvious, but let me
try to explain in a rapid way.
The idea here is that long sequences of
large amplitude becomes less probable than
they should be.
Remember that for a fair coin, you should
sometimes see long sequences of zeroes.
Here we have not one value but 256.
But, we should see sometimes some long
sequence of high values.
For instance something like that.
And if you see that sequence, it must be
associated to
a low frequency to a wave with a very long
wavelength.
And here is something that we may cutoff,
because of the low frequency cutoff.
So we are not going to see, these kind of
sequences of large amplitudes.
As we know, as a theory in principle
there's no problem.
We just think the real phenomenon,
estimate the probability of each sequence
and then compute the mean-entropy.
But in practice, you can easily imagine
this is not feasible.
So these correlations may create some
problems when it comes
to extracting a rigorous amount of
randomness from this data, okay.
That being said, of course, if again, we
are not
in a super paranoid scenario, we're in a
trusted scenario.
Want to extract randomness for practical
purpose, not for cryptographic ones.
There should be no de,
no big problem.
So I have reached the end of this very
short lecture.
The goal was really to show you that
we can extract randomness from a physical
noise.
The noise being phenomenon with a large
spectrum of frequencies.
I presented you an example of thermal
noise.
And I discussed how to extract randomness
and the effects of correlations.
This lecture was very short.
This leaves you more time to revisit
the first four lectures and prepare for
the first test.
Thank you, and see you next week.