After this introduction and these
theoretical explanations we are going
to observe thermal noise of a resistor in
the lab.
Before leaving the work to one of the
students here we demonstrate this
noise, I want to sketch rapidly what kind
of electronics is being used.
Remember that we want to detect voltage
fluctuations
that are in the order of half a microvolt.
This is normally
too weak to be detected directly, so an
amplifier
will be needed before sending the signal
to the oscilloscope.
The oscilloscope is a very routine device
in
a lab, for those who would not be
familiar.
Is essentially a signal analyser that can
block in
a real time, in this case the voltage
fluctuations.
So we are going to see how the resistor
produces indeed these
noise in a real time.
Now it's time to go to the lab and I leave
the string to
one of our students each and who is going
to demonstrate to determine noise.
>> Hi, I'm Ichen and today I'm about to
bring you a little visualization of this
Johnson noise.
So the Johnson noise is generated by a
resister, which is our little blue thing
here.
The good thing about this
one is that it's a variable resister,
allowing me
to change its resistance by tuning it with
a screwdriver.
But as you probably know that just a noise
at room temperature is simply too weak to
be directly measured so this is where an
amplifier comes in which is the gold box
here.
The amplifier receives the signal and
amplify it, output it to
an acidisco.
And it is on the acidisco that the signal
will be measured and displayed live on the
screen.
So now you probably don't see much here
because the
resistance now is zero and there's nothing
generating the Johnson noise,
but now I'm going to turn the resistance
to some
higher value and you may observe what's
changing on the screen.
So now we are at 0 ounce, and
I'm increasing the resistance and here we
are starting to have something oscillating
on screen.
Increasing it to a higher value.
And you can see the noise signal is much,
much stronger.
And now I'm going to the reverse.
Turning the resistance back to 0.
And
as you can see, the same thing happens as
the resistance decreases.
The signal amplitude also decreases.
And eventually leaves nothing on the
screen.
>> And we are back now so you have seen
now, how indeed,
changing the resistance changes the noise.
I want to finish on a comment, namely,
do these fluctuations obey the law that we
have seen.
Here is the result.
Ichen measured the five points in red, and
the
blue line is the theoretical curve that we
established before.
As you see, indeed, we can satisfy that,
we can be confident that
the noise that has been observed is indeed
the thermal noise of our resistor,
we are not picking up.
A different kind of knowledge, some other
sources of knowledge that will be around.