After considering various tasks in which
randomness is useful or maybe
not as we have just seen, we move now to a
series of tasks where randomness is
definitely necessary, and this is
Cryptography, where randomness is meant to
be the ignorance of the adversary.
I will devote two segments to it, the
first segment is devoted to the
task, to the implementations of
cryptography that
go under the name of secret keys.
Here is
a, here is a scenario.
There are two authorized partners that are
traditionally called Alice and Bob.
They share a secret code to communicate
between themselves.
There is an eavesdropper traditionally
called Eve,
that wants to learn to the message.
So, Alice and Bob are talking, and they
talk rubbish, according to what you
see here, but of course, this is encoded
so, so the secret code, so they
can understand what they are saying.
Eve is allowed to store, to hear this
communication, to listen to it, to
store it, maybe hoping for better times
when she will learn the secret code.
But of course, that's the goal.
The goal is that Eve should not be able to
predict what the secret code is either now
or later.
The reserve cryptography is very
interesting but
here, I will just catch very very
rapidly, and you can read it in other
sources I will suggest at the end.
Essentially, until 20th century the
history of
cryptography can be summarized in, someone
invents
a code and someone else finds how to break
it may take more time.
Sometimes it took centuries before someone
realized the code could be broken.
But that's the story.
One of the things that was noticed during
those
times is that, that could be a very bad
idea.
And the bad
idea is to trust that the protocol won't
be discovered.
The security by obscurity.
If you remember, we mentioned it already
in the previous lecture.
It may work at times, but there have been
big failures.
The two examples I have here on this slide
are both from second World War.
The case where it worked, is when the
Americans used some
Indian American tribe The Navajos to talk
plainly on the radio.
His language is very peculiar, and it was
to be expected that, it was
to be expected that the Japanese and the
Germans did not have a Navajo Indian.
But of course, if they had it, this would
have been completely insecure.
The Germans were using this famous Enigma
machine to communicate secretly with each
other.
It had some seed.
But a lot of the security of the Enigma
was relying
on the fact that nobody would understand
how the machine works, and
when Alan Turing understood how the
machine
works, to crack the code was essentially
easy.
So, this motivated of course this
Kerckhoff's principle you
see is before the second World War, but
these
kind of remarks we already made before
that you
should not trust the protocol not to be
discovered.
And so the idea is that the protocol
should be publicly known.
The only thing you have to guarantee is
the security of the key,
of the secret code.
Now I am going to show you some examples
of this and
we will insist on the fact that protocol
is known to the
[UNKNOWN].
In 1917, in fact a little bit before but
it
was not noticed and then later it was used
very often.
Someone found out that there is an
unbreakable
way of communicating, and it's called
one-time pad.
Here is the idea of the one-time pad.
Your ideal message is a binary stream.
This message has a meaning.
For instance, if I'm using the ASCII key
code, the first eight bits means H, and
the second eight bits means small I, so
I'm telling you I.
The key is the most important.
Then, you have a key.
As long as the message, drawn at random,
drawn at random is key, has no particular
meaning.
You just throw, in this case, 16 bits.
The encoding is done, is the following way
is just the
binary sum, bit by bit of the message and
the key.
You hide the message and the key one on
top of each
other and you take the binary sum bit by
bit.
Here, I try something in red and some in
blue just to, for ease of reading.
The C is a cipher, it's what is going to
be sent publicly.
So, how does it go?
Alice and Bob have their secret key.
It knows already that they are going to
encode
the letters of the alphabet using the
ASCII code.
And she knows that we're going to use
one-time pad.
The protocol is
perfectly known to Eve.
Of course, he does not know the key.
That's the thing that you have to keep
secret.
Alice wants to say hi to Bob, she encodes
with the one time pad and she sends
deciphered text.
Eve can store deciphered text.
Bob can decode because he has the key and
find out Alice is saying hi.
Eve has no clue about what's going on.
Why cannot Eve try to guess whats going
on?
Well let's prove the one time pad is
completely secure.
The claim is, if K is random for Eve,
the cipher text C carries no information
about M.
So Eve cannot learn anything by hearing
the cipher text.
Just as well she could toss a coin.
Here's the proof.
There's a more formal proof of the, of, of
the same
thing by Shannon in the 1940s but the
intuition is here.
Suppose that one
bit of the cipher text is zero.
Eve sees zero.
Now if the corresponding bit of the key is
zero, then the message was zero.
If the corresponding bit of the key is
one, then the message was one.
Eve knows nothing about the key.
So for her the message can be just as well
be zero or one, even if she hears the
cipher text zero.
So, she can just as well try to get the
message by tossing a coin that has nothing
to do with the cipher
text, similarly of course if the cipher
text is one instead of zero.
This level of security is called
informational-theoretical security or
sometimes unconditional security.
Why is it called like that?
Well, because it's opposed to security
based on
computational assumptions that we are
going to see later.
You remember I mentioned this in the first
lecture when I said that very often the
eavesdropper can get something, but it
must be limited in computational power.
In this case, however, even if the
eavesdropper had unlimited computational
power, just cannot guess it, there is no
information available for Eve.
Of course it must be said before there are
some misunderstandings that there are
conditions for unconditional security.
The key must be random for Eve, must be as
long as the message.
It must be kept secret all the time.
So, unconditional doesn't mean that you
can just do whatever you want.
Let me finish with the balance of the one
time pad.
The advantages of the one thing bad are
that it is unbreakable in principle.
Provided the key is as long as the
message, it's used
only once, unpredictable for Eve, and
doesn't leak out at some point.
There are some practical problems, though,
and this
is why this one-time pad is used rather
rarely.
The, one is the key distribution.
So once a key has been used, Alice and Bob
have to find a way of sharing a new one.
It'd be kind of like in the movies they
have to meet in
a train station, exchange a suitcase, in
which there is a new key.
There are other methods, one of them using
quantum
physics, but is always a problem to
distribute the key.
The other problem is key storage.
The key is very long, and you have to keep
it safe.
So, in as sense you put the trust one
step later; who keeps the key now?
You must trust the person of the safe,
that is keeping the key.
Ebanking; if you have a bank account that
uses ebanking, it does use one time pad,
you may have a device at home that has
some one time pad keys in it.
E-commerce and online transactions
normally don't.
And why?
Well because your computer cannot have a
one
time pad key stored for all possible
providers you
may want to buy from.
In the, next segment, we're going to see a
different
way of doing typography that is more
useful for online transactions.