We finish with something that is between a
game and
cryptography, in the sense that you see
it's a sort of game, but in which the
partners don't trust each other.
Topic of zero-knowledge proofs.
Here is the task.
Alice is a PhD student.
And she claims she has found the proof of
a fantastic theorem.
She wants to go to a conference to present
it, and
needs the approval of her supervisor, Bob.
Bob of course wants to check that Alice's
claim
is motivated and wants to learn about the
proof.
But Alice is reluctant to reveal the proof
to Bob
because the theorem is really important,
and she fears that
Bob upon hearing it just will go to his
computer,
type the proof, send it himself, and get
all the credit.
So the question
is, can Alice convince Bob that she has a
proof
without showing the actual proof to Bob.
So here's the goal.
Alice wants to convince Bob that she knows
the proof without showing the proof to
Bob.
Notice how this scenario's different.
From the secret communication we had
before.
On the one hand Alice and Bob now don't
trust each other.
On the other had
there is no Eve.
Alice and Bob don't need to be at a
distance.
They can be in the same room discussing in
the office of the supervisor.
The fact, the fact that this is possible
is based on a particular kind of
mathematical problem.
It's called three-coloring.
So let me show first.
That Alice can convince Bob that she has
proof of three coloring.
The question is,you
have a graph, like the ones shown here,
planar graph, just on a piece of paper.
Can a graph be colored with only three
colors
by making sure that two connected notes
have different colors?
You may know that this part applies us to
maps
of the world, and you know that in
general, you
need need four colors to color a map in
such
a way that two neighboring countries don't
have the same color.
But for some particular pieces of the map,
it may be possible to use three colors.
So that's the question.
And you see the two graphs I have here,
and
of course very simple and we'll use them
for illustration.
The first one is obviously three
colorable, the second one is obviously
not.
But of course if they give you a very
complicated graph, its not easy in fact
this, NP and even what people got NP
complete, to find out if given graph is
three
colorable or not.
The observation we are going to use for
the
zero knowledge proof, is that there is
obvious symmetry.
Each 3-coloring comes in six versions, six
permutations.
So here is the coloring I had before, and
clearly I can change
for isntance, here I kept the red but
again exchanged green and yellow.
I still get a valid 3-coloring.
Or here, I can change
yellow and red, still get a valid
3-coloring.
And so on.
And as you know there are six permutations
of this problem.
So, what is the goal again, okay, Alice
has found out there 3-coloring of the
graph and
wants to convince Bob that she has indeed
found it, but without revealing the
solution to Bob.
So she'll do the following.
Here is a sheet of paper in which the
graph
which has been drawn and Alice comes to
Bob's office and
says Look, I have the 3-coloring of this
graph.
Bob wants to be convinced.
Alice is keeping the real solution secret.
What she does is to hide, without Bob
watching,
her real solution under the blank piece of
paper.
And then ask Bob to unveil two out of the
four many notes.
For instance, Bob may ask, well I want to
see one and four.
Fair enough, you move one and four, and
you see they have different colors.
And then you repeat again.
So here is again the previous instance.
Hide the graph.
Reveal one and four.
In the second instance, Alice may choose a
different amutation.
She hides it.
Bob now is asking to see two and four.
Here they are.
Two and four are again different.
But model four is different from before,
because Alex has used a different
permutation.
[UNKNOWN]
Bob wants to see again one and four.
One and four are again different between
each other,
so it looks like the three coloring is
really there.
And, moreover, these two are different
from the same two in the first one.
You repeat this many times.
Now what can happen?
It may happen that Alice is caught at
fault at some point.
Okay, then she doesn't have the proof.
If Alice is never caught at fault after
some
time, Bob would sort of convinced that the
proof exists.
She must have the 3-coloring.
Of course, provided she cannot predict
which node Bob will decide
to look into in each hand, otherwise she
can easily cheat.
So here is where randomness comes into
play.
Alice must not be able to predict what Bob
does.
It means Bob must choose which nodes to
reveal at random.
Bob, in turn will not learn how
to draw the graph.
He cannot go back to his office and
publish the
proof unless he can predict which nodes
correspond to which permutation,
in which case he can solve out the
different nodes
according to the permutations and come up
with a consistent coloring.
Here again, randomness.
Alice must choose a permutation at random.
Now you may, now you may ask, fair enough,
okay amazing, we
find how to prove zero knowledge proof for
3-coloring, what if Alice's
proof is not about 3-coloring?
If, if it's about a math theorem, if it's
about the
[UNKNOWN]
conjecture or something else Here I cannot
go into
many details although the proofs are not
very difficult.
You will find them in an advanced computer
science book if you want to learn them.
But this is the idea.
The idea is a statement I have a proof of
theorem of length
n can be mapped to a, in a complicated
way, but systematic way.
And if the proof is correct, the graph is
graph is 3-colorable.
And if and only if,
in fact.
How is the argument of that one?
Well, first of all, notice that having a
proof
of a theorem is of length n is NP problem.
How do you prove that?
There is a formal proof, but you can do it
intuitively.
You know that
[INAUDIBLE]
has to find the proof but it's easy to
check a proof.
Is may, you might have felt this in
your mathematics lecture when the
professor states a theorem.
It's very obscure, how would I prove it?
Then, the professor goes to the proof.
And you check it, and the app makes sense.
So this is a exact definition of an NP
problem.
Hard to find the solution, but if someone
gives you the solution, you can check it.
And, now there is another theorem in
1970s.
Again, not a very difficult one by
Cook-Levin, that said the following.
Any NP problem can be solved If one can
solve one of the NP complete problems.
And 3-colorable is one of these problems.
That's in fact the definition of NP
complete or a consequence of the
definition.
An NP complete problem is a problem such
that if you
have it's solution you have the solution
to all possible NP problems.
That's the idea.
So essentially from if you have zero n
proof
for 3-coloring, in principle you have a
zero n proof for any possible mathematical
theorem.
I have a cryptographic remark on it.
Remember what we said that this kind of
proof relies
on Alice choosing a permutation before
learning about Bob's choices.
It's called commitment.
Of course, if Alice can chose a
permutatioin after learning
about Bob's choice, or knowing Bob's
choices, she can cheat.
And Bob must, the goal is that zero
knowledge,
the goal is that Bob must not learn which
permutation is being chosen in each run.
This can be easily guaranteed if you do it
"in person".
In an office, and you have the pieces of
paper that I was mentioning before.
You move them around, and you see that
though
I hide it before you look, and so on.
But if you want to do it within two
communicating
machines, it requires something, a
communication primitive called bit commit.
And bit commitment is not easy to
implement.
In fact, it cannot be implemented
unconditionally,
like the one-time pad.
It can only be implemented under
computational assumptions.
With these, we finish our second lecture
in which I hope to have
convinced you that unpredictability is not
always a nuisance, it can be a resource.
We have seen some tasks in which
randomness plays a role.
We spent some time discussing randomized
algorithms and the fact that maybe
randomization in that case is not useful
at the end of the day.
And then finally we discuss cryptography,
which are games where there are untrusted
parties,
and therefore we must guarantee that the,
some,
there is some randomness, some ignorance
of the
untrusted party in order to perform the
task.
See you next week.