We have seen the one time pad which
is very secure but very demanding in
resources.
Now we are going to see a different type
of cryptography that is more versatile.
Let me motivate it with online
transactions.
So, how do you make sure that
a transaction on the Internet is securely
encoded?
I divided it in four steps, although of
course the real protocol is much more
complicated.
In the first step, the company,
Alice.com, shares with some trusted
verifiers, some agencies, a
few numbers of them, are out there, some
keys.
So Alice sharing keys, public keys,
whatever they
are, will be explained later, with a
trusted verifier.
These communication can be encrypted with
one time pad, because there are few
trusted verifiers and it's only reasonable
that
Alice can communicate, can share some
secrecy,
with them.
Then comes this random client, Bob, who
wants to buy something from Alice.
Then Alice sends to Bob one of her public
keys.
Bob wants to check that the public key
comes from Alice and not from
someone in the middle who is simulating
Alice and tries to steal his credit card.
So what he does is to check with a
trusted verifier that the public key
indeed belongs to Alice.
The game
here, no problem in having one time part
can of security because there are few
trusted
verifiers, its only reasonable that you
have some
keys in your computer to talk to them.
The trusted verifier confirms that the key
belongs to Alice then Bob
sends his credit card to, number to Alice
encrypted in a suitable way.
Now, of course, there is Eve.
Eve wants to learn Bob's credit card
number.
Eve learns the Public Key that is sent
during the
step two because it's sent publicly,
there's no encryption there.
And Bob's text back contains information
about the credit card number.
So how can this be secure?
This is what we are going to discuss here.
Let me first discuss it with an example.
Take a donation box.
A donation box as you all know is an
object with a locker and with a small
slit.
In which you can put your mind.
It's very easy to put the money in, but
it's hard to get
it out unless you can open the locker, and
open the box fully.
That's the kind of idea that is used in
this public key cryptography.
If something were the, the public key is
like the box.
Bob checks that the box has been sent by
Alice and not by the eavesdropper.
And he puts his money, his credit card
number into it.
And sends it back.
And if Eve doesn't have the key, it will
be very hard for her
[COUGH]
to extract the money of.
Or the information in this case, that.
Now, let us see how we do with
mathematically.
This is the famous RSA protocol by the
names
of those who founded in 1977, Rivest,
Shamir, and Adleman.
For the anecdote goes, it was discovered
that a
few years before, in the contexts of the
intelligence
in the UK.
But the protocol was classified and was
only revealed in 1990.
So, the real inventor of the RSA is not
publicly know.
You will find this story on the Internet,
if you browse it.
The first step of RSA's preparing the
public key.
And this is something that happens only in
Alice location.
There's no Bob for the moment.
It's just a company.
And here are the mathematics.
You choose two primes at random,
they must be approximately the same size
And it must be quite big.
I will tell you later that nowadays the
primes
that are used are 150 to 160 digit each.
Multiply them, that is easy, and also
compute
this function that technical is called
Euler's totient function,
but is is very easy in this particular
case, it's just p minus 1 times Q minus 1.
Easy to compute if not p and q.
Much more difficult to compute if you know
only n.
Third step you to choose a number e
integer that has those two properties.
Is more than phi of n and co-prime with
it.
And fourth, you have to find a d such that
d
times e is an integer times phi of n, plus
1.
These two steps, three and four, can be
done with efficient computational methods
if you know some number theory.
So the whole algorithm is efficient.
Eve can easily genera-, sorry, Alice can
easily generate the Public Keys.
Now the idea behind the encoding would be
the following, that suppose I have a
message m.
And I, in terms our of an integer number,
and I
put it the power E compute this remainder
of division and
[INAUDIBLE]
cypher text, I take the cypher text and
put
into the power of D, I can retrieve the
message.
Now, Alice has prepared her public keys,
the public key will be N and E.
The private key, kept only by Alice, not
sent out, is D the, and of
course all that allows to compute D
directly, like the two factors of n, and
this phi of n.
And here how the communication with Bob,
now this
random client that comes in, wants to buy
something goes.
Alice sends n and e to Bob.
Bob encodes his message, by the process I
mentioned before, by taking
the message to the exponent e and taking
the modular of n.
So, dividing the remainder of the division
by n.
This
Cypher text and Alice as I said before can
extract the
message out by multiplying, by taking the
C to the power D.
Moreover, of course, Bob's message is not
normally a number.
An integer number is much more
complicated.
There is his name, his credit card number,
date of expiree and so on.
So there must be a procedure to transform
the real message into an integral number.
Alice and Bob must share this procedure.
Now we
have Eve.
Eve, by
[INAUDIBLE]
principle, knows that Alice and Bob are
using RSA.
She knows also how to translate an
integral number into a message.
And doing the communication, she hears N,
E and C.
Then she retrieve M.
Why she would like to find D, and D is
contained in N, but
to retrieve D from N, Eve should be able
to factor N into P and Q.
And these are a one way function.
The donation box that I mentioned before,
to multiply is easy, like
to put the money in the donation box To
factor is not.
It's like taking out the money from the
donation box from this lid.
Of course factoring is possible.
So, the security's based on Eve's limited
computational power.
The slide have, a little bit more of
mathematics for those who are interested.
I'm not going to stay here but
you can pause the presentation and read
through it, three.
Let us finish with the balance of this RSA
protocol.
What are the advantages?
The advantages are that it's very
versatile,
the key is generated only by the receiver.
Of course the choice of p and q must be
random for Eve.
The key distribution is not a problem
because the key is public.
And the key storage is only at one
location,
the one of Alice.
Potential issues, as I said, is a
securities
based on an assumption of limited
computational power.
And in fact in 2010, the 768 bit keys were
cracked.
This means 231 digits for n.
It means 120 digit numbers for the primes.
Nowadays, it's still secure to use
1024-bit
keys, so 300-digit n it means to use 150
to 160-digit primes.