Hello welcome to the second lecture.
Last week we have studied the definition
of Randomness.
This week we are going to see how
randomness can be a resource.
The plan of the lecture first the main
message, that
I've already announced, that
unpredictability,
randomness is not always a nuisance.
It can be a resource for some tasks.
Louie stopped in the first segment by
presenting a few of this tasks,
not in great detail, but just to give an
idea that
indeed its not absurd to think that
randomness is a resource.
Then second segment is devoted to
computational complexity.
These are some mathematical notions and
tools, that I have to
introduce in order to continue speaking,
in a more informed way.
The first segment is devoted to randomized
algorithms.
It's one of those task in which randomness
is supposed to help, or maybe not.
We're going to discover the debate that
has happened around this task.
The fourth and fifth segment are devoted
to Cryptography, one of them most
important applications of randomness or
secrecy is
guaranteed by the ignorance of the
adversary.
And the sixth segment would be something
very special because your knowledge proofs
is a bit mind boggling and, I hope you
will be interested by it.
So, let us move to the, to the beginning
of
this lecture.
It is a fast gallery of tasks in which
randomness is used.
These tasks can be divided in two classes.
Essentially according to the role of
randomness.
In many of these tasks, randomness is only
meant as lack of structure.
For instance, in sampling, for polls, you
sample a population, you want to sample at
random to make sure that you don't
introduce a bias
that would create problems in the
assessment, in the statistics.
Also, other tasks we are going to see in
the fur,
in the coming slides are what is called
Monte Carlo computation.
Monte Carlo is the name of the mountain,
of
the rock on which the casino in Monaco is
built.
And these task relate to optimization, to
software testing,
and also to these randomized algorithms
that
will be the object of the next segment.
And then, other tasks for which randomness
is used mostly because of secrecy or
ignorance.
And these tasks essentially the games.
In this case apart from cryptography that
would be a
big topic later, games in which randomness
guarantees that, fairness.
That players have all the same information
and not too much.
The first example of Monte Carlo method is
Optimization.
Optimization means to find the maximum
value of a function.
A function of many variables and the
function can be very complex.
Indeed this function can have many local
maxima and minima, many
peaks, many valleys, but we want to find
the global max.
The one that is really the highest peak.
Without randomness,
what will you do?
Well you can arrange a pre-established
grade on
your set of points and check the function.
Sample the function in those
pre-established
points or in some pre-established
directions.
And then you would keep the maximum
value With randomness, something else can
be done.
You can stop from a point.
At this point you study the variation
of the functioning various directions, and
then, you're choosing which direction to
move.
But you choose at random which direction
to move with suitable probabilities.
Of course, most of the time, you would
try to move in the direction where the
function
increases But these may not be the case,
and
then you'll go to the next point and
repeat.
What is the advantage of this method?
Just think that for instance that you go
back to other terministic
case without randomness, where you move
always in the direction where the
function increases.
Then for sure or almost for sure, you will
end up stuck in a local max.
Because once you're having the local
maximum function, the doesn't increase
anymore.
In the neighborhood and you stopped there.
However, with randomness, it's actually
possible to get unstuck to go down
from a local maximum to follow a direction
which the function decreases.
So this is the advantage of randomness
in this Monte Carlo method for musicians
are used
a lot in computation of physics and many
other tasks.
Another Monte Carlo method is testing a
complex software.
For instance, airplane control.
Suppose that you want to test the software
that is going to work in the air plane.
That are going to, to control in all
possible conditions.
Without randomness you should ask a team
of engineers to list all possible
emergency
situations that they can think of, and
then
you test the software, and you check if
the software can go with those emergency
situations.
With randomness, you just create
situations at random.
And see if the software can cope with
them.
What is the advantage here?
Well the advantage is clear.
Thee randomness helps not to rely on the
human
on human perception of what is likely to
happen.
That maybe a crazy bug in the software,
that non-engineer
will come about with, and however is, bug
is really serious.
If you sample at random all possible
situations, with a
very high pro, with a very high
probability, you will find.
Now this actually happens.
And the fact that our airplanes are very,
very safe is a proof that randomness is
useful.
Gambling.
Well, gambling is a very kind of special
activity.
Many studies have been devoted to it.
various activities in fact, go under the
notion of gambling.
Dart games, the famous cards, dice
roulette, the Asian contest of
pachinko in Japan, mahjong in the Chinese
world, oh there is activity of betting.
Betting on sports.
Betting on horses.
Betting on other situations of real life.
In gambling, randomness is seen
as ignorance.
So ignorance implies fairness.
And neither the client, nor the house have
privileged knowledge.
They're not suppose to have privileged
knowledge.
In this situation please remember that the
house wins on average.
So almost all the time.
If someone wins at the casino.
Is really by chance.
By a lucky strike.
But then, in on average, the house wins
all the time.
Odds are set in a way that the casino
doesn't lose.
Please remember this.
Now, of course there are plenty of
examples in the, where this fallacy is not
in place, and there have been soccer game
fixed, and all these kinds of problem.
Let me mention just two famous noncriminal
cases where the
house of a casino was broken by some smart
gambler.
Only the most famous example in history is
the one of Joseph Jagger,
an Englishman who went to Monaco, to Monte
Carlo, the casino mentioned before.
And in 1873, he noticed that one of the
roulette was not
a fair roulette.
Some numbers would come up more often than
others.
And they started betting on those numbers
and of course, they won a lot.
And there's a whole story there on how the
casino tried to change the roulette
of table and he noticed so he moved to the
other table and so on.
Another famous example, obviously some
movies or some
books about this is the MIT Blackjack
team.
These were a few people who were very good
with memory
with mathematics and they went to a
blackjack table and
managed to remember very well which cards
had been played.
And if you have that information, if you
managed to store
in your brain Which gambling you play, you
get an advantage.
Then again, there are many stories about
[UNKNOWN]
you can read about.
But these are just to show that these are
the cases where it's not
that the houses, cheating is not really
cheating, there are some people are using
addtional
information that the house have not
noticed, like in the case of the casino
Of might of Joseph Jagger, because he had
not noticed that roulette was a betrayed.
He noticed it and he could win.
That's where the lack of randomness, a bit
of knowledge
helps in changing the rules of the game.
Apart from gambling, randomness is also
useful in many other games,
those that are characterize under the
general feature of game theory.
Here is an example, the famous rock,
paper, and scissor game, where rock,
paper, scissor defeat each other, and as
you know, the best strategy for
each player is to throw each of their
choices at random with probability 1 3rd.
Why is it so?
Well, because if a player starts deviating
from the
strategy, and starts playing lets say rock
more often.
Then, the other player may start noticing
it, because at
this exchange he start playing paper more
often, that's winning.
So, you know, not to lose, as you know,
this game cannot be won.
But in order not to lose the best study is
just to draw each of the
player possibilities as random probability
of 1/3.
This is an example of what is called the
Nash equilibrium which is
presented as strategy from which each the
players do not want to deviate.
And this Nash equilibrium is mixed.
Mixed meaning precisely that it uses
randomness, The gaming itself may
sound a bit silly, but it can be used to
model this one or other ones similar ones,
very many situations in human and animal
behavior.
This leads us to another consideration
that will be done in the next slide.
The question is where is the randomness?
You can think of individuals, playing a
mixed strategy
like one in just described with rock,
paper, and scissors.
In terms of time.
And, you will think that the individuals
have really random choices.
So, here's an individual.
The circles split in three.
And that, in each arm, each individual
takes a decision.
And chooses.
Here, one of the newestchosen scissors,
the other has
chosen rock and the rock wins over the
scissors.
The next run, the players change decision.
One chooses paper, the other chooses rock,
and now continues to choose rock.
It's a possible
random decision to keep what you have.
And as a result the, the paper one now
wins.
This is supposed to mean that every play
here each time can choose its random.
Now theres a different situation though
that
this random populations play a mixed
strategy.
You can have a situation like this one.
This drawing is meant to mean that
each individual is always playing the same
strategy.
The first two on the upper left corner,
the first individual, is playing always
scissor, the second is
always playing rock, as a result, the
second always wins.
And so on.
Here you see all these individuals.
So the two populations of the column on
the left, the column
on the right some are winning, some are
losing, some are just
[INAUDIBLE]
.The statistics of these
realization is the same as the one of the
individual case.
So here, randomness is not individual but
in the sampling.
What does it mean in terms of biology, in
terms of genetics?
It means that the population may have
varying traits, something that determines
their behaviors that
is not obvious but each animal, let's say,
behaves in a given way.
So for instance, this particular animal
always very aggressive.
This other particular animal is always
very quiet.
But on average, the population has the
right fraction of aggressive animals and
quiet animals.
This is a very important slide.
We have to think about this problem.
Because, here we have the same statistical
conclusions,
and a different implications in terms of
randomness.
Ultimately, it can bee seen as the bond
between free will and determinism.
Let me put it like this, does a crab
or any other animal choose at random its
behavior?
Or is it the case that each graph has a
better mind behavior and only, on another
[INAUDIBLE]
of the population, you see the correct
statistics?
For the game to succeed, for the
equilibrium
to be reached, for the populations not to
disappear.
Of course reality's much more complex than
these games as with the
games I showed here, because there is
feedback, there is adaptive behavior.
It's known that some animals may stop
being aggressive.
Now, so, sometimes they see that they are
losing a lot.
Maybe they back up a little bit.
And so, it's not as simple, but the point
I want to make
is, the difference between the statistics
that actually that
are acheived by each individual playing a
random stratagy
verses, the whole population, playing
deterministically but with different
rates, and actually knock statistics out
of the sampling.