I've just introduced the complexity
class BPP, bounded-error probabilistic
polynomial time.
In this segment, we are going to ask
whether this
class is actually meaningful or is that
equal to B?
B is the class of the efficiently solvable
problems In a deterministic way.
And we're going to illustrate this
problem, this
question, with the story of the primality
test.
What is a primality test?
[INAUDIBLE]
primes of m in computer science books, is,
is the following task given
an integer number m, find out if it is a
prime or a composite.
The number of bits required to encode m is
essentially log 2 of m.
In fact, the smallest integer larger than
log2 of m.
So the input m is approximately 2 to the n
in terms of the number of
bits, so it's exponential in n.
By the way I want to make a remark here is
that.
If you're not very confident with bits,
the same
scaling is the scaling of the number of
digits.
The number of digits in base ten of a
number is, as we saw in
the previous lecture, related number of
bits by the log 10 of 2, which is 0.3.
So, if you are not comfortable with bits,
you can just say that the input
is exponential in the number of bits.
Now there is an obvious deterministic test
for
[INAUDIBLE],
is the following.
Take m and stop dividing by all the odd
integer numbers up to square root of m.
You divide by 3, because divide by 2, by 2
is 3 here because if the number is even,
you know, it's not prime.
So you start dividing by 3, by 5, by 7.
By is it x, not 9, eh?
11, 13 And so on, until you reach the
square root of m.
And that is what?
If you
find the divider, then m is certainly not
a prime.
If you don't find a divider, m is
certainly a prime.
So this algorithm is deterministic.
Unconditionally correct, no error.
However, as you see, there is a problem.
The problem is that the time is square
root of m,
which is 2 to the n over 2, so its
exponentially time.
Of course this is a very
trivial algorithm.
People have tried many, but, essentially
there is no much better
algorithm until the 1970s, when the first
randomized algorithm was proposed.
And here is how the, the randomized
algorithm works.
But there is an equation here, you may not
worry what
is an equation exactly means, but is
equation, is easily computable.
So here
is you can choose an integral number a.
And compute this remainder, a to the power
of m minus one over
two modular m, and compare it with the
something is called Jacobi symbol.
Whatever, I have some notions later of
modularity and so on, but if you're
not familiar just think that this simple
equation is something you can compute
easy.
And now, what is interesting here is that
if m is a prime
number, if the equation is true for all
values of a, what if m is composite?
Then the equation is satisfied by
approximately half the values
of a, if all the other half, it would
fail.
So what is the idea of randomized
algorithm?
The idea is pick a number of a at random,
and try your luck.
So let's go through the algorithm.
You pick one value of a at random, is the
equation there satisfied?
This you can check rapidly.
No.
It's not satisfied.
Then, m is not a prime, and you close
there.
Is the equation satisfied?
Then you go no.
And m could be a prime, or you could have
chosen the wrong value
of a, one of those for which the equation
is satisfied, also for non-prime numbers.
And the question would be, do you want to
try again?
If yes, okay, try again.
If no, guess that
m is a prime.
So you can repeat these, picking a a few
times, and it turns out, as I cannot prove
here, but the
probability of guessing wrongly decreases
exponentially with the number of calls.
So if you call a only once, you can get
some error.
If you call the a twice or three times or
four times then the error decreases and
decreases and decreases.
So this test is ultimately very precise.
It will almost always guess correctly.
This is the Solovay-Strassen algorithm
1973.
It turns out that the scales as the cubic
algorithm of m.
So scales like N to the cube polynomial.
Great.
There have
been more efficient algorithms.
One is called Miller-Rabin 1974, then
others.
This was the first type of randomized
algorithms and when the idea was out,
of course, many other people started
finding
many other randomized algorithm for
different problems.
And the conjecture has been for many years
that BPP is probably larger than P.
Or, in everyday terms, that randomness
really helps.
In simplifying computer short tasks, or
maybe it doesn't.
In 2002 came a great surprise, three
researchers Agrawal, Kayal and Saxena
found a deterministic algorithm that
scales log arithmetically for primality,
so they bring the primality back into P.
And after that there has been a improved
version and now that
I think, as far as I know the best version
has log to the power 6 of m.
So O to the N to the 6.
The algorithm is a bit complicated to
explain, but it works and it's efficient.
Since then, de-randomization has become
one of the big topics in computer science.
De-randomization mean take now one of the
successful, randomized
algorithms and try to find out
non-randomized algorithm, a deterministic
algorithm that is just as good.
So maybe BPP is equal to P after all.