In the second segment we are going to
pause a moment from the description of
tasks, and introduce some mathematical
notions very
elementary ones from the field of
computational complexity.
Computational complexity deals with
Scaling.
How a surface that computes a function
scales with the size of the input.
So here's the example.
You have an input, x, you want
to compute a function, f of x.
For these, you have a circuit.
Acircuit has a number of registers that
are called
a space, the number of registers that are
used to
encode input, and some other registers
that can be used
as memory that can, may be necessary for
the computation.
A circuit also has number of gates, and
this is called the time.
The time it takes to get rid of action, f
of x.
Now what I can see, I want to compute the
same function but for a larger input.
Then of course if we need more space, the
number of registers
must be bigger both to encode the input
and for the memory.
And then we need more time.
The number of gates will be larger.
Computation complexity is about how do
these time and the space change
with n?
n being the size of the input.
Let me go through one example.
Here's a multiplicaion in binary.
Is very simple.
In fact it's done with the same rule as in
primary school.
5 times 3, 5 is 101 in binary, 3 is 11.
How do you multiply them?
You take this number here, 1, and you
multiply the first register,
you get 101 again, then you move digit to
the left,
and you multiply now the second digit by
again, the first 0.
And you get this, you sum the two numbers
and you get 1111.
Which is 15 which we don't need a correct
answer.
So how do you do a circuit that the
[UNKNOWN]
computation is a circuit.
I have an input which is five and three.
I want to compute five times three.
In this particular example, it is not
optimized.
I will need four memory adjusters.
So what I am going to do is to take the
first one.
Multiply it by this one which is that one
and who
the result of the multiplication in this
region,
so the zero will be switched to one.
I repeat these for the other viewers so
in this moment here I have computed these
101.
And now I do the same by using this
control the second bit.
Here it is.
And on each line where there are two
adjusts, I put the binary sign.
The result would be 1111.
So let's count how many days and how many
of registers
I have.
The input is N bits.
I need, more or less, N bits of memory, as
you can see here.
Essentially yeah, I need one, one for each
of these
and for each of those, sort of for the
each
of the bits of the type So the size of,
the total size of the input, the total
space will be
[INAUDIBLE].
How many gates do I need?
Well, in this particular example, I need
approximately N over 2 squared.
It can be improved.
Why N over 2 squared?
Well, the two numbers, if you want to
multiply, are typically The same
size, so N over 2 for the first, N over 2
for the second.
And then each number of the first must be
multiplied by the each number
of the second, so in this particular
example I had N over 2 squared.
What matters is not this, this circuit
is optimum.
Again I repeat it's not.
But just to give an idea on how
you compute time and space in these
calculations.
So certainly this computational seems to
be rather efficient.
Indeed what kind of scalings are usual?
There are three of them that are very
famous.
And there are plenty of intermediate ones
that can be discussed.
The very favorable scaling is logarithmic,
if the space all
the time of the
[UNKNOWN]
scales only logarithmically with the input
size then these are extremely efficient
computation.
Then there is the polynomial scaling,
polynomial, here, the one I
plotted this N squared, but it could be N,
it could
be N cube, it could be N to the 10, it
could be N to the 20, anything that is
polynomial, is favorable.
Of course, its not as good as logarithmic,
but
it can be managed What is really
unmanageable is
the other one is exponential.
Exponential would be two to the n, ten to
the n, these kind of functions.
These one's grow far to fast for our
computation to be effective.
I want to also introduce a frequent
notation, there are many of those
but this is always the most famous one Is
the big O notation.
So a function f of n is big o of small f
and n.
If for lage n so when
M becomes big.
They essentially differ by a
[INAUDIBLE].
So f of n is always bounded from above by
a constant.
Of course not ifinity.
Times small f of n, then you would write
that f is O of small f.
Let's give a few examples, 1000000 log N
is O of log N.
Right, by definition, they're the constant
clear is N.
N plus log N.
Is
O of N.
Because log N varies very, very little as
we have seen compared to M So essentially
what we can say is if N becomes large we
can forget about the log N part.
E to the N is 2 to the N log 2 of e.
And so it's 2 to the O of N.
This is what is meant by scaling
logarithmic, polynomial or exponential.
It means that, so if an algorithm scales
logarithmicly it
can scale logarithmic with a factor of 1
million in front.
Start to one meter is not supposed to be
detrimental.
It's really just scaling.
The function of M that matters.
Now complexity classes.
There are many.
In fact, I will point you later to a
website where there are 500 listed.
I want to introduce three of them.
First two most famous ones of P and NP.
P means polynomial time.
And, you know, if the time is polynomial,
it means that the problem is efficient
disorder.
NP is this awful name non-deterministic
polynomial time, it's actually
means that it's efficiently verifiable if
I give you a solution.
Let me give you an example, the travelling
salesman problem, so
here is the problem, there are towns
linked by some roads.
And the salesman want to go all, so all
the
towns, if possible only once, and in the
shortest possible path.
Or with the path of length L.
Now you look at the graph, especially if
the graph is
more complicated than this one, you will
find it very difficult to
find the path, but if I give you a path
It's a
matter of trivial checking to verify that
this path is indeed lengthened.
So this is an example of NP problem.
Keep in mind th-, keep in mind that the,
it's still possible that P maybe equal to
NP.
It is still possible that all problems
that are efficiently verifiable could be
factor computations that can be verified
efficiently and in fact be efficiently
solvable.
Not many people believe it, many strange
things will
happen, but has not yet proved that these
differ.
And, last computation in our class I want
to mention
is BPP's.
Here is where randomness matters.
BPP stands for bounded error probabilistic
polynomial time.
So what does it mean?
We have a circuit such that The
time is more than polynomial in principle.
But,
if I allow a random input the time because
polynomial.
With some error.
That's why it, it says bounded error
probabilistic polynomial time.
So probabilistic refers to the fact you
are using randomness Bounded
arrow means, that made, you can allow that
the computation fails sometimes.
And this class is the one we are going to
discuss in the next statement.