I'm going to, to introduce the idea
of deterministic chaos, with a very
familiar example.
The example of predicting the weather, or
weather forecast.
How is weather forecast down today.
The recipe goes as follows.
There is a preparation phase, in which one
has to define a
grid on a portion of the Earth, and define
the meaningful variables.
That are going to be considered
inside the grid.
Typically, the pressure, the temperature,
the humidity, the wind, whatever
is needed to describe the weather in an
accurate way.
Then, one is to specify the initial
conditions in each point of the grid.
This is the value of the variables now.
What is the weather like today?
And then what uses evolution equations
from physics,
from fluid dynamics, from thermodynamics
to compute how
the weather will evolve in the coming
days?
Let us give a look to the computation of
complexity of these procedure.
Assuming for a moment the evolution
equations are perfectly correct, if I want
more precision, I will need to create a
smaller mesh in the grid.
And this leads to
more computation.
How much more?
Here is a grid with two cubes,
that describes the weather to some decent
precision.
And I want to double the precision.
Then, these cubes are three dimensional.
So, each time I double the precision, it
creates 8 cubes in each of the previous
cubes.
This means that each time the precision is
double,
the number of cells is multiplied by 8.
Or in other terms, the number of cells
grows as 8 to the power n, with
n the number of times the, we want to
increase the precision by a factor of 2.
This is one is exponential growth.
That mean that, the computational
complexity is very high.
What about the evolution equations
themselves?
There are many.
I'm not going to enter into details but
one
that is inescapable is the Navier-Stokes
equation,
that describe the motion of a fluid.
Here I've written it.
On the left hand side you find the
variables
that describe the fluid, the density and
the speed.
On the right hand side you find all that
acts on the fluid.
The pressure, some form of stress.
The forces,
for instance gravity that obviously as on
the air molecules as well.
And these variables require further
modelling because they
depend themselves on the density on the
speed.
This equation is of the same form as the
famous Newton equation f equal to ma.
In fact, as written here, would be rather
ma equal to f.
The acceleration is the property of the
particle in the force, that f
is the force that acts on it, and here we
have the
acts of the fluid on the left and the
forces on the right.
I'm not going to speak a lot about these
equation but just want to mention that it
is not even known in the most general
case whether these equation have a
solution at all.
It is known that has a solutions
in some modified version, in some
simplified version,
but whether it has a solution in general,
it is one of the most complicated
open problems in mathematics.
So with this what one can do?
Well, here is something that a person
called
Edward Lorenz debuted in 1960s or end of
1950s.
He took the Navier-Stokes equations
already with some approximation.
He added something that is called
the Condition of Incompressibility for the
fluid.
He added an equation for heat transfer.
Notice that in the Navier-Stokes
equation we don't have any mention of
temperature that is obviously an important
variable.
When it comes to weather, he need a
few further manipulations, some
assumptions on the physics and
you got the system of free equations
written on
the right, for the whole weather, on a
surface.
On a surface of the earth.
So, what are the characteristics of three
equations.
First of all notice that, we have only
three real numbers there x,
y, and z.
We don't have anymore vector fields like
the speed before.
X is related to the velocity, and y
and z are related to the variations of
temperature.
The original Lorenz model had 12
variables, but Lorenz
himself simplified down to this one a few
years later.
Also we have removed all the derivatives
in space.
In the previous
equation, the Navier-Stokes equation,
there were variations
of speed and of pressure, across the
space.
Here everything has been absolved in the
assumptions and the manipulations that
have been done.
And we are left only with derivatives in
time.
This is what's called an ordinary
differential equation.
And, another noticeable feature is that
there are no
linear terms, terms where the variable
apply, appear not
by themselves in this case they appear by
multiplying two of
them instead in the second equation and XY
in the third equation.
And we come to the discovery of
the domesticate cares it was a serendipity
discovery.
Serendipity means precisely a discovery
that is made by chance, Lorenz,
around 1960 bought a computer, and tried
to do computer prediction,
computer forecast of the weather with his
no linear set of equations.
One day he decided to check his program,
by
running the calculation again for the same
initial conditions.
And what he found is that after some time,
the prediction changed completely.
So, at the beginning, he thought it was a
bug in the program or in the computer.
But looking more carefully, he realized
what really happened.
That he had not used exactly the
same initial conditions.
He had rounded them to the 4th significant
digit.
So instead of, let's say, 5.0013 He wrote
5.001.
So, what he discovered is that the
computer was working but the system
of equation was behaving very differently
for
some initial conditions that were very
similar.
It was sensitivity to initial conditions
that led to the deviation.
Later he wrote, this discovered in 1963 in
a paper, and in 1972, in a talk
he mentioned for the first time his
metaphor
of the butterfly effect, that nowadays
everybody probably knows.
Namely that the motion of the wings of a
butterfly in Brazil
can influence the weather in the United
States a few weeks later.
The explosion of interest in this topic
happened only 1975.
Before we move to more chaos, let me
stress
a few things.
[UNKNOWN]
We are here, we have seen a
simple deterministic and unpredictable
system of equations.
I want to stress that the fact that the
weather itself is hard
to predict is a no-brainier, because the
system is just too complex to model.
If I would only go around saying the
weather is hard to predict, you could
say well that's not a real discovery, it's
the same as the noise of last week.
That's too many variables.
However what Lorenz
discovered is that even simple
mathematical systems, only
three variables, ordinary differential
equations can be chaotic.
In the literature on chaos by the way, the
word chaotic is referred
to precisely this behaviour or sensitivity
to
initial conditions of the variables under
study.
And randonmess, random is used for noise
coming from other sources.
And let us just finish by noticing that
even if sometimes we complain,
prediction of the weather is quite an
achievement.
It's not an easy task.