We've come to last segment of these
lecture that as I announced is
devoted to two topics to related to chaos
and also related to each other.
The topic of fractals and the topic of
power laws.
Let us start with a very innocent-looking
map.
You remember our logistic map.
This one, is another possible map.
It takes a number, z.
This time it must be a complex number.
Squares it, here I have a reminder of how
you square a complex number.
You add another complex number c, always
the same.
And this new number defines the number z,
at the following iteration.
So you see there below how it goes, you
start with z0.
z1 would be z0 squared plus c.
z2 would be z0 squared plus c, squared
plus c, and so on.
Z square, also for complex number, is a
function that normally grows.
So, in fact, it can be checked.
It's not difficult to realize that for
most values of z0
and c, the iteration of zk will just tend
to infinity.
Zk squared would be bigger than zk and
adding c, it
may also make it bigger and essentially
the whole thing explodes.
Of course, there are values of z0 and c
for which the map goes to 0.
Or for which it remains bounded.
So, we can ask a few questions.
For instance, if I fix c, what are the
values
of z0 such that z k is escapes to
infinity?
Or conversely, what are the values of z0,
such that k, zk remains bounded?
You can also ask the opposite question.
If I fixed at z0, what are the value
of c such that the iteration escapes to
infinity?
The answer to the first question is called
a julia set.
In fact, there is a particular case of a
julia set.
I should say, julia probably because its a
French mathematician.
So the question I repeat it is for a fixed
value of c,
which are the values of z0, such that the
iteration blows up?
Okay, if c is equal to 0, then the
iteration is
zk plus 1 is equal to zk squared.
We know the answer to that one, is
a circle of radius one, If z0 is smaller
than 1, the iteration will go to 0.
The square, square, square are numbers
more than 1, goes to 0.
If they are, the z0 is larger than 1, it
will blow up.
If z0 is equal to 1, it stays there.
Okay, so what happens if we change c
naught?
Here is a negative c and you see that the
set is not easy to identify.
By the way, I want to stress that the
boundary is essentially what matters here.
Inside the boundary what is red in this
drawing, are the points that will go to 0.
Outside the boundary are all the points
that will go to infinity, at different
speeds.
That's why there are some coloring there
that is
for artistic reasons But what really
matters is the boundary.
The boundary of the points that do not
blow up, and do not go to 0.
Okay, so, let's change again a little bit
c.
And suddenly
we see, amazingly complex and beautiful
behavior of the boundary.
The set, that before was connect has blown
up, and is kind of stars.
And you see I've modified just the
imaginary part of
c from 0.6 to, sorry minus 0.6 to minus
0.66.
What happens if one takes a much larger
value?
Then as expected, essentially everything
blows up.
You can see some islands somewhere, some
specific points where it
doesn't blow up, but it's completely
disconnected and not very interesting.
So here's another beautiful example just
for the pleasure of
the eyes, is c equals 0.35 plus i times
0.36.
And again I want to stress that the Julia
set is the boundary.
And what is inside the boundary here in
orange, is what, goes to 0.
What is the outside the boundary here in
green is what goes to infinity.
So you see how a very simple map like,
square the number, add a
complex number and repeat it again, can be
twice to extremely complicated structures.
Now the answer to the other question is
even more famous.
It's the famous Mandelbrot set.
So for fixed z and I, z0 and I chose z0
equal
to 0.
What are the values of c such that now the
iteration will explode?
That's the result.
And again what you have to concentrate on,
is the boundary of that set.
In the blue, light blue region, at the
point for which the iteration would go to
0.
The red points are the boundary.
Outside the boundary, you have all the
points that
will go to infinity again at different
speeds, and that's
what allows people to call us and create
more beautiful images.
There is in fact a relationship between
the Mandelbrot set and the Julia set,
if you plot the Julia set's corresponding
to the c, remember zero zero was a
circle, then we had this one, zero point,
minus 0.21 minus 0.6.
The other one, the beautiful one.
There, another beautiful one up there.
One completely
is connected out there.
You may guess what is the relation, and in
fact, it's true.
Is that the Julia set is connected, if and
only if,
the point c is inside the curve defined by
the Mandelbrot boundary.
And it's disconnected if it is outside.
Another very famous problem with the
Mandelbrot set, is it's self similarity.
Supposed you zone in, on that path for
instance, you see
the yellow dot down there, and also some
small, smaller yellow dots.
If you would zoom more and more in,
you find that these structures have the
same form.
As the original Mandelbrot set.
Again now don't do it here because you
can find amazing animations of these on
the internet.
You just go and find them.
But it's probably the self-similarity is
what I'm going
to explore for the next topic which is the
power
of laws.
So what is self-similarity?
Well, it means that it's similar to itself
but in this case it
means that it looks the same when you zoom
in, in some places.
You have some visual examples in nature
and that's why fractals is kind of
complicated
patterns look very familiar to us because
they
remind us of something we see in nature.
For instance, stones, are a very clear
example.
If you see a photo
of only stones, you don't know if these
are boulders or just small pebbles.
And that's the reason why for instance,
it's hard to estimate distances on
mountains.
If you go to an excursion in the mountain,
you know it's very hard
to estimate how far a peak is, because the
stones look all the same.
Another example are coast lines.
Even galaxies and large structures in the
universe form fractal sets.
Examples of self-similarity mathematics
apart from
fractals of these power laws that I'm
going to present in the next fuse lights.
So, this is a very simple example.
A power law is nothing that a function
that is
a constant and then x to the power of
something.
Something doesn't need to be an integer
number, it can
be any real number, what that means if I
zoom?
By zoom I mean that I changed the variable
x to variable y, that is b times x.
Is a scaling up,
or scaling down if b is more than 1.
And F of y is F of b of x, become C
times b to the power alpha times x to the
power alpha.
So it's another constant, times x to the
So the function looks exactly the same, if
I zoom.
It's just the constant in front of it
changes.
I will explain these with very relevant
example, which is the Gutenberg-Ricther
law for earthquakes.
That is an empirical law.
It's hard to demonstrate why people have
tried.
But it's something very hm, matched by
observations.
Here is a law that relates number of
earthquakes in
a given region with their amplitude of the
seismic waves.
And it says that, there are essentially,
this kind of power law.
A to the power of minus b,
b a number close to one.
between the number of earthquakes and the
number, and their amplitude.
So,you find that the larger the amplitude,
the fewer earthquakes are there, it's
called.
Notice that this is usually given as an
exponential law,
but by defining the magnitude as the
logarithm of the amplitude.
So in fact, it's a power law but you
can define the logarithm and then it
becomes, looks, it,
you may look, to make it exponential.
So, what I want ask is the following
question,
it sounds artificial, but I will bring it
home later.
Does nature choose earthquakes by tossing
coins?
What do I mean by that?
It means that, there is an earthquake of
amplitude 1.
Each time something happens and
equivalently
to tossing a coin and finding 10.
That is earthquake of amplitude 2.
Each time a sequence 00 is found in a fair
coin.
Is an earthquake amplitude 3, each time a
sequence
000 is find in a fair coin and so on.
Do the statistics of earthquakes, as a
function of
the amplitude, behave like the statistics
of a fair coin?
Well, let's check.
For a fair coin, you have this ratio.
Remember the fair coin, the probability is
1 over 2 to the n.
So, the number of sequences with n 0s.
Is related to number of sequences of m 0s
by that exponential relation.
For the Gutenberg-Richter law, the number
of earthquakes
of amplitude n is related to the number
of earthquakes of amplitude m, by a
fraction n over m to the power minus b.
Again,b is approximately 1.
So, let's compare the two.
Let's assume that an earthquake of
magnitude 1, so amplitude
10 happens every hour in some particular
region of the world.
What is the frequency of earthquakes of
magnitude 8?
So, the amplitude 10 to the 8.
Like the most destructive ones that we
have here on earth.
If
I take the Gutenberg-Richter law, then
these magnitude 8 earthquake happen
once every ten to the seventh hours which
means every 1100 years.
Of, of course, it's
a very approximate model, but it makes
sense.
Fortunate these very destructive
earthquakes in a given part of
the world happen, yeah indeed every
century, every some centuries.
If you use the fair coin, these
destructive earthquakes
should happen every 2 to the 10 to the 8
hours,
minus a 10 it doesn't really matter.
Now for comparison the age of the
universe at 13 billion years is 2 to the
46 hours.
So essentially it means,that if the
earthquakes would follow
a fair coin statistics, destructive
earthquakes would never happen.
Which would be very good for us but that's
not how nature works.
The answer is no it does not.
The statistics of earthquakes does not
follow the ones of fair coin.
Now the last bad news is that, as you
certainly know
the fact that we know the statistical
earthquakes doesn't
mean that we are able to predict them
better.
It just that we know how probable it is,
that a destructive earthquake will happen.
We've come to the end of this lecture 5,
so let me summarize, the main message I
want to send across was that sometimes
deterministic does
not mean predictable because we don't have
unlimited computational
power and precision.
I started with an introduction on physical
determinism and indeterminism.
We discussed precisely this topic of chaos
of
the deterministic systems that can be
unpredictable nevertheless.
I gave a few examples; complex systems
like the weather that would rather be
called
noise; simple systems like models of the
weather, the Lorenz model or the logistic
map.
And even
closed systems, systems that do not have
dissipation.
But there are many body systems like the
many planet motion.
And in the lecture after showing some
beautiful factors, I mention that there
exists statistics
out there in the world that behave like
power laws and not like fair coins.
Thank you and see you next week.