I'm going now to illustrate the notion of
deterministic cares, with what
is possible the simplest example, even
simpler than the model of Lorenz.
This example is called the logistic map.
Its a time evolution by this three steps.
So instead of having differential
equations, instead
of having derivatives with respect to
time,
We just had the relation between what
happens at the following step as a
function
of the value of the variable, at the
previous step.
It's a simple quadratic equation with a
parameter mu.
This model had a initial motivation as a
model for evolution of populations.
But nowadays it's not used as such, it's
just used as
the simplest example of a chaotic map with
a rich behavior.
So in order to see what happens with
these iteration, with this evolution, we
are going
to concentrate on the whole of the
parameter mu.
If mu is small, the behavior is not
chaotic.
It's very regular and very easy to
explain.
In fact if, for instance if mu is more
than 1, any initial population just dies
out with time.
You see in this graph, three initial
populations, 0.5, 0.3 and 0.1.
And all of them decay down to zero in a
few iterations.
If mu is between one and two, the behavior
is also rather predictable.
Namely any population would converge to a
given value, the same
one for all of them given by mu minus 1
over mu.
Now, if mu is larger than two.
But still below three, something else
happens.
The ultimate behavior or what is called
asymtotic
behavior or the long time behavior, is the
same.
It will stabilize the population, will
stabilize to
the same value mu minus 1 over mu.
But it does it with some oscillations, not
monotonically as we saw before.
Something more dramatic happens if you
cross the boundary of three.
From mu larger than three and smaller than
that other particular value, any
population initially at
any value will, will end up oscillating
between two values.
This behavior is called bifurcation.
It means that what was previously a unique
equilibrium point,
the mu minus 1 over mu, becomes now a
cycle, an equilibrium cycle.
So there is no equilibrium point but
there's an oscillation, between one point
and another,
and it back to the first and back to the
second, and so on forever.
Here is, I plotted it again on longer
scale.
One of the previous curves, of period 2.
Now let's see what happens when mu
increases again a little bit.
When mu goes around 3.5, the behavior
looks also very oscillatory, but is
different from
the previous one, in that, now the
oscilation
is among four values instead of two
values.
So we say that this is an oscillation of
period 4.
And if mu is only slightly larger, 3.56
now, there is an oscillation
of period 8, an oscillation among eight
possible values and so on.
There will be an oscillation for mu
slightly
larger of period 16, 32, 64 and so on.
And if our critical value around 3.66,
there are
just too many points to detect a
meaningful oscillation.
At that point, the system becomes chaotic.
Let's see what happens for mu equals 3.9
just as an example.
Here is a clear example of chaotic
behavior.
You see the three curves corresponding to
three initial conditions.
And these initial conditions are very,
very close to each other.
They differ in the fourth digit x1 0.2999,
or
x1, 0.3000, or x1 0.3001.
You see that in the first
10 iterations or so, 10 to 15 iterations,
the three curves are very similar.
Suddenly, around the 15th iteration.
The three curves start deviating
significantly from each other.
And at some point there is no relation any
more.
You see here for instance, the blue curve
is almost flat.
The other
two are wildly oscillating.
Now, here is the red curve that is flat.
Sometimes it's the green curve of is flat
here and here
and the other oscillate and oscillations
don't correspond to each other.
And now I can come to the former
definition of chaos.
The plot is slightly differnet because I
changed again the mu.
Now its 3.94 this time.
As I said a couple of times before.
Chaos is defined by sensitivity to the
initial
conditions, that is very clearly
demonstrated by these curves.
But another important feature of chaos is
mixing.
Mixing means that each evolution for every
possible initial conditions explores
almost all possible values.
What does it mean?
Suppose that you have another system that
is sensitive to initial
conditions, that is a ball on the top of a
hill.
Of course if you put the ball.
Is light in the right or is light on the
left, the ball will
fall into two different, very different
values.
So it's sensitive to initial conditions.
But the system is not chaotic, because the
long time
behavior is just to be in one valley or
another.
Here, you see that, let's take the red
curve, it
takes very high values, very low values,
some intermediate values.
So and, and these continuous all the time.
So that's the idea of mixing.
That all values or almost all
values, are taken at some point by the
evolution.
This makes it hard to predict in the long
run.
As a random number generator, such a
process is not really amazing.
We have just said that its hard to predict
in the long term.
However, it's easy to predict in the short
term.
So one could consider using these
processes on a number generator,
by taking long steps, like from here to
here for instance.
But the problem is that it's not
very efficient.
Because it's many iterations of the map,
in order
to adjust one step of the random number
generator.
In fact as random number generator it is
not particular interesting.
But I have shown it as a clear example of
a chaotic system, and a very simple one.
One single variable.