I'm pretty convinvced that the best way to
learn about chaos and
all the systems that exhibit chaos is to
just browse the Internet.
There are amazing websites with beautiful
photos, animations, descriptions.
I will not spend too much time here.
But before you browse, I just want to
introduce you to
the broad classes of chaos that has been
de, has been described.
Just to give you some ideas.
And then really please after that browse
the internet and find.
How many interesting things have been done
in the past 40 years or so?
First of all, there is a traditional
division of
physical systems, dynamical systems, into
closed and open systems.
The closed systems are called also
"conservative",
no pun intended for politics; or
"Hamiltonian."
The open systems are sometimes called
"dissipative."
What is a closed system?
It's a system that is considered as
completely isolated, from the rest of the
universe.
As a consequence, the energy of a closed
system is conserved.
That is why it's called a conservative
system.
During the evolution the energy of the
degrees of freedom under study don't
change.
Of course, the closed systems are a
theoretical idealization.
There is no real closed systems, but If
you think of a typical example that are
planets.
It's true that there is very, very, very
little dust in open space.
So you can safely consider that a planet
is not feeling any friction.
The only interaction it feels is
the interaction with the other celestial
bodies.
Other examples are essentially most of you
studied in high school mechanics.
For instances ideal springs,
ideal pendula and so on.
Dissipative system or open systems on the
contrary,
are those that exchange energy with other
systems.
In this case, the evolution goes toward an
attractor.
I'm going to explain what is this in the
next slide.
Many examples, again essentially
everything that
you see around you, interacts with
environment.
But, a very dramatic example, for instance
turbulence.
Double end flow of water for instance.
This is due to the interaction with the
boundaries of the channel
or the sea or the river on which the water
is propagating.
The Lorenz map is dissipative, the
logistic map is also a dissipative one.
It's this trait in time as we said.
Let us start with open system first.
Of course if the open system is pure of
dissipation.
Namely the energy of the system is lost
from
the system to the environment, then the
system stops.
In this case what is called the attractor
is just a point.
Is a point of the mathematician that
describes the state of the system being
stopped.
If there is both dissipation and drive,
so the energy of the system gives energy
outside, but also receives energy from
the outer world.
Then there are essentially two kind of
behaviours.
The system may oscillate with one or more
frequencies.
In this case the attractor is a cycle, or
the system may become chaotic.
And the attractor become what is called
the strange attractor.
And again, if you go to the internet you
can browse you
would find the beautiful strange attractor
of the Lorenz system, and many others.
Now to be chaotic,
just for your information, I'm not going
to give the details now.
An all consistent requires at least three
variables for
continuous time, as we have seen in the
Lorenz model.
However, for this three time, as we seen
with
the logistic map, it can be just one
variable.
An interesting question is, how is
possible that some
trajectories go all of them, to a given
attractor.
To a given set of trajectories that these
ultimately,
they stay there.
While showing sensitivity to initial
conditions.
If all the trajectories end up in the
attractor then,
you may think oh, there is no sensitivity
to initial conditions.
In fact that can be, that there is a
condition for that,
is that the attractor must be what is
called a fractal object.
And I'm going to present some fractals in
the next segment.
Let us now move to closed systems.
And the first example, I want to discuss
is
the famous three body problem.
Is a problem essentially in Astronomy
although you can formulate for other
situations.
In which you don't consider only for
instance the
earth and the sun or the earth and the
moon.
But you consider the three of them, the
sun, the earth, and the moon.
In fact here, instead I will consider an
example that is more specific for chaos.
That is, the planet Saturn, one of its
satellites called Mimas.
And the famous rings of Saturn,
represented by these three rings.
In fact of course as you know there are
many more.
So, why is it a closed system?
Well, because again there is no dust out
there, so there is only these body there.
There is no interaction with anything
else.
No dissipation, and normal orbital
behaviour.
And we know from Kepler's law, that the
period of an orbit depends on the
distance,
as the square of the period be
proportional
to the radius of the orbit to the cube.
In fact its not the radius but the,
largest semi axis of the ellipse.
Now, here we are in a situation where I
have this three grains of dust.
And at that particular position at the
given
time, and the, the moon Mimas at that
position.
So what is happening?
Well because of tidal forces,
three grain of dust would be attracted
towards Mimas.
Then time goes by, all these systems
rotate around Saturn, in first
approximation at least.
And at a later time, here is the
situation.
On the, inner orbit, the period is faster,
so it the period is longer.
The frequency is faster, so the grain of
dust in the inner orbit has gone further.
In the central orbit,
the grain of dust is back at the same
position.
And in the outer orbit, the grain of dust
is delayed.
And mine must happens to be back in the
same position as before.
So what happens here?
The two, internal and external grain of
dust feel a different attraction than
before.
Where as the one in the central
orbit feels exactly the same attraction as
before.
Now you repeat this process many, many
times, and you
realize that the grains of dust in the
central orbit.
Will constantly feel the same kind of
attraction, so this
attraction will accumulate over time, so
that orbit becomes unstable.
In fact this orbit is renal, a resonant
2.1.
It means that the grains of dusk in the
orbit,
in the ring, would go twice as fast, as
the moon.
And such a very resonant orbits become
unstable at the tidal forces.
And because of the chaotic motion that is
generated there, the matter is expelled.
And this is the origin of what is called
the Cassini division.
If you look at the rings of Saturn there
are some gaps.
And the most obvious gap is that one is
called the Cassini division.
And, it's also in fact this resonant orbit
effect, is also the origin of
some other of the gaps in the Saturn
rings, although not all of them.
Some of them are still not understood.
So, our first example of chaos is
concerned by resonance.
And by the fact that the grains of dust in
the
central orbit are always in the same
relative position with the moon.
They get the same kick all the time in the
same
direction, and at the end of the day they
will get.
Expelled from the stable motion that would
be the orbit.
A second example of closed system.
This one is clear, it's a bit, it's, it's
mathematical, but it is a clear image.
It's what is called the billiard.
And this is what is called Sinai's
billiard by
the name of the one, who started it
mathematically.
You see this is just the black dots are
just half spheres.
And there is a small body, a small ball
you can imagine, that impinges on them.
And is reflected without losing any
energy.
So is a conservative system, is just a
pure reflection.
The drawing that I have there illustrates
how Sinai's billiard is sensitive to
initial conditions.
You see two trajectories that are not very
different at the beginning.
They become very rapidly different.
They end up in completely different
positions.
An equivalent way of describing a Sinai's
billiard is just to
concentrate on a single sphere and enclose
it with a box.
So now the particle, there's only one, one
sphere, and
the particle will bounce between the
boundary and the sphere.
What happened there for some trajectories
of
course, very special ones, the motion is
periodic.
If I send the, the small ball
perpendicularly
on the sphere it just bounces back and
forth.
But for most trajectories, you see that
the motion becomes chaotic.
And in fact what happens is that almost
all trajectories end up filling the space.
At some point in time, you can find the
moving ball
at any position you want.
This property is called ergodicity in the
language of physicists.
And is a very important property in
thermodynamics in
statistical physics, when it comes to
describing big systems.
The third and last example of closed
system I want
to discuss is very famous is called the
kicked rotor.
It can be presented in many ways, I
presented it here as a stick.
Suspended by one of the ends.
And gets
periodically kicked at the other end.
You can sort of imagine what's going on,
again
you will find beautiful illustrations,
animations in the internet.
That if you kick at the right moment the
rotor will go around and
around and go even all the way up and fall
down on the other side.
If you kick at the wrong moment, the rotor
will stay more or less where it is.
I've written here for your information,
how to describe this system
in Physics?
There are two variables.
I, I've written P, the angular momentum,
sometimes written, I and theta, the angle.
Is similar to speed and position.
That's the kind of variables.
There is a continuous time evolution you
can write
down, there is a kinetic energy and
potential energy.
For those who know distinct's from those
two.
You can create
a Lagrangian or a Hamiltonian, that's why
it's called a Hamiltonian system.
There's also discretized map, that
describes
only what happens essentially at every
kick.
And is, written like that.
This looks more or less like our logistic
map.
It's called the standard map.
I think that the message has come across.
I don't think I have to present many more
examples of chaos.
please, I repeat again, browse the
internet and find them there.
There is also a very rich mathematical
theory behind all these for those who are
interested.
In the next segment I will rather move to
two topics that are related to chaos.
And the, just for the fun of it, just to
learn something that also related to our
topic of randomness.