Hello, welcome to the fifth lecture.
After four lectures devoted to
defining and characterizing and producing
randomness.
We are going to move to a different
perspective
which is the presence of randomness in our
world.
As you see the color of the lights change,
changed lightly.
And this particular lecture will be about
deterministic chaos.
The plan of the lecture is as follows.
We start
by speaking of physical determinism or
(in)determinism.
Then we devote three segments to the main
topic, which is deterministic chaos.
And the last segment the fifth will be
devoted to two related
topics, the beauty of factor curves and
the power of laws in statistics.
So let us start with physical determinism
or (in)determinism.
If you ask a physicist
in a few minutes, you will get the
following simple story.
That classical physics, the physics, let's
say until the
19th century included, is deterministic in
the sense of Laplace.
Remember the citation of Laplace that we
had
in the first lecture, where a being, that
an intelligence that would know everything
perfectly would
be able to predict the future without any
uncertainty.
I have to start that this is usually
identified with Newtonian physics, the
physics pioneered by Newton, but it
also included Einstein's relativity in
that sense.
Relativity is of course a big scientific
revolution
in many respects but not in this one.
It doesn't challenge the idea of
deterministic.
In fact, one may even say it's time
sensitive.
Then comes quantum physics, one of the,
the
second greatest discovery of physics in
the 20th century.
That is not deterministic, and
it's intrinsically random.
So this is the simple story, and at the
end of the day I will stick to it.
However, I want to mention that these begs
a few questions.
In fact it begs many questions.
Here is again, our simple model from
physics,
Classical physics - determinism; Quantum
physics - randomness.
What are the questions?
There are some questions about physics
itself.
For instance, the description, the simple
description,
Classical - deterministic.
Quantum - random is certainly correct,
when it come to the theory.
When it comes to describing the formalism,
the way mathematics are
done, the way physical phenomena are
described in a mathematical framework.
But what about nature?
For instance the fact that Quantum
Physics, Quantum theory sorry, is
random does it imply that there are really
Random Phenomena out there?
Or does it mean that this is just the best
theory we've
been able to come about with and maybe one
day someone will find something better
that is deterministic again.
Or on the contrary, is it possible that
everything is actually random.
So that Newtonian physics is deterministic
by accident.
That okay, we got a theory that looks
deterministic
but in fact everything out there is
completely unpredictable.
Then there are of course questions beyond
Physics,
or better said, does all this discussion
imply anything beyond Physics?
For instance, assuming you would conclude
to
physical determinism, which was the case
for
many centuries in Physics, of these
centuries,
would that imply lack of free will?
Or on the contrary if you now accept a, a
physical indeterminism of Quantum
Physics, isn't this a proof of free will?
In order to go deeper into
these topics, let me introduce what they
call the Conspiracy Theater.
It's the question that probably each of us
have asked a few times.
And humanities have asked a need for many
years, namely whether
everything that we observe with our senses
is in fact an illusion.
And we are just acting in a theater play
set up
by, let's see what are the options that
have been proposed.
Of course one of the options is theater
plays set
up by an all powerful God.
This is similar to the position that
Bishop
George Berkeley, the famous Irish
philosopher was upholding.
Although we have to say that in Berkeley's
philosophy the souls had some freedom.
It was only the physical world that was
illusion created by God.
But of course we can quote many other
people who may have a
much more deterministic view, even where,
even behaviour is determined in the play.
In the movie The Matrix, that you are
certainly familiar with, the human beings
that are prisoners
of their dreams are in fact playing in a
theater set up by robots, who have taken
control.
In some science fiction stories you can
find that we human beings and our world
is nothing else than a big computer
game being played by an alien superior
civilization.
Or you may just say that nobody
has really, no intelligence has really set
up these
theater, it's just the universe is
deterministic by itself.
This topics are very old and very famous
in the history of humanity, for instance
the
allegory of the cave by Plato, theater
Plays
like Life is a dream by Calderon dela
Varga.
And many others that can be quoted here,
brings up a similar idea.
Anyway, you understand what I'm speaking
about, let's see if someone who upholds
this view can be convinced by quantum
physics that this is wrong.
The answer is clearly not.
Obviously someone who has such a world
view, would not be
able to be convinced that this is wrong by
physics, by observation.
Why?
Well, simply because if, if you believe
that everything is a, a deterministic
play, even
the fact that we observe Quantum
Phenomena, and
that they look random to us, it's
predetermined.
So in fact such a world view cannot be
falsified.
Now, does it make sense to continue
following this lecture and speaking about
randomness?
It does.
Even if you believe in such a world view,
I don't, personally, but of course
I leave you free to believe in it, it
makes sense to speak of randomness.
because as usual, we have to specify for
whom the phenomenon is unpredictable.
Let us discuss that point.
Keep calm.
Let's not go too much excited about
philosophy.
Let's keep calm and ask, for whom it is
random?
So, if we are a being in our universe,
with limited computational power, then
that being cannot predict Quantum
Phenomena in
Physics, and cannot predict chaotic
Classical Phenomena.
If you take a being that is in our
universe but with
unlimited computational power, this would
be
the intelligence Laplace was speaking
about.
Then all Classical Phenomena would become
predictable but Quantum Phenomena would
not.
What happens if outside our we are
universe, in particular, outside out time.
A being in that situation, I would say it
does
not make sense to speak of prediction in
that case.
I thought this
being is just looking at our world and
then it's just passive vision.
Or that being is actually actively messing
up with our world
and this is would be decision and this
being is in control.
Now to be sure we are in the first
category
ourselves, we are in our universe and with
limited computational power.
So for us, both Quantum Phenomena and
chaotic Classical Phenomena are random.
Are unpredictable.
It's not impossible for us to imagine
being in
the place of the intelligence that Laplace
was speaking about.
In that case, we can understand that there
is a difference between Quantum Phenomena
and Classical Phenomena.
Its very hard to us to conceive what it
would
mean to be outside our universe and
outside our time.
So I will not deal with that option
anymore during these lectures.
Let's say it again.
What is Physical Determinism?
Is phenomena that can be predicted
with unlimited computational resources and
physical
(in)determinism, a phenomenon cannot be
predicted
with, even with unlimited computation or
resources.
So if a phenomenon is deterministic,
the information is already fully available
now.
It's just a matter of extracting it from
the present state of the universe.
Whereas an (in)deterministic phenomenon is
a
phenomenon that creates new information
the universe.
Nevertheless, some deterministic phenomena
may be unpredictable, if
we have limited resources, as we do have.
And this the case of deterministic case,
it will be the main topic of this lecture.
Let me just finish by analogy.
We have seen in lecture two, the security
of the
RSA protocol, and the security of the
one-time pad protocol.
You remember
the security of RSA was guaranteed under
computational assumptions of the power of
the historical.
The security of one time part is
guaranteed unconditionally.
It's similar to this distinction between
physical determinism,
but chaotic that cannot be predicted, and
physical indeterminism.