After having seen the biased coin let us
look to other
sources of randomness, weaker ones that
have correlations between the runs.
So if fair and biased coins are indeed
equally
grouped to generate randomness, as we have
just seen.
What can be possibly go wrong?
What other processes can there be that
look random or maybe are not?
And the problem is that there can be
correlations between the runs.
Let me take an extreme
example first.
Consider a process that can produce only
two sequences.
All zeroes or all ones.
And clearly there, once you have tossed
the coin once.
The future is fully predictable.
If you have seen a zero to be always zero.
If you have seen a one, it will be always
one.
This means that there is at most one bit
of randomness in that process.
And this independent of the length or a
sequence.
And conversely we have seen before that if
you toss uncorrelated coins, and
times the amount of randomness is
proportional to n, and grows, of course.
you get more randomness the more often you
toss a coin.
Here is the mathematical definition of
correlations.
Two random variables a and b are said
correlated if the
joint probability is different from the
product of the marginal probabilities.
So the marginal distribution is defined
there, is the sum
over all the possible values of the other
random variable.
An equivalent definition of correlation is
that the conditional probability
of a given b is not the same as just the
marginal probability of a.
When you apply this to sequences, a
sequence of runs
has correlations between the runs if the
result of the kth
run depends on the result of the previous
k minus one runs.
For some values of k at least, maybe for
all.
A favorite example for mathematicians and
physicists also is Markov chains.
A Markov chain is, the simplest process of
the type
I described before, in which the memory is
only one run.
So there's
only correlation with the result of taking
the previous run.
Let me give an example on Markov chain,
that by
far not the most general, but just to
drive ideas.
So, here is a process where the
probability of getting zero, if I had zero
before, or of getting one if I had one in
the run before is p.
And one minus p is the probability of
the other processes, namely of flipping
the bit.
Clearly,
these probabilities are different from the
individual
probabilities of observing one zero or one
one.
That are both 1/2.
Here is again this, this particular case
of Markov chain.
Let us see what happens in some extreme
cases.
If this probability p is close to one,
then you see the probability of flipping
is low.
So essentially once I have a zero I will
have a long string of zeros, and suddenly
maybe there is a flip, I go to one, and
then
there will be a long string of ones and so
on.
if the probability p, on the contrary, is
close
to zero, then the flipping, the
alternation is very frequent.
So there will be very short sequences,
sometimes three zeroes, but most of
the time, it's one or two zeros followed
by one one, and so on.
Clearly, this behavior, for instance, can
be
detected by looking at the statistics of
strings.
Although again, if you look at
the statistics only of single events, of a
zero or
of one, you will see that both are one
half.
Another example after Markov chains,
humans.
Maybe in the previous lectures or even at
the beginning of this one you
have been thinking the following question,
can
I just generate a random sequence myself.
After all, I'm not sure that I'm not
being influenced, so the process is really
random.
In fact it turns out that we humans are
bad random number
generators for a couple of reasons.
First of all of course, we are very slow.
We can produce approximately one bit per
second and this means one hertz of
rate of production of random numbers, but
most importantly we are not very random
either.
Because after saying, say a few zeroes, we
feel the need that we should create a one.
Now, a fair coin never feels such a
pressure of being forced
to produce a one.
In fact, experiments with humans show that
without warning, you can see a
difference between a fair coin and a human
being already with three bit sequences.
The sequences 000 and 111, would be
significantly less probable than the six
others that were two zeroes and one one or
two ones and one zero.
because now that you are warned, don't
fall on the other extreme.
Don't stop producing too long sequences at
in excess.
Here I want to remind you also that the
definition
of randomness is not that there is no
external influence.
Or that there is some form of free will.
That it is impossible to predict.
And clearly, you see here that with our
bias, with our
psychological bias we feel the need to, to
flip at some point.
It introduces some bias in favor of
predicting what's going to happen.
And of course one
can imagine all kind of correlations
beyond Markov
chains and beyond this memory effect of
humans.
Here are few examples that I just invented
to show you how things can go badly.
Consider for instance the following k's,
every k bits, the first k minus one
are fair coins, and the kth are just
binary sum of all the previous.
So here it's also detectable by
statistical tests but
it's going to be how to detect if the, if
k is large enough.
Another example.
You toss a fair coin one million times and
then you record
that sequence and just repeat the same
sequence over and over again.
This kind of regularity could be dangerous
for most applications, including for
instance Monte Carlo.
And maybe it's not that easy as well to
detect by statistical tests.
Yet another example, suppose take a
generator that generates
strings of increasing length.
As you see there there is one zero, two
ones, three zeroes, four
ones, five zeroes, five, six ones, seven
zeroes, eight ones and so on.
Here, approximated the probability of
finding a zero
is the same as probability of finding a
one.
But there is no randomness at all, in this
sequence.
So here's the message of this segment
about correlations.
First of all.
It's pretty
obvious, but keep in mind that it's not
because there are zeroes and ones that
it's random.
Second, a finite battery of statistical
tests would detect the
common correlations, but may easily fail
for more perverse ones.
And then we think what this perversion
comes from.
Normally, nature is not supposed to be
perverse.
And indeed we may not expect perversion
in, in, in some
natural phenomenons but they can come at
least in two possible situations.
One we can introduce them unwillingly.
The next segment we show an example of
such a problem.
Or remember that randoms is used
sometimes in adverse scenarios, for
instance cryptography.
And if you have an adversary out there
that's trying to cheat you.
It's all normal to consider this adversary
is behaving in a perverse way.