We conclude today's lecture with a balance
of the first three lectures.
We have seen that ignorance lead to
randomness, to lack of predictability.
In turn, lack of predictably may imply
lack of control.
This is the reason why we normally don't
feel very comfortable
with randomness, with unpredictability,
because we like to be in control.
However in some cases as we have seen
this feature enables us to do something
positive.
For instance, in the case of games, we can
hope that
the, the other players cannot bias the
odds in their favor.
Similarly randomness implies lack of
structure because
where there is structure it's easy to
predict.
And this is positively used in
optimizations, in tests, and
in polls in order to explore all of the
possibilities
without falling into our preconceptions.
Also, if the ignorance is not our
ignorance but the ignorance of
an adversary, randomness is the resource
that allows secrecy, cryptography to be
possible.
Very important questions.
Ignorance by whom?
And ignorance of what?
We have always to keep in mind that what
is unpredictable for me may not be
unpredictable for you.
In particular, I have stressed a few times
that, when it
comes to assessing randomness, there is
always an element of trust.
If the trust to be assessed is known
adversarial, the
trust will be something like, I have
performed a few tests.
And after performing them, I am confident
enough that there is no structure.
We have seen this bad example of RANDU,
this random number generator, if you
don't do enough statistical tests,
probably you
don't detect that this generator is bad.
In adversarial scenario, the element of
task is something
like, I trusted the key has not leaked
out.
The secrecy has not leaked out.
That the adversary has limited
computational power and similar.
This is all the important because you are
making assumptions
not on yourself but you are making
assumptions on someone else,
who is your enemy.
So it's all the more important to make
these assumptions carefully.
Another element that I was stressing is
the relation
between individuals and populations and in
particular the fact
that you can have a population behaving at
random
even if each individually is in fact
behaving deterministically.
For this is sufficient that you are not
monitoring the trait or the feature that
determines
the behavior.
And then in this case when you average
over the population you see that
there is a statistical, a mixed behavior,
whereas each individual is following very
precise instructions.
This can happen.
Finally, we have seen some sources of
randomness, especially those of the first
column.
The pseudo-random sources.
These are computational complicated
algorithms with some choice of a seed.
And we
have seen the linear congruential
generators in
which the seed is the just the first
number of a sequence and then all the
other numbers are generated by the
particular equation.
We have seen the linear feedback shift
registers.
We have also mentioned that it's probably
well-known to
all of you that you can use the computer
clock
to generate random numbers using as a seed
the
moment at which you touch a key on your
keyboard.
And so on.
There of course there are many others and
hopefully you have clicked on one
of these links that I gave you to find out
many more pseudo-random generators.
Then the other sources of true randomness
were true here
in inverted commas simply means that there
are unpredictable physical processes.
In these first three lectures I mentioned
only three, two of
them or a series of examples like coins
dice, and similar.
In the following lectures, we are going to
see a few more.
We're going to see noise and fluctuations
in the next lecture.
We're going to discuss chaos,
deterministic chaos in lecture five.
And lectures six and seven will be
devoted to quantum physics and its
intrinsical unpredictability.
So, thank you for listening to this
lecture, and see you next time.