Is now time to practice a little bit with
our first random number generators.
So, recall the idea of Monte Carlo
software testing.
For instance, if you want to sample the
parameters space at random.
So this means that your random number
generator should sort of fill the space.
And if you look at this field that I
brought in at some point with some random
number generator.
It looks pretty good.
However, you should not be fooled by it
because if you start rotating the
three-dimensional plot.
You see very clearly that in fact these
random numbers in these plot are aligning
15 planes.
So what's going on?
What's going on is that I've implemented
here one
of the most famous and ill conceived
random number generators.
It's called RANDU.
Here's the mathematical rules
that define it.
You take the previous number, you multiply
it by 65539.
And you take the remainder of the division
by two to the 31.
And this will be your new number.
So why is this supposed to be interesting?
Okay the two to the 31 was chosen.
Because computers have often 32-bits
registers.
So its a very convenient
number because 32 bits and not to exceed
these 32 bits.
And this has been chosen because this is
the closest
point number to two to the 16 which is
65536.
This random number generator is the one
that I used before.
It fails what is called the spectral test
for D equal three.
What it mean, you take triples of
consecutive numbers at each run.
You can create Xj and then you take Xj, Xj
plus one so in the next run Xj plus two,
and
in the next next run, you plot them in a
scatter plot.
And as you've just seen, they define
fifteen
two dimensional planes instead of filling
the whole space.
And this is related to what I was
mentioning
before that we can introduced unwillingly
some perverse correlations.
Things you wouldn't have thought of in
advance,
and certain people did not want to
implement this.
And you see how these random numbers
fall on place.
Let us see RANDU in action as I probably
did in MatLab.
So here is MatLab code.
I'm not a great programmer, so probably
can be done simpler.
But let me just show it to you.
I'm going to go use 10,000 random numbers
starting with initial value one.
This just a vector, where I'm going to
adjust the old values.
Here is the duration.
You see here the multiplication and
then taking the remainder, and this is
just the routine that arranges for
the plot this last instruction is the plot
of the scattering of the points.
So let us run the program.
And here is the plot.
Here you see a few of the random, of
the pseudo random numbers that are
produced by this algorithm.
You can see a few more if you go.
But, it's not particularly interesting.
And as you see, as you have seen already
before, the random numbers fall on planes.
Let us go back now to our Powerpoint
presentation.
Random numbers fall mainly in the planes.
This is the title of a paper by George
Marsaglia
where he mentioned, he noticed this
problem and mentioned it.
By the way, for those who don't know,
these citation reminds
us of a famous exercise in the movie My
Fair Lady,
where the protagonist is trying to form
this young lady to
become society lady, and trying to teach
her how to pronounce
correct English.
And the sentence there is, the rain in
Spain falls mainly in the plain.
And this lady's pronouncing something like
the
rine in spine falls minely in the plines.
And after many exercises she manages to
pronounce it correctly.
So anyways so this George Marsaglia wrote
a
paper with a remaind, reminder of these
famous movie.
RANDU is in fact the bad example par
excellence
quoted in all the main books on the
subject.
Although you may know recently that the
dual EC, where EC
stands for elliptical curves, is also
going to make history too.
This is the one that had the NSA back door
according to the latest media reports,
RANDU was widely used in the early 1970s,
and when it was used to
do some Monte Carlo optimizations.
So, because of these, some of the results
obtained in those years are supposed to be
doubtful.
What Marsaglia proved is that in fact the
problem of RANDU
is not only because of the specific values
that were chosen there.
Any random number generator of this form
is called linear congruential generator.
See you have the a that we had before.
Before we didn't have this c.
We had
the m.
But any of these random number generators,
pseudo-random number
generators, at some point, we fails a
spectral test.
Although sometimes the planes may not be
three-dimensional but higher dimensional,
so it would be hard maybe to show you on a
screen.
It's beautiful that RANDU fails in
three-dimensional, but anyway, all these
random
number generators are a bit faulty, when
it comes to Monte Carlo.
There are other designs I
will give you a list to browse at the end
of this, the segment.
I just want to present one that is used
now-a-days very often.
Not for Monte Carlo but for faster
generation of randomness.
Its called linear feedback shift
registers.
Here I have one with eight registers, so
in practice that would be 16 or 32.
So how does it go?
You put a sequence into it.
Here it is.
And then what you are going to do next is
to compute the, some function.
Here, just compute all function of some
bits, just to the last two.
And you are going to plug it in the first,
shifting all the others to the right.
So let's follow it here, so here the or of
these two is one, so I'm
going to put a new one here and shift all
the registers to the right, and
then you repeat again.
Here, of course, I didn't tell you before,
but here you're computing
the or of zero and zero, therefore the
result of this is zero.
And again, you shift previous sequence to
the right and so on.
Of course, it is some periodicity but it's
very often used in a point it's very
practical.