Hello, welcome to this sublecture, which
would be
devoted to the characterization of a
source of randomness.
It'll probably be the most mathematical
lecture of this course.
Please bear with me, I'll try to put some
examples here and there.
This is the plan.
It is to learn what are non-ideal sources,
and what one can do with them.
The first non-ideal source that we'll
mention is a bias coin.
Then, in the segment two and three I will
discuss other random sources.
Other weaker sources of randomness.
In segment four we'll discuss Min-entropy,
which is
the mathematical object that quantifies
the amount of randomness.
In the fifth segment we'll discuss the
notion of extraction.
The sixth segment of the lecture will
affect the balance
of the first three lectures before we move
on to physics.
So let us start with the biased coin, and
the message I
want to send across is that essentially a
biased coin is just
as useful as a fair coin.
So here is a definition of the biased
coin.
It is rather similar to the one of the
fair coin.
The alphabet is still two values, 0 and 1.
A single run, or a single toss of the
coin, should be partially unpredictable.
Remember that the, fair coin will be fully
unpredictable.
Still, it retains the feature that after
several runs must be uncorrelated.
So, what are the statistics in a single
run?
The probability of outputting 0 would be
level P, and just by
convention I've chosen that P is larger
than one-half, and the probability of
[UNKNOWN]
1 is 1 minus P which would be the for P
smaller than
one-half, which means that 0 is more
probable than 1 for this coin.
And in a sequence of runs, well it's
uncorrelated.
So you have to count how many zeroes there
are.
How many ones there are and then just
multiply those probabilities.
So each sequence that features k 0 and n
minus k once,
as the probability written there p to the
k, 1 minus p
to the power n minus k.
As we did for the fair coin, let's look
into the statistics of sequences of bits.
So the probability of having k 0's and n
minus k 1 in a sequence is given
as before by the number of sequences of
this
property times the probability of each of
these sequences.
Each of the sequences are equally
probable, as
we have just seen, so this is just
multiplication
of the number of sequences times their
individual probabilities.
And one can check it's not very difficult
mathematics.
I am not, I'm not going to do it.
That the maximal value here is when k is
equal to n times p approximately.
Because p is not necessarily an integral,
so n times it might not be an integral.
Essentially it means that long sequences
will have almost certainly n times
p 0 and n times 1 minus p once which is
what you expect in average.
Nevertheless, I want to stress here and we
come back later
that the single most probable sequence is
the sequence of all 0's.
Because the probability of that one is p
to the n.
So if you were to bet on a specific
sequence.
This is the one that you have to choose.
Now, let us consider our first example of
extraction.
The question is can one simulate a fair
coin with a biased one?
I have a biased coin and I want to obtain
some statics of a fair coin out of it.
This is what is called the von Neumann
extraction.
It goes like this.
Here is a sequence.
First you group the bits by pairs.
And if this is a biased coin the pairs 1,0
and
0,1 have the same probability, which is p
times 1 minus p.
The pair 0,0
has probability p squared.
The pair 1,1 has probability 1 minus p
squared.
Then you discard the pair 0,0 and 1,1, and
you keep the pair 0,1 and 1,0.
0,1 is replaced by 0, 1,0 is replaced by
1, by the first bit.
That's it.
And now the new list that you have got is
of course shorter.
The average length it would be n times p
times 1 minus p,
instead of n.
So approximately one quarter of n is p is
not very far from one half.
But now is a fair coin because in this new
list the
probability of 0 and the probability of 1
are exactly one half.
So this way we see that if you have a
biased coin
upto tossing it a few more times, we can
simulate a fair coin.
Now I'm going to ask the opposite
question.
Can I simulate a biased coin
with a fair one?
So for instance I want, I have a fair coin
only
and I want to simulate a coin where the
probability is 0.75.
Of 0.
The probability of 0.
What is not valid is the
[UNKNOWN]
written here.
Toss the coin.
If you see 1, discard it with probability
2 3rds.
This of course would give the right
probabilities if you, you can check it.
But this assumes that you can choose.
To discuss something with probability
[UNKNOWN].
It assumes that you have another coin,
biased already, with probability 2 3rds.
Here we are assuming that we have only the
fair coin.
There's no other source of randomness
available.
Not even your intellect if you want, not
even your choices on your brain.
Still, this can be done.
And here is a
[INAUDIBLE].
Again here's a bit mathematics so, be
careful.
We compute first the binary decimal
expansion of the probability.
So here's the probability p.
And we express p in powers of 1 over 2 to
the k, times some coefficient, 0 or 1.
Let me give an example.
The simplest one possible is 0.75.
Is 1 times one half plus 1 times 1
quarter.
This already 0.75.
So then 0 times 1 8th, 0 times 1 16th, 0
times 1 over 32 and so on.
So the, this vector of qs of 0.75 is
just 1, 1 followed by an infinite sequence
of 0s.
So now I have the binary decimal
expression of p equal to 0.75.
In the next step, here it will becomes a
bit
complicated, is toss the coin, the fair
coin and you do the following thing.
If you see 0 and your q was 1, you
output 0 and start again at the beginning
of the least.
If you see a 1 and your q was 0, you
output 1.
If your coin, and the q of the list are
the
same, you do nothing and you move to the
next step
in the list and toss again.
So now why this procedure works?
Let's compute the probability of finding
0.
And let's check that indeed this
probability is p.
Here is the formula, I am going for it.
First, you toss the coin k minus 1 times,
and in all these first tosses the coin and
the q list are exactly the same.
Then at some point, you toss the coin and
the coin and the q list
are different.
At this time you stop and you output
either 0 or 1.
So when do you output 0?
You output 0 when q was 1 and the coin was
0.
So this is the probability of outputting
And as you see, indeed, these, compare
this formula
here with the formula up here, it's
exactly the same.
So this is the definition of p.
As a result, the probability of getting 0
is exactly p if you
do this procedure.
So let me summarize.
If you have a biased coin.
You can get a fair coin by extraction.
And this is possible in infinite time.
Essentially the time is 1 over remember
this ratio that we had between
the length of the initial list and the
length of the final test.
If you have a fair coin, you can go to a
biased coin also in finite time.
This is the kind of time you can think
about it.
If that was my assumption, the binary
decimal expansion of p can be computed
efficiently.
So if the value qk can be
efficiently computed in, efficiently
remember means polynomial, so
it can be computed in a time k to the
power c, for some constant c.
This is not true for all values of p.
So if you want to simulate a coin, if the
value
of p is not efficiently computable, it's
going to be difficult.
But apart from this detail,
the two resources, fair coin and biased
coin are basically equivalent.