After seeing some examples of random
number generation.
Now I'm going to present the mathematical
tool
that quantifies the amount of randomness,
its called
[UNKNOWN].
So how much randomness do we have?
Clearly a very good quantifier is the
guessing probability.
Here it is how its defined.
If you are asked to bet on a particular
sequence to be drawn.
Which one would you guess?
Obviously the best choice is to guess for
the sequence with the largest probability.
There is no reason to bet on any other
sequence.
So the point of guessing is defined as the
maximum of all,
over all possible sequences of the
probability of that particular sequence.
Now these probability of guessing have
two unpleasant features a quantifier of
randomness.
The first one is that, of course, the
larger Pguess, the smallest the amount of
randomness.
So it's inversely related to randomness.
And indeed, if you have the probability of
guessing equal to one, it means no
randomness.
Second is take the random the fair coin,
if you
toss it n times, it will give n random
bits.
But the probability of guessing is changes
like one over two to the n.
So you want to get this n out and we've
already done it in the first lecture.
We just take minus log to of the
probability of guessing.
This quantity is called min-entropy.
Why is it called min-entropy is
because in, there is a family of
mathematical objects called entropies.
It's part of also information theory and
bio-thermodynamics.
They're called Renyi entropies, and this
family
is the one that gives the minimal value
among all the others, for any given
probability
distribution that, that where the name
comes from.
But it doesn't really matter where the
names comes from, because what we
care is that this is a good quantifier of
the amount of randomness.
Notice again as we have done
in the first lecture that since we take
the
logarithm in base two, the unit of
min-enthropy is bit.
So I'm going to speak of 10 bits
of min-enthropy, n bits of min-enthropy,
and so on.
Here are some examples.
The fair coin.
The probability of guessing one or two to
the n.
Sequence, which sequence, or any.
All the sequences of the probabilities so
in the case
of fair coin you can just guess your
favorite sequence.
And this leads to a min-entropy of n bits.
The biased coin, the probability of
guessing these
p to the power n, I must assume in
here that p is larger than one half,
the sequence corresponding to that
probability is all zeroes.
So the min-entropies, the log of this
number which is minus the log
of this number, which is n times log two
of one over p.
Which is clearly smaller than n if p is
larger than one half.
Which, which we are assuming, n is 0 in
particular if p is equal to one.
The Markov examples that I gave, remember
it was
not an arbitrary Markov chain but a
specific one.
Still, the probability of guessing is p to
the power n because,
this would be the probability of guessing
either the sequence 00000 or 11111.
So the min-entropy is the same number of
bits.
Now
I want to refine a little bit the
definition.
Because, remember that randomness is
ignorance.
So it is not really the observed
probability distribution that
matters, but the probability of guessing
conditions to someone's knowledge.
Let me give a few examples before writing
down a formula.
The toss of the coin maybe unpredictable
for me, so to me the coin looks random.
But it may be predictable for someone who
is able to describe the motion
of my finger and of the air molecules and
of course of the coin exactly.
So for that person, the coin, the physical
coin is not random.
In cryptography, remember that the seed or
a
key should be random for Eve, not for
Alice.
If Alice and Bob remember the citing of
cryptography do not agree on the key.
Nothing can happen.
The important
thing is that they must be sure that the
key is not known, is random.
To Eve, to eaves dropper.
So in fact what is useful for randomness.
In general is what is called conditional
min-entropy, which
is the logarithm of the maximum
probability of guessing given
some information that I have written here
for Eve,
but it can be the, the information that
care for.
This is the number that will quantify the
randomness,
as seen by this person.
What is even more important is that the
min-entropy has what is called an
operational interpretation.
And now I introduce to you this notion let
me first
recall what we saw before with the biased
coin von Neumann extraction.
From a sequence of n bits of biased coin,
there was a procedure.
So, it's like the sequence of all the n
bits
of a fair coin.
On average, it was np times one minus p.
And now there is this very famous theorem
that has
the beautiful name of, Leftover hash
lemma, proved in 1989.
That says the following, if I have a
sequence of bits n, with min-entropy given
by some value, there exists an extraction
procedure that allows you to get m bits
of a fair coin where m is exactly
quantified by the min-entropy.
So in other words, the min-entropy is the
amount
of ideal randomness that is present in
your sequence.
And it can be extracted out of the initial
data.
It's remarkable it can be extracted.
We are going to devote the next section to
extraction.