Let us finish this lecture.
I remind you that sixth segment would be
more of a balance
of the first three lectures by practicing
this notion of extraction of randomness.
So here is, again, the leftover
[UNKNOWN].
If I have a sequence of n bits of given
min-entropy.
I can extract a sequence of m shorter m
bits,
m equal to the same min-entropy of a fair
coin.
Now, this is a very strong claim, because
the claim is that
this is possible without any other
information about the random number
generator.
Example, let's suppose that the
min-entropy
is 0.1 times 10, what can that be?
What forces it could be a source that
produces one fair-coin bit
and then replicates it nine times before
tossing the fair coin again.
Or, it could be a source that behaves like
a fair coin 10% of the time.
For instance in the first six minutes of
each hour,
and then for the rest of the hour just
produces 0's.
Of course it gives a very different
sequence
from the previous one.
Or it could be a biased, uncorrelated coin
with a suitable probability, such
as when you take the log it gives the 0.1,
and so on.
So how are we going to do an
extraction in practice without knowing
which mechanism is behind?
In fact, the way of doing it was called a
strong extraction.
And here is the idea.
We have this initial sequence of length n,
and min-entropy m is more than n.
We want to extract a sequence of length
m, with min-entropy also m, which means
fair coin.
The extractor will be just a matrix field
with n times m random bits.
So all these elements of the matrix mij
would be zeroes or ones.
So you need a fair coin.
And it seems that this defeats the
purpose.
If I already have a fair coin, why
would I bother extracting randomness from
a imperfect source?
I just used the fair coin to produce my
randomness.
But that's not so simple.
And we have to think about cryptography.
What does it mean?
Remember also this notion of conditional
min-entropy.
What does it mean that we are trying to
extract
randomness in cryptography?
We have some initial list shared by Alice
and Bob but they are partly comprised.
It means the min-entropy of those lists
given
the information of Eve is m smaller than
n.
So you see Eve here has some information.
For instance, she knows exactly the second
bit.
She doesn't know the fourth and the eighth
but
she knows exactly the x4, the binary sum
of the
2, and so on.
So now what you, at least what I would
like to do,
is to get a shorter list but in which Eve
has no clue.
And now where is the coin that is used to
generate the extractor?
Well, the coin can be in Bob's hand.
It doesn't need to be secret.
It would be certainly uncorrelated from
Eve's attack.
Let me be more precise on this.
So Eve, when Alice and Bob were sharing
their secret,
she managed to compromise a little bit.
But the way she attacked, the kind of
information she got, is
certainly not correlated with how Bob is
going to toss his coin.
So in particular, Bob can even reveal
publicly which extractor he is using.
Eve can try to apply it to her data, but
it will not
help her as I am going to show you in the
next slide.
And as a result,
once the extractor is applied, Alice and
Bob come up with
the same list, but now Eve has no
information about that list.
How can we be sure that Eve has no
information about that list?
So here's intuitions.
Take a very simple example.
Suppose that we have a list of six beads,
and Eve knows
a3 exactly and nothing else, and we create
our extractor at random.
Then let's see what happens in b.
So b1 will be the product of this line
times this color, this vector.
You see, in this line at position three
there is a zero.
So the a3 would not even contribute,
doesn't know nothing a3 in b1.
So Eve cannot know anything about b1.
Similarly here, Eve cannot know anything
about b2.
What about b3?
Well here there is a one.
So a3 the, the bit that Eve knows will
be picked up, but it would be summed with
a2 because of this one.
And a2 is unknown to Eve.
So the sum a2 plus a3 would look random to
Eve because a2 is random.
And similarly, for the fourth line, for
b4, again, a3 would be picked up,
but it would be summed with a1, a4, and
a5,
and again, Eve would have no information
at the end.
So in this very trivial example, Eve would
know one
of the bits in the final list bk, if and
only if the kth line of the extractor has
zeroes
everywhere, and a one only on the b that
she knows.
This is the kind of intuition that since
it's improbable to draw this kind
of line for the extractor, Eve will have
little or no information about the final
result.
Of course this must be made much more
rigorous in general and not for
a specific example, but that's the kind
of intuition behind drawing the matrix at
random.
So let me recapitulate, because it's
probably a lot of notions that this cannot
view in this short period of time.
If I only had one source of randomness,
like a biased coin, like a macro chain, or
like one of these mobile versed ones.
One needs to know its structure in order
to perform possibly some extraction.
Example, if you know that it's
uncorrelated as we knew before, then
we can do the von Neumann extraction
without even knowing the probability p.
The highest coin, if it's trusted or
known to be uncorrelated, will always be
extractable
with the von Neumann procedure.
If I don't know anything about the
structure, I need
to add a coin or some other source of
randomness.
And if I do that I can extract randomness
from
any source, knowing or trusting only the
value of H min.
Remember that in a way or another, you
need to know what the min-entropy is.
If you don't know how much Eve has
comprised your source,
for instance, you cannot extract anything
because Eve potentially might know
everything.
You must be able to bound somehow the
knowledge of the eavesdropper or the lack
of randomness.
In cryptography you just would extract
your secret using a coin so
then, you see, I've already said it but
let's phrase it again.
What you want to extract has the
additional value of being secret.
And you're extracting with a coin that is
just random, but is not secret.
So that's why you want to do it.
Now if you are non, in a non-cryptographic
scenario,
for instance if only Bob trying to access
some randomness, you can also
think that the, that the random bits of
the matrix are not spoiled.
You can use them again.
And you got m more bits coming from the
imperfect source.
So it may still be useful in some cases to
perform an extraction.
Even if it is not a cryptographic scenario
and you have a fair coin in your pocket.
I must make a remark that, of course all
the rigorous versions
of these results are statistical.
They sound something like this.
If you can afford failing your extraction,
or
your secrecy with probability epsilon, you
can extract fair
coin of length m which is the h min,
the min-enthropy minus a correction that
depends on espilon.
Now is this a bad news, well, let's check.
Let's put epsilon 10 to the minus 9.
It means I can afford to fail one every
billion trials.
Then this log of 1 over epsilon is 30.
It means I lose 30 bits out of my
min-entropy.
Imagine that the list m and n are all the
all the millions of billions.
Its 30 bits really don't matter too much.
So of course, when you do the mathematical
theory correctly you have to include these
corrections.
But they are not really dangerous and they
don't
change the message, which is you can
perform an extraction.
Let me finish with a summary of lecture
three.
We reviewed some non-ideal sources and
what one can do with them.
We have seen some specific examples of
weaker sources of randomness, the biased
coin.
Some sources with correlations,
specifically the Markov chain,
our human random number generators and a
few others.
And then we discuss more in detail some
bad or
less bad examples like RANDU and the
linear feedback shift registers.
Then we discuss min-entropy as the
quantifier of the amount of randomness.
And we stressed how this is an operation
and interpretation in that,
it defines how much randomness can be
extracted from a weak source.
And finally we went through some of these
extraction procedures.